<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Tue, 02 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Fuck trees, use tags
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-02-fuck-trees-use-tags
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-02-fuck-trees-use-tags?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 02 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>We&#39;ve been trained to organize our files into a tree-like structure. A file can only exist once in the entire tree. It may have multiple contexts, but it can only exist once. Here&#39;s an example: you get a really important invoice for your car that you have to keep for your taxes. Where do you store this invoice alongside your other files?</p>

<ul><li>Maybe organized by type:<code>/invoices/important_invoice.pdf</code>?</li><li>Or <code>/tax/2024/important_invoice.pdf</code> since that&#39;s where you will probably need it next?</li><li>But it&#39;s an invoice for my car! So <code>/vehicles/&lt;licenseplate&gt;/important_invoice.pdf</code>?</li></ul>

<p>Whatever strategy you choose, there are probably times where you wish to have used a different directory structure. Sure, you can put the file in one directory and then create a shortcut or link in the other directories, but the original file will only ever exist in one place.</p>

<p>I believe that these tree-like directory structures are inherently flawed, and that tagging systems are superior in almost every way.</p>

<p>What I mean by tags is to organize files/entities/whatever into a flat structure and add meaningful tags/labels to add context. To revise the example above: our <code>important_invoice.pdf</code> could have the following tags:</p>

<ul><li><code>invoice</code></li><li><code>vehicles/&lt;licenseplate&gt;</code></li><li><code>tax/2024</code></li></ul>

<p>One could argue that <code>vehicles</code> and <code>tax</code> could be their own tags, but I specifically choose these tags to prove an important point:</p>

<h2>Tags can mimic trees</h2>

<p>If you think about it, a file path in a sense is just a reference to some location. Files on a physical hard drive aren&#39;t organized in trees. They&#39;re a bunch of ones and zeros slapped together in a pool of other files. A file path is just an abstraction for the user to reference a specific location in this pool of files. A file path is a tag!</p>

<p>Unfortunately, most systems are designed to only allow one path per file. This creates the hierarchical structure we so often use. But as I mentioned above, we could simply assign multiple tags or paths to a single file to organize it in multiple ways. The <code>important_invoice.pdf</code> has little to do with <code>tax</code> or <code>2024</code> as standalone terms, but assigning the tag <code>tax/2024</code>  gives it a similar meaning as a path to a file in a directory. The term <code>invoice</code> is enough to infer that everything using this tag is an invoice. It&#39;s equivalent to having a directory named <code>invoices</code> with multiple files inside.</p>

<p>So, we have established that tags are easily superior to trees. Why are we not using them?</p>

<h2>Tags have bad UX</h2>

<p>There have been many attempts at giving users the possibility to organize their stuff using tags. Your Gmail mails can be labeled, you can use tags for files in MacOS and there are apparently even efforts to create <a href="https://relfs.sourceforge.net/">tag-based filesystems</a>. But none of them were good enough to change the game.</p>

<p>Our brains seem to be so used to the idea of a piece of information only existing at one location at a time that it&#39;s really hard to adapt at this point. I&#39;m sure there are some power users out there who make the most of the limited tagging features of their systems, but what I would really like to see is a real shift in how we store and retrieve information.</p>

<h2>Discussion</h2>

<p>This post has spark some interesting discussion on <a href="https://lobste.rs/s/pssbmx/fuck_trees_use_tags">Lobsters</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Toil
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-01-toil
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-01-toil?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>After cheating death himself, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sisyphus">Sisyphus</a> was punished to push a large boulder up a steep hill for eternity. Every time he reached the top, the boulder would roll back down and Sisyphus had to start over.</p>

<p>Our life is full of such toil. Mowing the lawn, cleaning the dishes and doing our taxes are examples of toil that prevents us from doing sustainable work. We should always seek to minimize toil where possible. We have dishwashers and spam filters to help us fight toil, but there are some reoccurring tasks that cannot be automated.</p>

<p>Sisyphus eventually found peace with his fate. Instead of seeing his punishment as an eternal burden, he saw it as his life&#39;s purpose. Maybe those comparatively small annoyances in our life are worth enjoying. They&#39;re part of what makes us human.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Dive Log: Vietnam
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>So, after our <a href="/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket">adventures in Phuket</a>, we journeyed on to Nha Trang in Vietnam, where we also went diving.</p>

<p>Unfortunately the visibility was average, and the wildlife in Nha Trang wasn&#39;t as diverse as in Phuket, but that only made the hermit crabs or the occasional lionfish feel just that much more special.</p>

<p>In total, we did 4 dives in Nha Trang. Here&#39;s a full list, taken from my logbook:</p>

<p>| Title       | Date       | Site       | Depth (m) | Time (min) | Highlights                   |
| ----------- | ---------- | ---------- | --------- | ---------- | ---------------------------- |
| Nha Trang 1 | 2024-02-25 | Dam Bay    | 12        | 45         | Cold water and sandy bottom  |
| Nha Trang 2 | 2024-02-25 | Mot Island | 13.5      | 45         | Squids and lots of anemones  |
| Nha Trang 3 | 2024-02-26 | Tam Island | 11.2      | 37         | Playing around with bouyancy |
| Nha Trang 4 | 2024-02-26 | Tam Island | 10        | 46         | Hermit crabs                 |</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Dive Log: Phuket
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just became a certified diver! 🥳</p>

<p>I got my license through the <a href="https://rumblefishadventure.com/">Rumblefish Adventure</a> divecenter in Kata Beach, as per a recommendation from a friend who happened to be around in the area when we were there.</p>

<p>Kata Beach is a great dive spot. It has crazy wildlife, it&#39;s just a short swim away from the beach and the visibility is quite good if you haven&#39;t seen many reefs yet (like myself).</p>

<p>After doing our PADI Open Water license, we went to Phi Phi Islands to do a fun dive. The experience swimming through the reefs there can simply not be put into words.</p>

<p>In total, we did 7 dives in Thailand. Here&#39;s a full list, taken from my logbook:</p>

<p>| Title                 | Date       | Site              | Depth (m) | Time (min) | Highlights                                         |
|-----------------------|------------|-------------------|-----------|------------|----------------------------------------------------|
| Open Water Training 1 | 2024-02-16 | Kata Beach        | 6.4       | 39         | First time seeing the reef!                        |
| Open Water Training 2 | 2024-02-18 | Kata Beach        | 10.9      | 62         | Almost finished all mandatory training             |
| Open Water Training 3 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 16.3      | 44         | Artificial reefs with lots of interesting wildlife |
| Open Water Training 4 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 12.9      | 48         | Even more crazy wildlife                           |
| Phi Phi Islands 1     | 2024-02-20 | Koh Bida Nok      | 20.5      | 51         | Sharks!                                            |
| Phi Phi Islands 2     | 2024-02-20 | Turtle Rock       | 17.6      | 55         | Turtles, Sharks, Cave                              |
| Phi Phi Islands 3     | 2024-02-20 | Shark Point       | 20.4      | 46         | Lots of verticality                                |</p>

<h2>Photos</h2>

<p><img alt="P2170670 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1d00d17d-a889-417d-a4c9-8dd83eff58f9"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170752 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d3b80e60-2155-481f-8232-a5a57b3898ab"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170727 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/25e75fb1-dec7-4ad2-89a9-d929144cd60a"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170759 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1f9c2c0f-cc2e-440a-9bba-2a03c984f301"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180898.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/7f33d8a9-1d5f-4f94-87de-6078233be6a8"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180901.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/e1caf403-4ea2-4dce-a48c-1a0b5b5ce360"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180859.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/6fe5e666-0099-445f-bdcc-35bc0e5e9943"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170749 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d6a239a8-fb98-478a-9e38-d15e3587a7b4"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180837 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/50fe5c89-f1cb-4a73-aac0-f1311a3116fc"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170733 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d44f52a2-2228-4a3e-801d-930f0eddf975"/></p>

<p>After Phuket, we went to Vietnam where we&#39;re currently also on a lot of fun diving trips. But I&#39;ll save that for another dive log post.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Cosmic Horror: The Festival
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-10-cosmic-horror-the-festival
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-10-cosmic-horror-the-festival?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 10 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&quot;The nethermost caverns are not for the fathoming of eyes that see; for their marvels are strange and terrific. Cursed the ground where dead thoughts live new and oddly bodied, and evil the mind that is held by no head.&quot;</p><p>— H.P. Lovecraft</p></blockquote>

<p>I loved reading <a href="https://www.hplovecraft.com/writings/texts/fiction/f.aspx">The Festival</a> by H.P. Lovecraft, especially this quote by &quot;the mad Arab&quot; at the end of the story. The Festival is one of Lovecrafts first short stories in the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cthulhu_Mythos">Cthulhu Mythos</a>. The quote excellently shows the unique style of Lovecrafts short stories. Each story is a grotesque depiction of horrors that are beyond our imagination. I recently tried to replicate this style of writing in  &quot;<a href="/posts/2023-09-10-short-story-haunted-memories">Haunted Memories</a>&quot;, a short story about digital media. I&#39;m just getting started with reading Lovecrafts stories, but the ones I read so far absolutely blew me away.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                To prove something is true, try disproving it first
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-30-to-prove-something-is-true-try-disproving-it-first
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-30-to-prove-something-is-true-try-disproving-it-first?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>We&#39;ve been taught that, to prove that a thing is true, we should point out what&#39;s true about it.</p>

<p>However, we can learn much more about why something is true by trying to <strong>disprove</strong> it first. If you think something is true, try as hard as you can to prove that it&#39;s false.</p>

<p>Disproving a theory is core to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_method">scientific method</a>. Only when we validate that something cannot be false, we come closer to proving that it&#39;s true.</p>

<h2>Source</h2>

<p>&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vKA4w2O61Xo?si=2dtApWo8JmHOwqff&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Cost per Request
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-18-cost-per-request
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-18-cost-per-request?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 18 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>When monitoring infrastructure, we often use metrics like &quot;Requests per second&quot; or &quot;Time per request&quot;.</p>

<p>Contrary to that, when monitoring the cost of our infrastructure, we often only review the cloud bill at the end of the month and tell ourselves that those costs are justified for our product.</p>

<p>What if we made &quot;Cost per request&quot; a key metric in our observability strategy, alongside &quot;Requests per second&quot;?</p>

<p>If we follow that path even further, we could derive a standard for how much a request should cost for x% of uptime, across the entire industry. This way, we should be able to identify how much we&#39;re overspending for our infrastructure compared to other companies or products.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                A better publishing workflow for static blogs
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-06-a-better-publishing-workflow-for-static-blogs
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-06-a-better-publishing-workflow-for-static-blogs?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 06 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it">post</a> celebrating the completion of my <code>#100DaysToOffload</code> challenge, I teased that &quot;I built myself a handy script that turns the contents of a GitHub issue into a pull request, ready to be merged as a blog post&quot;. I didn&#39;t believe this was such a big deal, but a couple of readers actually reached out to me to ask about this.</p>

<p>First, some background. My site is built using a static site generator (not that it matters, but I use <a href="https://nextjs.org/">Next.js</a>). The beauty of using a SSG is that every blog post is literally just a markdown file in <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/tree/main/content/posts">a directory</a>. </p>

<h2>The story so far</h2>

<p>Before coming up with an automation, I had to</p>

<ol><li>Copy an older post to a new file</li><li>Rename the file</li><li>Fix the metadata/frontmatter</li><li>Delete the contents of the post</li><li><strong>Write the actual post</strong></li><li>Commit the file</li></ol>

<p>Putting out content on my blog involved quite a bit of friction. I felt like there was a barrier between my thoughts and the blog.</p>

<h2>The solution</h2>

<p>I&#39;ve been looking into how I could solve this issue for quite some time. I even had thoughts to build a custom blogging backend that would commit files to the <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz">repository</a>, which is of course quite silly.</p>

<p>But then it struck me: GitHub issues fully support markdown! The idea was born:</p>

<ol><li>Open an issue in the repository of this blog</li><li>Write the post</li><li>Kick off an automation that takes the content of the issue and dumps it in a new file</li><li>Create a pull request to generate a preview of the post</li><li>Merge the PR once I&#39;m done reviewing the post</li></ol>

<h2>So, how does the automation work?</h2>

<p>The magic lies in <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/blob/main/.github/workflows/publish_via_issue.yaml">this GitHub Action</a>. It is kicked off whenever the <code>action:publish</code> label is added to an issue.</p>

<p>If for some reason this link will not be there anymore in the future, this is the action as of the time of writing:</p>

<p>&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Expand me!&lt;/summary&gt;</p>

<p><code></code>`yaml
on:
  issues:
    types: [labeled]</p>

<p>name: Publish issue as post
jobs:
  publish-issue:
    if: github.event.label.name == &#39;action:publish&#39;
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    env:
      POST<em>BODY: &#39;${{ github.event.issue.body }}&#39;
    steps:
      - uses: actions/checkout@v4
      - name: Create commits
        run: |
          export POST</em>DATE=$(date +&quot;%Y-%m-%d&quot;)
          export POST<em>TITLE=&quot;${{ github.event.issue.title }}&quot;
          export POST</em>TAGS=$(echo &quot;${{ join(github.event.issue.labels.<em>.name, &#39;, &#39;) }}&quot; | grep -o &#39;tag:[^,]</em>&#39; | cut -d: -f2- | paste -sd &quot; &quot; - | sed &#39;s/ /, /g&#39;)
          export FILE<em>TITLE=$(printf &quot;$POST</em>TITLE&quot; | tr -cs &#39;[:alnum:]&#39; &#39;-&#39; | tr &#39;A-Z&#39; &#39;a-z&#39; | sed &#39;s/--/-/g&#39; | sed &#39;s/^-\|-$//g&#39;)
          export FILE<em>NAME=&quot;$POST</em>DATE-$FILE<em>TITLE.md&quot;
          export FULL</em>PATH=&quot;content/posts/$FILE_NAME&quot;
          git config user.name &#39;Publish Bot&#39;
          git config user.email &#39;publish-bot@github.com&#39;</p>

<pre><code>      cat &lt;&lt; EOF &gt; $FULL_PATH
      ---
      title: &quot;$POST_TITLE&quot;
      date: &quot;$POST_DATE&quot;
      tags: &quot;$POST_TAGS&quot;
      ---

      EOF

      echo &quot;$POST_BODY&quot; &gt;&gt; $FULL_PATH

      git add $FULL_PATH
      git commit -m &quot;Publish $POST_TITLE&quot;

  - name: Create Pull Request
    uses: peter-evans/create-pull-request@v5
    with:
      title: &quot;New Post: ${{ github.event.issue.title }}&quot;
      body: &quot;Closes #${{ github.event.issue.number }}.\n\n This PR has been generated automatically.&quot;
  - uses: actions-ecosystem/action-remove-labels@v1
    with:
      labels: action:publish</code></pre>

<p><code></code>`</p>

<p>&lt;/details&gt;</p>

<p>So, when I&#39;m done writing the post, I simply label the issue as <code>action:publish</code>, and the action turns it into a new file, commits it and ultimately opens a PR for me to review. You can see this in action by looking at <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/issues/432">the issue for this post</a>. The action also handles tags for blog posts. You can see that there are a bunch of labels on the issues that correspond to the tags of this post.</p>

<p>One additional benefit of using a static site generator is that I can generate a preview site for each pull request. So, once I&#39;m done writing and the pull request is generated, I can just wait for Netlify to build the preview to read the blog post as if it is published to the site! This is very helpful for spotting typos or formatting issues, especially if I&#39;m writing a post on my phone.</p>

<h2>Further improvements</h2>

<p>There are two things the current setup is lacking:</p>

<p>Firstly, GitHub doesn&#39;t really highlight typos when writing an issue. I&#39;m sure there are ways to address this post-publish, I just didn&#39;t get around to doing that yet.</p>

<p>Secondly, there&#39;s no sustainable way to add images to the repository this way. I have an <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/tree/main/public/assets">assets directory</a> where I put all my images for blog posts. You can paste images directly into the issue, which is really handy, but that generates a permalink on a GitHub CDN, somewhere that I don&#39;t control. For the future, it would be nice to teach the GH action to take these images and dump them into the asset directory.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Using this workflow, I can pump out ideas whenever and whereever I feel like it. It drastically reduced the time from idea to written article, which helps me organize my thoughts a lot better. I also frequently create drafts for things I want to write about but is not fully fleshed out yet.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Greg, the Developer
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 05 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This is Greg. Greg loves to play with his computer and create amazing things.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg.svg"/></p>

<p>Greg has many friends. He listens to his friends and helps them. Greg knows that teamwork is very important.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg and his friends" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-friends.svg"/></p>

<p>Greg is curious about what his friends do. Greg learned how they help everyone create amazing things. Greg was happy that he learned something new.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg learns from his friends" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-learning.svg"/></p>

<p>One day, Greg has an idea. Greg shares his idea with his friends. They try it, and it works! Everyone is happy that Greg shared his idea.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg has an idea" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-idea.svg"/></p>

<p>When Greg learns something new about computers, he writes it down and shows it to his friends. This helps everyone learn how computers work.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg writes down what he learned" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-documentation.svg"/></p>

<p>Sometimes Greg and his friends make a mistake, but Greg knows that&#39;s okay. Everyone makes mistakes, even Greg. He says that everyone can learn from mistakes. This makes them better and happier.</p>

<p><img alt="It&#39;s okay to make mistakes" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-mistake.svg"/></p>

<p>Greg is a good software developer. Be like Greg.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg is a good software developer" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-okay.svg"/></p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Temporal vs. fundamental content
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just read <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38829907">this comment</a> on a thread on HackerNews which resonated with me:</p>

<blockquote><p>I&#39;m trying to read less temporal (things that matter now) and more fundamental (stuff that mattered 1+ year ago and will still matter in 1+ year, with even wider intervals for non-tech content).
This does result in missing ~important things occasionally (e.g. I still don&#39;t know what happened with SamA at OpenAI, and yes, I am curious), but that&#39;s a small price to pay for greater intellectual sanctity and an increased attention budget to distribute across important tasks or funnel into something hyper focussed.</p></blockquote>

<p>Is this news important <em>now</em> or do I benefit from it in the long term? Our time is the most precious resource we have, and we should be careful how we spend it.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>