<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Thu, 28 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Linkdump #2
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-28-linkdump-2
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-28-linkdump-2?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 28 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>A while back <a href="/posts/2023-09-11-linkdump-software-development">I did a linkdump</a> to get some links out of my system that deserve some special attention. Since my &quot;to read&quot; list is filling up once again, I decided to do another link dump. I hope you find these articles as interesting as I do!</p>

<ul><li><a href="https://dubroy.com/blog/cold-blooded-software/">Cold-blooded software</a> - On maintainability and simplicity</li><li><a href="https://www.industriallogic.com/blog/discovery-trees/">Working With Discovery Trees</a> - An interesting alternative to the Kanban-Board</li><li><a href="https://www.berkansasmaz.com/every-programmer-should-know-idempotency/">Every Programmer Should Know #1: Idempotency</a> - The title says it all</li><li><a href="https://blog.alexewerlof.com/p/broken-ownership">6 Archetypes of Broken Ownership</a> - Responsibilities in a DevOps environment</li><li><a href="https://read.engineerscodex.com/p/how-pinterest-scaled-to-11-million">How Pinterest scaled to 11 million users with only 6 engineers</a> - On going from simple, to complex, and back to simple</li><li><a href="https://iximiuz.com/en/posts/on-software-design-and-good-writing/">On Software Design... and Good Writing</a> - Essentially <a href="https://spacecraft.ssl.umd.edu/akins_laws.html">this amazing post</a> with additional notes for software developers</li><li><a href="https://andreasjhkarlsson.github.io//jekyll/update/2023/12/27/4-billion-if-statements.html">4 billion if statements</a> - A fun analysis of a silly solution to a simple problem. Teaches critical thinking</li></ul>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                #100DaysToOffload: I made it!
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 23 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This marks post 100 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com">#100DaysToOffload</a>. These last couple of days, I&#39;ve been sprinting towards the finish line with one post every day to finish the challenge until the end of the year. And I finally made it!</p>

<p>I started this challenge with <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-01-11-100daystooffload">this</a> post on January 11th, 2021, which means it took me almost three full years to finish it. The original challenge was to write 100 posts in <strong>one</strong> year, so I&#39;m way overdue. 😅 But that doesn&#39;t make me less proud to finish it!</p>

<p>If you&#39;re interested, you can find the list of all 100 of my posts <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts?tags=100DaysToOffload">here</a>.</p>

<h2>What I learned</h2>

<p>Before starting this challenge, I sometimes struggled with putting out content on this blog. It felt like each post had to be perfect, and if it wasn&#39;t, I was scared to publish it.</p>

<p>The idea of #100DaysToOffload is to let go of this fear and <em>Just. Write.</em> This absolutely worked. I accepted the fact that not every post is perfect and <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity">sometimes posting more often with worse quality makes way for better posts</a>.</p>

<p>In order to post more often, I also found ways to reduce the friction between me writing a text and publishing it to the blog. I&#39;ve yet to cover this in a post, but I built myself <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/blob/main/.github/workflows/publish_via_issue.yaml">a handy script</a> that turns the contents of a GitHub issue into a pull request, ready to be merged as a blog post. This enables me to write posts everywhere I want (like the one right now, which is written on my phone), instead of having to open my laptop, create a new file, write the post and commit it to the repository.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>I will continue posting when I feel like it! I set myself the goal to publish at least 50 posts a year, but that&#39;s just a rough estimate. If I don&#39;t feel like blogging, I won&#39;t force myself to do it.</p>

<p>All in all, I&#39;m very thankful for having taken part in this challenge. I met <a href="https://kevquirk.com/">a</a> <a href="https://joelchrono.xyz/">bunch</a> <a href="https://claytonerrington.com/">of</a> <a href="https://dougbelshaw.com/">like-minded</a> <a href="https://jlelse.blog/">folks</a> that are happy to discuss whatever I&#39;m rambling about, and it&#39;s great to read whatever they are rambling about as well! I&#39;m also thankful for all the nuggets of information I got to share with you, and also with my future self (seriously, you won&#39;t believe how often I&#39;m looking up old posts and being happy that I wrote that down!).</p>

<p>Thanks for reading, until next time!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 100 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                10.000 Hours
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-22-10-000-hours
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-22-10-000-hours?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 22 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>In his book <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outliers_(book)">Outliers</a>, Malcolm Gladwell popularized the idea that it takes 10.000 hours of concentrated practice to master a skill.</p>

<p>According to my <a href="https://wakatime.com">WakaTime</a> stats, I spent 2.384 hours writing code in an editor (December 2023). If you&#39;re reading this post in the future, this is my current record:</p>

<p><a href="https://wakatime.com/@811525e7-5cc5-4eef-9e29-3cece3a03847"><img alt="wakatime" src="https://wakatime.com/badge/user/811525e7-5cc5-4eef-9e29-3cece3a03847.svg"/></a></p>

<p>This time is the time actually spent writing code. It doesn&#39;t track the time reading or thinking about it, nor the time spent in editors without the WakaTime plugin. It&#39;s hard to say how much time I spent engulfed in code, but this number is a good indicator as to how far I&#39;ve come in my programming journey.</p>

<p>I believe we should never say that we&#39;ve &quot;mastered&quot; a craft, even after spending 10.000 hours practicing it. There are always so many things to learn, so many novel ideas to catch up with.</p>

<p>So far, each of my 7 years of working as a software developer has advanced me tremendously. I&#39;m curious to see where I am once I reach 10.000 hours of practice.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 099 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Notes on "Immutability Changes Everything"
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-21-notes-on-immutability
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-21-notes-on-immutability?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Published books are immutable. Accountants don&#39;t use erasers or they go to jail.</p></blockquote>

<p>The paper <a href="https://www.cidrdb.org/cidr2015/Papers/CIDR15_Paper16.pdf">Immutability Changes Everything</a> by Pat Helland talks about the trend towards immutability in data storage thoughout all layers of the stack. From append-only apps (Record changes, then derive the current state), down to how bits are stored on a hard drive (e.g. Copy on Write).</p>

<p>I stumbled upon this paper through the <a href="https://paperswelove.org/">Papers We Love</a> collection. I was specifically looking for a paper that&#39;s short and easy to comprehend, since I don&#39;t have much experience in reading scientific papers. This is absolutely both short and easy to comprehend. If you&#39;re a beginner like me, I can highly recommend this one to you.</p>

<p>Key takeaways:</p>

<ul><li>Immutability enables clean replication</li><li>Change logs (e.g. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Write-ahead_logging">write-ahead logs</a>) are the source of truth. The database is a cache of a subset of those change logs</li><li>It&#39;s okay to consider violating <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Database_normalization">normalization</a> rules to trade storage cost for read speed</li><li>Modern SSDs minimize wear by storing new versions of data to other blocks instead of mutating the data in place</li><li>The cost of immutability is increased storage</li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 098 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                re: Giving context to a blogroll
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-20-giving-my-blogroll-more-context
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-20-giving-my-blogroll-more-context?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 20 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>This is a reply to Simone Silvestroni&#39;s <a href="https://minutestomidnight.co.uk/blog/giving-context-to-a-blogroll/">blog post</a> about blogrolls, which itself is a reply to a <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site">call for feedback</a> for my site.</p></blockquote>

<p>Simone argues that Blogroll entries without an explaination are just random links with a name. The reader doesn&#39;t know what&#39;s behind those links and therefore doesn&#39;t benefit from the blogroll. It would be better to give some context to the entries by explaining why they are on this list.</p>

<p>I absolutely support this idea. In response, I added context to all of my <a href="/blogroll">Blogroll</a> entries. I hope this helps you discover more awesome content on the web. Also, if you know a website that might fit on this list (maybe your own?), feel free to <a href="/contact">let me know</a>. I&#39;d be happy to read it!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 097 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Another reason why you can't divide by zero
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-19-another-reason-you-can-t-divide-by-zero
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-19-another-reason-you-can-t-divide-by-zero?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>So, I recently wrote about [why you can&#39;t divide by zero](/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can&#39;t-divide-by-zero). In that post, I argued that dividing a number by zero breaks the rules of <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverse_function">inverse functions</a>. Of course that&#39;s not the only way to prove that the result of dividing a number by zero is not defined, so here&#39;s another.</p>

<p>If you approach the number zero from some arbitrary number as the divisor, you will find that the result is getting larger and larger: <code>1 / 1 = 1</code>, <code>1 / 0.5 = 2</code>, <code>1 / 0.1 = 10</code> and so on. If we keep dividing by smaller numbers, the result will get bigger and bigger. It&#39;s obvious that if we go all the way down to zero as the divisor, we will see infinity as the result, right? Well, no.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s flip this around and start from a negative number, going up towards the number zero: <code>1 / -1 = -1</code>, <code>1 / -0.5 = -2</code>, <code>1 / -0.1 = -10</code>. As you can see, the numbers are getting <strong>smaller</strong>, the more we approach the number zero! This shows that the results differ if we change the perspective on the problem. The result cannot be defined.</p>

<p>After writing the first post on this topic, I honestly didn&#39;t realize how complex this seemingly simple problem is. I&#39;m not a mathematician, but I&#39;m starting to like maths. Fascinating stuff!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 096 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Overcoming "air hunger"
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>For as long as I can remember, I often had the feeling of not being able to get a full breath. I&#39;m taking deep breaths and sometimes forcing a yawn to overcome this feeling, sometimes successful, sometimes failing and trying again. This feeling gets worse the more I focus on my breath.</p>

<p>I always felt like this is somewhat uncommon, since none of my friends and family can relate to this feeling, but it wasn&#39;t worse enough to justify consulting a doctor about it either.</p>

<p>Doing some research, it seems like this phenomenon is called <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortness_of_breath">dyspnea</a>, or &quot;air hunger&quot;. Some guy even made <a href="https://airhunger.org/">a website</a> about it. In a nutshell, it is caused by your body not being able to regulate carbon levels in your blood, which leads to an urge to breath unnaturally.</p>

<p>In a <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=XliOGg8Tl98">video</a>, the author points out that this might be caused by irregular breathing patterns. Indeed, I often find myself breathing through the mouth or sitting in awkward positions with a humpback when the symptoms are at its worst. In fact, what led me to look this up was because I was annoyed by the feeling while I&#39;m laying in bed staring down at my screen, which is a very unnatural position.</p>

<p>A simple trick to get into a more regular breathing pattern is apparently to force yourself to breathe through the nose. Mouth breathing lets your body take in way more air than you need, which throws off the balance of the carbon levels in your lungs.</p>

<p>It seems like nose breathing does work very well. Where I&#39;ve just been struggling with air hunger, once I forced myself to nose breathe, the urge to breathe doesn&#39;t come nearly as often anymore.</p>

<p>These are just my results after some quick research. The topic of short breathing seems to be quite broad. Perhaps you&#39;re struggling with this as well. In that case, I hope this post was helpful to you!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 095 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                I'm finally off coffee
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Disclaimer: There&#39;s no real story here — just a dump of my thoughts.</p>

<p>I used to drink two cups of coffee a day on average. One during breakfast and one during the day.</p>

<p>On days where it was difficult to get my hands on coffee — during camping for example, or on some days where I don&#39;t really have time to brew a coffee — I would routinely get headaches. This might have been a coincidence, but it&#39;s not unlikely that my body was craving this delicious drink. Waking up was always accompanied by this nagging feeling of how I&#39;m gonna get my dose of coffee today.</p>

<p>That all changed when I got sick a few weeks ago. I wasn&#39;t feeling well for a few days, and as a result I didn&#39;t drink coffee at all. Knowing that caffeine is a huge stress-inducing factor in my day to day life, I decided to just not start drinking it again once I felt better.</p>

<p>Quitting caffeine cold turkey can be difficult, but two cups isn&#39;t much. Some of my peers drink way more than that. While being sick, my body quickly adjusted to the missing two cups each day. I wasn&#39;t feeling good anyway, so what&#39;s an extra mild headache?</p>

<p>Now, about two weeks later, I feel great. There&#39;s one stress-factor less in my life. I occasionally still drink coffee with friends, but it&#39;s not something I crave directly after waking up. I opted for caffeine-free tea in the morning. We also have decaffeinated coffee at home, but it feels to me like brewing decaffeinated coffee isn&#39;t worth the effort. It&#39;s still a nice alternative for nice breakfasts on the weekend.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 094 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Roast my Site!
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 12 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Let&#39;s try something: <code>#RoastMySite</code>!</p>

<p>I want to hear your honest feedback about my website. (Not so) constructive criticism, funny bug reports and savage burns. 🔥</p>

<p><a href="/contact">Shoot me a mail</a> with your roast and I&#39;ll include it on this site!</p>

<p>Got your own site? I&#39;ll roast it! Just ping me via mail or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@garritfra">on Mastodon</a>.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 093 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Formula E is essentially Mario Kart
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-11-formula-e-is-essentially-mario-kart
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-11-formula-e-is-essentially-mario-kart?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 11 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I never actively watched a Formula E race, let alone Formula 1. Racing just isn&#39;t on my radar. However, I just came across <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=En-__5ewnAk">this</a> video about the driving style in Formula E races, and I was instantly hooked. Formula E is basically Mario Kart.</p>

<p>In a race, drivers can enter a so called &quot;attack mode&quot;, in which they can leave the optimal route in a turn to activate a significant power burst for a short while.</p>

<p><img alt="grafik" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/712c8317-a669-4a20-8d29-c746aea54392"/></p>

<p>Sound familiar? You bet!</p>

<p><img alt="grafik" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/22c8cf0f-6ac4-491d-8814-a24f937ec3a7"/></p>

<p>Additionally, drivers have the strategic option to &quot;hyperboost&quot; for some time. During a race, the drivers have to balance speed and efficiency. If your battery is empty, you&#39;re out of the race. The cars usually don&#39;t drive with full power to conserve energy, until the &quot;hyperboost&quot; is activated. So thinking about <strong>when</strong> to overtake a car plays a huge strategic role. Does that ring a bell?</p>

<p><img alt="grafik" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/18b326c6-e4db-495e-8cfb-1039f9c39691"/></p>

<p>Formula 1 cars generate <strong>a lot</strong> of data which is analyzed by the pit to predict tire wear, fuel usage, weather conditions and so on. In Formula E, no data is streamed to the pit at all. It&#39;s entirely up to the skill of the driver to make decisions. Again, just like in Mario Kart.</p>

<p>Although I have no stakes in car races whatsoever, I was blown away by this video about Formula E. If you liked this post, I suggest you <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=En-__5ewnAk">watch it by yourself</a> and let it be explained by an expert.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 092 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>