<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Dive Log: Phuket
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just became a certified diver! 🥳</p>

<p>I got my license through the <a href="https://rumblefishadventure.com/">Rumblefish Adventure</a> divecenter in Kata Beach, as per a recommendation from a friend who happened to be around in the area when we were there.</p>

<p>Kata Beach is a great dive spot. It has crazy wildlife, it&#39;s just a short swim away from the beach and the visibility is quite good if you haven&#39;t seen many reefs yet (like myself).</p>

<p>After doing our PADI Open Water license, we went to Phi Phi Islands to do a fun dive. The experience swimming through the reefs there can simply not be put into words.</p>

<p>In total, we did 7 dives in Thailand. Here&#39;s a full list, taken from my logbook:</p>

<p>| Title                 | Date       | Site              | Depth (m) | Time (min) | Highlights                                         |
|-----------------------|------------|-------------------|-----------|------------|----------------------------------------------------|
| Open Water Training 1 | 2024-02-16 | Kata Beach        | 6.4       | 39         | First time seeing the reef!                        |
| Open Water Training 2 | 2024-02-18 | Kata Beach        | 10.9      | 62         | Almost finished all mandatory training             |
| Open Water Training 3 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 16.3      | 44         | Artificial reefs with lots of interesting wildlife |
| Open Water Training 4 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 12.9      | 48         | Even more crazy wildlife                           |
| Phi Phi Islands 1     | 2024-02-20 | Koh Bida Nok      | 20.5      | 51         | Sharks!                                            |
| Phi Phi Islands 2     | 2024-02-20 | Turtle Rock       | 17.6      | 55         | Turtles, Sharks, Cave                              |
| Phi Phi Islands 3     | 2024-02-20 | Shark Point       | 20.4      | 46         | Lots of verticality                                |</p>

<h2>Photos</h2>

<p><img alt="P2170670 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1d00d17d-a889-417d-a4c9-8dd83eff58f9"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170752 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d3b80e60-2155-481f-8232-a5a57b3898ab"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170727 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/25e75fb1-dec7-4ad2-89a9-d929144cd60a"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170759 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1f9c2c0f-cc2e-440a-9bba-2a03c984f301"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180898.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/7f33d8a9-1d5f-4f94-87de-6078233be6a8"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180901.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/e1caf403-4ea2-4dce-a48c-1a0b5b5ce360"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180859.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/6fe5e666-0099-445f-bdcc-35bc0e5e9943"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170749 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d6a239a8-fb98-478a-9e38-d15e3587a7b4"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180837 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/50fe5c89-f1cb-4a73-aac0-f1311a3116fc"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170733 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d44f52a2-2228-4a3e-801d-930f0eddf975"/></p>

<p>After Phuket, we went to Vietnam where we&#39;re currently also on a lot of fun diving trips. But I&#39;ll save that for another dive log post.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Cosmic Horror: The Festival
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-10-cosmic-horror-the-festival
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-10-cosmic-horror-the-festival?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 10 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&quot;The nethermost caverns are not for the fathoming of eyes that see; for their marvels are strange and terrific. Cursed the ground where dead thoughts live new and oddly bodied, and evil the mind that is held by no head.&quot;</p><p>— H.P. Lovecraft</p></blockquote>

<p>I loved reading <a href="https://www.hplovecraft.com/writings/texts/fiction/f.aspx">The Festival</a> by H.P. Lovecraft, especially this quote by &quot;the mad Arab&quot; at the end of the story. The Festival is one of Lovecrafts first short stories in the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cthulhu_Mythos">Cthulhu Mythos</a>. The quote excellently shows the unique style of Lovecrafts short stories. Each story is a grotesque depiction of horrors that are beyond our imagination. I recently tried to replicate this style of writing in  &quot;<a href="/posts/2023-09-10-short-story-haunted-memories">Haunted Memories</a>&quot;, a short story about digital media. I&#39;m just getting started with reading Lovecrafts stories, but the ones I read so far absolutely blew me away.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                To prove something is true, try disproving it first
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-30-to-prove-something-is-true-try-disproving-it-first
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-30-to-prove-something-is-true-try-disproving-it-first?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>We&#39;ve been taught that, to prove that a thing is true, we should point out what&#39;s true about it.</p>

<p>However, we can learn much more about why something is true by trying to <strong>disprove</strong> it first. If you think something is true, try as hard as you can to prove that it&#39;s false.</p>

<p>Disproving a theory is core to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_method">scientific method</a>. Only when we validate that something cannot be false, we come closer to proving that it&#39;s true.</p>

<h2>Source</h2>

<p>&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vKA4w2O61Xo?si=2dtApWo8JmHOwqff&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Cost per Request
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-18-cost-per-request
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-18-cost-per-request?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 18 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>When monitoring infrastructure, we often use metrics like &quot;Requests per second&quot; or &quot;Time per request&quot;.</p>

<p>Contrary to that, when monitoring the cost of our infrastructure, we often only review the cloud bill at the end of the month and tell ourselves that those costs are justified for our product.</p>

<p>What if we made &quot;Cost per request&quot; a key metric in our observability strategy, alongside &quot;Requests per second&quot;?</p>

<p>If we follow that path even further, we could derive a standard for how much a request should cost for x% of uptime, across the entire industry. This way, we should be able to identify how much we&#39;re overspending for our infrastructure compared to other companies or products.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                A better publishing workflow for static blogs
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-06-a-better-publishing-workflow-for-static-blogs
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-06-a-better-publishing-workflow-for-static-blogs?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 06 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it">post</a> celebrating the completion of my <code>#100DaysToOffload</code> challenge, I teased that &quot;I built myself a handy script that turns the contents of a GitHub issue into a pull request, ready to be merged as a blog post&quot;. I didn&#39;t believe this was such a big deal, but a couple of readers actually reached out to me to ask about this.</p>

<p>First, some background. My site is built using a static site generator (not that it matters, but I use <a href="https://nextjs.org/">Next.js</a>). The beauty of using a SSG is that every blog post is literally just a markdown file in <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/tree/main/content/posts">a directory</a>. </p>

<h2>The story so far</h2>

<p>Before coming up with an automation, I had to</p>

<ol><li>Copy an older post to a new file</li><li>Rename the file</li><li>Fix the metadata/frontmatter</li><li>Delete the contents of the post</li><li><strong>Write the actual post</strong></li><li>Commit the file</li></ol>

<p>Putting out content on my blog involved quite a bit of friction. I felt like there was a barrier between my thoughts and the blog.</p>

<h2>The solution</h2>

<p>I&#39;ve been looking into how I could solve this issue for quite some time. I even had thoughts to build a custom blogging backend that would commit files to the <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz">repository</a>, which is of course quite silly.</p>

<p>But then it struck me: GitHub issues fully support markdown! The idea was born:</p>

<ol><li>Open an issue in the repository of this blog</li><li>Write the post</li><li>Kick off an automation that takes the content of the issue and dumps it in a new file</li><li>Create a pull request to generate a preview of the post</li><li>Merge the PR once I&#39;m done reviewing the post</li></ol>

<h2>So, how does the automation work?</h2>

<p>The magic lies in <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/blob/main/.github/workflows/publish_via_issue.yaml">this GitHub Action</a>. It is kicked off whenever the <code>action:publish</code> label is added to an issue.</p>

<p>If for some reason this link will not be there anymore in the future, this is the action as of the time of writing:</p>

<p>&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Expand me!&lt;/summary&gt;</p>

<p><code></code>`yaml
on:
  issues:
    types: [labeled]</p>

<p>name: Publish issue as post
jobs:
  publish-issue:
    if: github.event.label.name == &#39;action:publish&#39;
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    env:
      POST<em>BODY: &#39;${{ github.event.issue.body }}&#39;
    steps:
      - uses: actions/checkout@v4
      - name: Create commits
        run: |
          export POST</em>DATE=$(date +&quot;%Y-%m-%d&quot;)
          export POST<em>TITLE=&quot;${{ github.event.issue.title }}&quot;
          export POST</em>TAGS=$(echo &quot;${{ join(github.event.issue.labels.<em>.name, &#39;, &#39;) }}&quot; | grep -o &#39;tag:[^,]</em>&#39; | cut -d: -f2- | paste -sd &quot; &quot; - | sed &#39;s/ /, /g&#39;)
          export FILE<em>TITLE=$(printf &quot;$POST</em>TITLE&quot; | tr -cs &#39;[:alnum:]&#39; &#39;-&#39; | tr &#39;A-Z&#39; &#39;a-z&#39; | sed &#39;s/--/-/g&#39; | sed &#39;s/^-\|-$//g&#39;)
          export FILE<em>NAME=&quot;$POST</em>DATE-$FILE<em>TITLE.md&quot;
          export FULL</em>PATH=&quot;content/posts/$FILE_NAME&quot;
          git config user.name &#39;Publish Bot&#39;
          git config user.email &#39;publish-bot@github.com&#39;</p>

<pre><code>      cat &lt;&lt; EOF &gt; $FULL_PATH
      ---
      title: &quot;$POST_TITLE&quot;
      date: &quot;$POST_DATE&quot;
      tags: &quot;$POST_TAGS&quot;
      ---

      EOF

      echo &quot;$POST_BODY&quot; &gt;&gt; $FULL_PATH

      git add $FULL_PATH
      git commit -m &quot;Publish $POST_TITLE&quot;

  - name: Create Pull Request
    uses: peter-evans/create-pull-request@v5
    with:
      title: &quot;New Post: ${{ github.event.issue.title }}&quot;
      body: &quot;Closes #${{ github.event.issue.number }}.\n\n This PR has been generated automatically.&quot;
  - uses: actions-ecosystem/action-remove-labels@v1
    with:
      labels: action:publish</code></pre>

<p><code></code>`</p>

<p>&lt;/details&gt;</p>

<p>So, when I&#39;m done writing the post, I simply label the issue as <code>action:publish</code>, and the action turns it into a new file, commits it and ultimately opens a PR for me to review. You can see this in action by looking at <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/issues/432">the issue for this post</a>. The action also handles tags for blog posts. You can see that there are a bunch of labels on the issues that correspond to the tags of this post.</p>

<p>One additional benefit of using a static site generator is that I can generate a preview site for each pull request. So, once I&#39;m done writing and the pull request is generated, I can just wait for Netlify to build the preview to read the blog post as if it is published to the site! This is very helpful for spotting typos or formatting issues, especially if I&#39;m writing a post on my phone.</p>

<h2>Further improvements</h2>

<p>There are two things the current setup is lacking:</p>

<p>Firstly, GitHub doesn&#39;t really highlight typos when writing an issue. I&#39;m sure there are ways to address this post-publish, I just didn&#39;t get around to doing that yet.</p>

<p>Secondly, there&#39;s no sustainable way to add images to the repository this way. I have an <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/tree/main/public/assets">assets directory</a> where I put all my images for blog posts. You can paste images directly into the issue, which is really handy, but that generates a permalink on a GitHub CDN, somewhere that I don&#39;t control. For the future, it would be nice to teach the GH action to take these images and dump them into the asset directory.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Using this workflow, I can pump out ideas whenever and whereever I feel like it. It drastically reduced the time from idea to written article, which helps me organize my thoughts a lot better. I also frequently create drafts for things I want to write about but is not fully fleshed out yet.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Greg, the Developer
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 05 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This is Greg. Greg loves to play with his computer and create amazing things.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg.svg"/></p>

<p>Greg has many friends. He listens to his friends and helps them. Greg knows that teamwork is very important.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg and his friends" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-friends.svg"/></p>

<p>Greg is curious about what his friends do. Greg learned how they help everyone create amazing things. Greg was happy that he learned something new.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg learns from his friends" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-learning.svg"/></p>

<p>One day, Greg has an idea. Greg shares his idea with his friends. They try it, and it works! Everyone is happy that Greg shared his idea.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg has an idea" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-idea.svg"/></p>

<p>When Greg learns something new about computers, he writes it down and shows it to his friends. This helps everyone learn how computers work.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg writes down what he learned" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-documentation.svg"/></p>

<p>Sometimes Greg and his friends make a mistake, but Greg knows that&#39;s okay. Everyone makes mistakes, even Greg. He says that everyone can learn from mistakes. This makes them better and happier.</p>

<p><img alt="It&#39;s okay to make mistakes" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-mistake.svg"/></p>

<p>Greg is a good software developer. Be like Greg.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg is a good software developer" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-okay.svg"/></p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Temporal vs. fundamental content
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just read <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38829907">this comment</a> on a thread on HackerNews which resonated with me:</p>

<blockquote><p>I&#39;m trying to read less temporal (things that matter now) and more fundamental (stuff that mattered 1+ year ago and will still matter in 1+ year, with even wider intervals for non-tech content).
This does result in missing ~important things occasionally (e.g. I still don&#39;t know what happened with SamA at OpenAI, and yes, I am curious), but that&#39;s a small price to pay for greater intellectual sanctity and an increased attention budget to distribute across important tasks or funnel into something hyper focussed.</p></blockquote>

<p>Is this news important <em>now</em> or do I benefit from it in the long term? Our time is the most precious resource we have, and we should be careful how we spend it.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                2023 in Review
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>That&#39;s a wrap! 2023 was an exciting year for me. I started my new role as a <a href="/posts/2023-04-22-the-role-of-a-devops-engineer">DevOps Engineer</a> at my current company, I got <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/open-source-der-patch-basierte-git-workflow-soll-bleiben-2302-171585.html">two</a> <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/wertestrom-in-devops-das-projekt-am-laufen-halten-2312-180174.html">articles</a> published on a prominent German news site and finally finished my <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a> challenge!</p>

<p>This year, I launched two projects: <a href="https://sendpasswords.net/">sendpasswords.net</a> and <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/positive_hackernews">Positive Hacker News</a>.</p>

<p>In <a href="/posts/2023-01-02-welcome-2023">last year&#39;s review</a>, I said I wanted to launch <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/fling">Fling</a>, my household management app. Fling is currently in open alpha, so you can try it out <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=de.garritfra.fling">on Android</a> or via the <a href="https://fling-list.web.app">hosted website</a> to give feedback! I&#39;m planning a public release very soon.</p>

<p>Furthermore, I wanted to launch <a href="https://docs.kubinity.com/">Kubinity</a>. This was a very ambitious project, and although it technically works, it&#39;s very hard to maintain due to high running costs, which I&#39;m not ready to pay yet.</p>

<p>I have some more drafts for projects in private repositories. One project that I&#39;m feeling comfortable to release next year is a website for the #10ShittyProjects (working title) hashtag. More on that hopefully later!</p>

<h2>Goals for 2024</h2>

<p>Here are some personal goals that I want to set myself for the upcoming year. Some of them are already defined on my <a href="/impossible">impossible list</a>.</p>

<ul><li>Build a side project that generated at least 100€ of value</li><li>Get a scuba diving license</li><li>Do a 10 km run (I really need to start moving again)</li><li>Sell my car</li><li>Write at least 50 blog posts</li></ul>

<h2>Prediction results</h2>

<p><strong>&quot;Meta will change course (again), and kill the &quot;Metaverse&quot;&quot;</strong></p>

<p>A <a href="https://labs.sogeti.com/the-metaverse-is-dead/#:~:text=The%20Real%20Promise%20of%20VR%2FAR%20Lies%20in%20Training%20Simulations&amp;text=Yet%2C%20as%20of%202023%2C%20we,Reality%20(AR)%20has%20diminished.">quick Google search</a> reveals that the metaverse as originally imagined is not dead, but it&#39;s focus shifted to a more enterprise-y approach. I must admit that this prediction was quite vague. Depending on whom you ask, the metaverse is <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schr%C3%B6dinger%27s_cat">both alive and dead at the same time</a>.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Cheap matter devices will enter the market. As a reference point: I predict that there will be a matter-ready smart plug for under 20€ on Amazon&quot;</strong></p>

<p>I found <a href="https://amzn.eu/d/iA9ZBQf">this</a> matter-enabled smart plug on Amazon for 19,54€. If this is a real product, I&#39;d say my prediction is a pass!</p>

<p><strong>&quot;AI generated content will be regulated in some way&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Also a pass! On December 9th, the European union agreed on the <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/headlines/society/20230601STO93804/eu-ai-act-first-regulation-on-artificial-intelligence">EU AI Act</a> and will now become EU law.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Twitter is still around, but it&#39;s still not profitable&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Twitter is in fact <a href="https://www.businessofapps.com/data/twitter-statistics/#:~:text=Twitter%20generated%20%244.4%20billion%20revenue%20in%202022%2C%20a%2011%25%20decrease,a%20loss%20of%20advertising%20revenue.">still not profitable</a>. I&#39;ll leave the &quot;Twitter is still around&quot; part up for debate, as it&#39;s now called X.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;I still won&#39;t have finished my #100DaysToOffload challenge from 2021&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Wrong!! In early December, I decided to push through and whip out one post a day. I <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it">finished the challenge</a>!</p>

<h2>2024 Predictions</h2>

<ul><li>Bitcoin will at last reach a value of 100,000$, following the <a href="https://www.nicehash.com/countdown/btc-halving-2024-05-10-12-00">halving</a> likely happening in 2024</li><li>SpaceX will use a <a href="https://www.spacex.com/vehicles/starship/">Starship</a> prototype to launch Starlink satellites into orbit</li><li>Tesla cars a still not fully self driving (<a href="https://motherfrunker.ca/fsd/">reference</a>)</li><li>Google will replace their main search with an AI chat bot (see <a href="https://bard.google.com">Bard</a>)</li></ul>

<p>Let&#39;s see what 2024 brings to the table!</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Linkdump #2
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-28-linkdump-2
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-28-linkdump-2?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 28 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>A while back <a href="/posts/2023-09-11-linkdump-software-development">I did a linkdump</a> to get some links out of my system that deserve some special attention. Since my &quot;to read&quot; list is filling up once again, I decided to do another link dump. I hope you find these articles as interesting as I do!</p>

<ul><li><a href="https://dubroy.com/blog/cold-blooded-software/">Cold-blooded software</a> - On maintainability and simplicity</li><li><a href="https://www.industriallogic.com/blog/discovery-trees/">Working With Discovery Trees</a> - An interesting alternative to the Kanban-Board</li><li><a href="https://www.berkansasmaz.com/every-programmer-should-know-idempotency/">Every Programmer Should Know #1: Idempotency</a> - The title says it all</li><li><a href="https://blog.alexewerlof.com/p/broken-ownership">6 Archetypes of Broken Ownership</a> - Responsibilities in a DevOps environment</li><li><a href="https://read.engineerscodex.com/p/how-pinterest-scaled-to-11-million">How Pinterest scaled to 11 million users with only 6 engineers</a> - On going from simple, to complex, and back to simple</li><li><a href="https://iximiuz.com/en/posts/on-software-design-and-good-writing/">On Software Design... and Good Writing</a> - Essentially <a href="https://spacecraft.ssl.umd.edu/akins_laws.html">this amazing post</a> with additional notes for software developers</li><li><a href="https://andreasjhkarlsson.github.io//jekyll/update/2023/12/27/4-billion-if-statements.html">4 billion if statements</a> - A fun analysis of a silly solution to a simple problem. Teaches critical thinking</li></ul>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                #100DaysToOffload: I made it!
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 23 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This marks post 100 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com">#100DaysToOffload</a>. These last couple of days, I&#39;ve been sprinting towards the finish line with one post every day to finish the challenge until the end of the year. And I finally made it!</p>

<p>I started this challenge with <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-01-11-100daystooffload">this</a> post on January 11th, 2021, which means it took me almost three full years to finish it. The original challenge was to write 100 posts in <strong>one</strong> year, so I&#39;m way overdue. 😅 But that doesn&#39;t make me less proud to finish it!</p>

<p>If you&#39;re interested, you can find the list of all 100 of my posts <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts?tags=100DaysToOffload">here</a>.</p>

<h2>What I learned</h2>

<p>Before starting this challenge, I sometimes struggled with putting out content on this blog. It felt like each post had to be perfect, and if it wasn&#39;t, I was scared to publish it.</p>

<p>The idea of #100DaysToOffload is to let go of this fear and <em>Just. Write.</em> This absolutely worked. I accepted the fact that not every post is perfect and <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity">sometimes posting more often with worse quality makes way for better posts</a>.</p>

<p>In order to post more often, I also found ways to reduce the friction between me writing a text and publishing it to the blog. I&#39;ve yet to cover this in a post, but I built myself <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/blob/main/.github/workflows/publish_via_issue.yaml">a handy script</a> that turns the contents of a GitHub issue into a pull request, ready to be merged as a blog post. This enables me to write posts everywhere I want (like the one right now, which is written on my phone), instead of having to open my laptop, create a new file, write the post and commit it to the repository.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>I will continue posting when I feel like it! I set myself the goal to publish at least 50 posts a year, but that&#39;s just a rough estimate. If I don&#39;t feel like blogging, I won&#39;t force myself to do it.</p>

<p>All in all, I&#39;m very thankful for having taken part in this challenge. I met <a href="https://kevquirk.com/">a</a> <a href="https://joelchrono.xyz/">bunch</a> <a href="https://claytonerrington.com/">of</a> <a href="https://dougbelshaw.com/">like-minded</a> <a href="https://jlelse.blog/">folks</a> that are happy to discuss whatever I&#39;m rambling about, and it&#39;s great to read whatever they are rambling about as well! I&#39;m also thankful for all the nuggets of information I got to share with you, and also with my future self (seriously, you won&#39;t believe how often I&#39;m looking up old posts and being happy that I wrote that down!).</p>

<p>Thanks for reading, until next time!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 100 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>