<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Wed, 12 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Principles of DevOps: Flow
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-12-principles-of-devops--flow
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-12-principles-of-devops--flow?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 12 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>This post is part of a series called <a href="/posts?tags=PrinciplesOfDevOps">Principles of DevOps</a>.</p></blockquote>

<p>&quot;Flow&quot; refers to the performance of a system, as opposed to the performance of a specific silo or department.</p>

<p>In our daily work, we often only see what&#39;s inside our own silo. As a developer, we see requirements come in and code going out. In operations, we see code being pushed to a repository and pipelines deploying it to production. However, it&#39;s crucial to understand the flow of work in a broader context.</p>

<p>Most services or products have a &quot;value stream&quot; which describes how work is performed. You can think of the value stream as a carrier belt with multiple work centers. The first work center might be the business department, followed by a design team, a dev team, QA, operations and finally the customer. This structure might look different, depending on what product or service you are building.</p>

<h2>The flow of work should always go in one direction</h2>

<p>Work is typically generated at some point of the value stream. A requirement by the business department, an issue created by the QA team, an incident in operations, feedback from a customer, and so on.</p>

<p>Regardless of where the work originates, the flow of work should always go in one direction: forward. Work moving backwards, or even standing still, introduces bottlenecks that prevent downstream work centers from properly working. Always seek to resolve these bottlenecks as soon as possible.</p>

<h2>Always seek to increase flow</h2>

<p>The goal of almost any product or service is to bring value to the customer. More work flowing through the system means more value generated. But how do we increase the flow of work?</p>

<p><strong>Eliminate work in progress</strong>. This almost always indicates a bottleneck in one of the workcenters. Work should always flow smoothly through the system. If a ticket is stuck in one department for too long, ask why and how this can be avoided in the future.</p>

<p><strong>Match the pace of the customer</strong>. If the value stream is pumping out more features than the customer demands, you are not generating value to the business.</p>

<p><strong>Reduce work batch size</strong>. By <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-05-19-work-batch-sizing">iterating in small steps</a>, you can adapt to changes more quickly. Split up requirements into smaller tickets and increase the amount of deployments.</p>

<p>If you want to learn more about how to increase flow in a system, see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_constraints">theory of constraints</a> and the <a href="https://hbswk.hbs.edu/item/decoding-the-dna-of-the-toyota-production-system">Toyota production system</a>.</p>

<h2>Never unconsciously pass known defects downstream</h2>

<p>Aim to fix problems immedietely as they occur, especially if it&#39;s higher up in the value stream. Everyone should be responsible for the work of the entire value stream instead of just their work center.</p>

<p>If you notice work or problems being introduced multiple times, it&#39;s likely the upstream work center is unaware of this. Immediately seek awareness and work together on resolving it.</p>

<h2>Never allow local optimization to create global degradation</h2>

<p>Optimizing local work is important, but it should never introduce friction in other workcenters and, by extension, decrease performance of the value stream.</p>

<p>Local optimization is often linked to the &quot;tribal warfare&quot; between organizations (e.g. development vs. operations, business vs. development, etc.).</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Understanding and optimizing the flow of work within a value stream is crucial for achieving efficient and effective software delivery. By ensuring that work moves in one direction and continuously seeking to increase the flow, we can generate more value for customers and the business.</p>

<p>Eliminating bottlenecks, matching the pace of the customer, and reducing work batch size are all key strategies to enhance flow. Moreover, actively addressing known defects, promoting collaboration across the value stream, and avoiding local optimizations that hinder overall performance are essential for achieving successful outcomes. By embracing these principles, we can unlock the full potential of DevOps and drive continuous improvement in software delivery processes.</p>

<h2>Resources</h2>

<ul><li><a href="https://itrevolution.com/articles/the-three-ways-principles-underpinning-devops/">The Three Ways: The Principles Underpinning DevOps</a></li><li><a href="https://itrevolution.com/articles/elements-of-the-first-way-and-the-devops-implications/">Elements Of The First Way: And The DevOps Implications</a></li><li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_constraints">Theory Of Constraints</a></li><li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lean_IT">Lean IT</a></li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 073 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                PSA: RSS feed changes
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-06-rss-changes
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-06-rss-changes?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 06 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>If you&#39;re subscribed to this blog via <a href="/rss.xml">RSS</a>, you will soon likely see
a bunch of my posts re-appearing in your feed. For that, I apologize in advance!</p>

<p>I&#39;m planning to make two modifications. Firstly, I want to add a <code>id</code> property
to all entries. So far, your reader has been likely been relying on the URL slug
to identify an entry. Adding the <code>id</code> property makes this more flexible, but it
also means that your reader will think that there are new entries in the feed.
This will only happen once.</p>

<p>Secondly, I want to reduce the amount of the entries. If you look at the
<a href="/rss.xml">feed</a>, you&#39;ll see a lot of junk from way back, containing every word
I wrote on this blog. Remember that this page is fetched periodically (usually
every hour for most readers) by <strong>every</strong> subscriber. That&#39;s a lot of traffic
that could be better put to use somewhere else. Not that it costs me anything -
this site is hosted on <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> - but if this
helps reduce the carbon footprint of the site even by one gram, it&#39;s worth the
effort.</p>

<p>As of the time of writing this post, by restricting the number of posts to 10,
we reduce the amount of traffic per client per hour from 272 kB down to to 24
kB. That&#39;s over <strong>2 GB</strong> of traffic saved each year <strong>per subscriber</strong>!!</p>

<p>That&#39;s all - just a heads up. Thanks for your patience, you&#39;re awesome! ✌️</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 071 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Make a List
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-25-make-a-list
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-25-make-a-list?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 25 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>My dad taught me this important lesson. </p>

<p>Whenever you&#39;re feeling stuck or you don&#39;t know what to do, make a list. The next step will often become clear.</p>

<p>Whether you&#39;re going shopping or you&#39;re feeling mentally overloaded. It helps to write down your thoughts in an actionable form. I don&#39;t care if it&#39;s in some fancy mobile app or on a napkin. Just make a list.</p>

<p>Lists are the answer to almost anything. And where they&#39;re not, a spreadsheet is.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 070 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Single Page Applications on GitHub Pages
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-01-single-page-applications-on-github-pages
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-01-single-page-applications-on-github-pages?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>My latest project, <a href="https://sendpasswords.net/">sendpasswords.net</a> is a <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Glossary/SPA">Single Page Application</a> deployed on GitHub Pages.</p>

<p>GitHub Pages is configured in a way to host static HTML files without any bells and whistles. This means that if you try to fetch a document that&#39;s <em>not</em> the index, for example <code>/foo</code>, the server will try to load the file with that name. </p>

<p>By nature, SPAs only consist of a single HTML entry point (<code>index.html</code> in most cases). It&#39;s responsible for routing the user to the correct page if there are multiple paths. And here&#39;s the crux: if the user tries to load <code>/foo</code>, he will not land at the SPA entry point. Instead, he will see a <code>404</code> error.</p>

<h2>The solution</h2>

<p>A <code>404</code> response will automatically return a file called <code>404.html</code>, which we can use to our advantage. After building the application, simply copy the <code>index.html</code> to <code>404.html</code>, as demonstrated by <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/sendpasswords.net/commit/66bdb68c229a3ac3386f7816a746155e658eb586">this commit</a>. This will use <code>index.html</code> to serve the application on the root level, and <code>404.html</code> to load <em>the same app</em> if the page doesn&#39;t exist as a file. Whether the <code>index.html</code> is needed if there&#39;s already a <code>404.html</code> is up to you. I left it in to make clear that this is just a workaround.</p>

<p>This is a <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/69308662/9046809">well known</a> workaround, but I wanted to bring some extra awareness to it, since it&#39;s a problem I ran into a couple of times so far. Happy SPAing!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 069 (nice) of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Optimizing work batch size
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-05-19-work-batch-sizing
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-05-19-work-batch-sizing?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I&#39;ve been playing 
<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carcassonne_(board_game)">Carcassonne</a> a lot with my girlfriend recently. It&#39;s a boardgame about building cities, roads and farms, and each completed &quot;project&quot; earns you some amount of points. The twist is that there&#39;s only a limited number of tiles, and once all tiles are used, the game is over unfinished projects are discarded.</p>

<p>The first couple of playthroughs I tried to maximize my score by increasing the number of projects I actively had going. I&#39;d start a new city or road whenever I could, thinking that the multipliers you sometimes get would pay off in the end. Boy was I wrong.</p>

<p>Where I&#39;m from, we have multiple sayings for this approach. &quot;Having too many irons in the fire&quot; or &quot;dancing on too many parties&quot;. I was too busy starting new projects instead of making actual progress.</p>

<p>A far better approach is to finish projects early, earning less points, but with a greater certainty that they will pay off. With every project you start, the likelyhood of the other projects paying off decreases.</p>

<p>Keeping batch sizes small was a key concept of the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lean_manufacturing">lean manufacturing movement</a> in the 1980s, and has since been adopted by the <a href="https://de.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps">DevOps movement</a> for the IT industry. If you want to learn more about this topic, you should check out <a href="https://itrevolution.com/product/the-devops-handbook-second-edition/">The DevOps Handbook</a>. It goes well beyond the basics of making IT processes more productive and efficient.</p>

<p>After realizing that small batch sizes are the key to success, I haven&#39;t lost a game of Carcassonne since. I hope you&#39;re not reading this, honey.🤭</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 068 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Serverless Framework Retrospective
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-28-serverless-framework-retrospective
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-28-serverless-framework-retrospective?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>A current project requires the infrastructure to be highly scalable. It&#39;s expected that &gt; 50k Users hit the platform within a five minute period. Regular ECS containers take about one minute to scale up. That just won&#39;t cut it. I decided to go all in on the <a href="https://www.serverless.com/">serverless</a> framework on AWS. Here&#39;s how it went.</p>

<h3>Setup</h3>

<p>Setting up a serverless application was a breeze. You create a config file and use their CLI to deploy the app.</p>

<h3>The rest of the infrastructure</h3>

<p>I decided to define the rest of the infrastructure (VPC, DB, cache, ...) in Terraform. But, since I wasn&#39;t familiar with how the Serverless Framework worked, I struggled to draw the line between what serverless should handle vs. what the rest of the infrastructure (Terraform) should provide. In a more traditional deployment workflow, you might let the CI deploy a container image to ECR and point the ECS service to that new image.</p>

<p>I chose to let Serverless deploy the entire app through CI and build the rest of the infrastructure around it. The problem with this approach is that we lose fine-grained control over what&#39;s deployed where, which leads to a lot of permission errors.</p>

<p>In retrospect, I should&#39;ve probably chosen the location of the S3 archive as the deployment target for the CI, and then point the lambda function to the location of the new artifact. This defeats the purpose of the framework, but it gives you a lot more control over your infrastructure. Once the next project comes along, I&#39;ll probably go that route instead.</p>

<h3>Permissions</h3>

<p>Serverless suggests to use admin permissions for deployments, and I see where they&#39;re coming from. Managing permissions in this framework is an absolute mess. Here&#39;s what the average deployment workflow looks like, if you want to use fine grained permissions:</p>

<ol><li>Wait for CloudFormation to roll back changes (~2 minutes)</li><li>Update IAM role</li><li>Deploy Serverless App</li><li>If there&#39;s an error, go to 1</li></ol>

<p>Thankfully, some people have already gone through the process of figuring this out. <a href="https://serverlessfirst.com/create-iam-deployer-roles-serverless-app/#determining-deploy-time-permissions">Here&#39;s</a> a great guide with a starting point of the needed permissions.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Using the serverless framework is a solid choice if you just want to throw an app out there. Unfortunately the app I was deploying isn&#39;t &quot;just&quot; a dynamic website. The next time I&#39;m building a serverless application it&#39;s probably not going to be with the Serverless Framework, though I learned a lot about serverless applications in general.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 067 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Migrating Homeassistant from SD to SSD
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-27-migrating-homeassistant-from-sd-to-ssd
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-27-migrating-homeassistant-from-sd-to-ssd?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I finally got frustrated with the performance of my Raspberry Pi 4 running Homeassistant on a SD card, so I went ahead and got an SSD.</p>

<p>The migration was <strong>very</strong> easy:</p>

<ol><li>Create and download a full backup through the UI</li><li>Flash Homeassistant onto the SSD</li><li>Remove the SD card and plug the SSD into a USB 3.0 port of the Pi</li><li>Boot</li><li>Go through the onboarding procedure</li><li>Restore Backup</li><li>Profit</li></ol>

<p>It worked like a charm! The speed has improved A LOT, and everything was set up as it should be. </p>

<p>...Until we turned on the lights in the livingroom. My ZigBee-dongle, plugged into another USB port, wasn&#39;t able to communicate with the devices on the network.</p>

<p>After some digging around, I came across several threads stating that an SSD over USB 3.0 apparently creates a lot of interference to surrounding hardware, including my ZigBee dongle. The fix was simple: either get an extension port for the dongle, or plug the SSD into a USB 2.0 port of the Pi. Since I didn&#39;t have an extension cord to get the dongle far away enough from the SSD, I went with the latter option for now. And that fixed it! The performance was much worse, but still better than the SD I used before. My next step will be to grab an extension cord from my parents. I&#39;m sure they won&#39;t mind.</p>

<p>I hope this helps!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 066 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                The role of a DevOps Engineer
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-22-the-role-of-a-devops-engineer
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-22-the-role-of-a-devops-engineer?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 22 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>The term &quot;DevOps&quot; can be interpreted in many different ways. It&#39;s often thrown around as a buzzword whenever somebody is talking about &quot;what comes after development&quot;. Obviously, it&#39;s not just that. Or is it? It depends on whom you&#39;re talking to.</p>

<p>Although I just recently started my new role as a &quot;DevOps Engineer&quot;, I&#39;m still discovering what that term means to me. I just had a fruitful conversation with the DevOps lead of a client, and they phrased this role in a very fitting way.</p>

<blockquote><p>A DevOps Engineer doesn&#39;t push the button, they enable the developers to push the button themselves.</p></blockquote>

<p>To me this role is fascinating, since it touches so many different aspects of software delivery.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 065 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Instant dark theme
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-12-instant-dark-theme
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-12-instant-dark-theme?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Thanks to <a href="https://jacksonchen666.com/">Jacksons</a> <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/darktheme.club/pull/79">update to darktheme.club</a>, I just came across a neat little <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/color-scheme">CSS property</a> that turns a mostly CSS-free document into a pleasantly dark site:</p>

<p><code>css
:root {
  color-scheme: light dark;
}
</code></p>

<p>This will adjust all elements on the page to the color scheme preferred by the user - without any other custom styles! 🤯 It is also <a href="https://caniuse.com/mdn-css_properties_color-scheme">widely supported</a> by browsers.</p>

<p>I&#39;ve always been quite dependent on CSS-frameworks for any project I&#39;m starting. Going forward, I&#39;d be interested to see how framework-less sites would feel using this property. If all else fails, there&#39;s always the awesome <a href="https://simplecss.org/">simple.css</a> library, which you can slap on top of a raw document to make it pretty (and dark, if preferred) without using custom classes.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 064 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Older is often better
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-07-older-is-often-better
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-07-older-is-often-better?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I&#39;m guilty of buying shiny new things. After being unhappy with the Bluetooth connectivity in the OnePlus Nord I bought in december of 2020, I bought a brand new Pixel 7 last december. I told myself that t would be using the OnePlus Nord for at least three years, preferably four, yet I gave in after two years due to some issue that could have been fixed with a pair of cable-headphones. I&#39;m now asking myself again: am I able to use my new Pixel 7 for more than 3 years?</p>

<p>I just stumbled upon a blog post called &quot;<a href="https://woodfromeden.substack.com/p/my-long-goodbye-to-windows-xp">My long goodbye to Windows XP</a>&quot;, in which the author explains that he is currently replacing his 2008 laptop running Windows XP with a &quot;new&quot; PC running Windows 7. He states that he knew the ins and outs of this operating system, so why switch to a new one? Eventually he did switch, but to an OS that is already end of life.</p>

<p>I totally love this. If you&#39;re happy with what you got, you shouldn&#39;t let a new feature dictate how to change your workflow. Does one really need the features introduced in some software/hardware/tool in the past year? Wouldn&#39;t it make sense to use the things that have been battle-tested for at least a few years?</p>

<p>As I said, I&#39;m very guilty of living at the cutting edge of technology. Maybe it&#39;s time to slow down. I&#39;m certain it would simplify a lot of things.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 063 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>