<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Sun, 10 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Short Story: Haunted Memories
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-10-short-story-haunted-memories
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-10-short-story-haunted-memories?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 10 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I had ventured deep into the heart of the forest that day, my heart alive with the joy of nature&#39;s embrace. The woods had called to me, and I, unwary of what lay ahead, had answered.</p>

<p>Beneath the green canopy, in the soft sunlight, I had walked along ancient trails, watched leaves fall to the forest floor, and breathed in the earthy scent of life. The sound of rustling leaves and chattering birds filled the air, and I wanted to capture these moments with my little device.</p>

<p>My phone, the recorder of my adventure, was like an extra eye. Every twisty tree and glistening stream, every play of light on a dewy leaf, I kept them all in digital form. It was my way of keeping a piece of nature&#39;s beauty.</p>

<p>When I got back home, I found myself alone, sitting in my comfy chair. I gazed at the screen, filled with memories of the day. Each swipe revealed a collection of images: the old trees, the winding paths, and the sun playing with the leaves. It was a familiar ritual, going through the day&#39;s photos.</p>

<p>Little did I know that this simple act would reveal a story of strange and unsettling things. As I looked at the pictures, the happy memories started to change. The forest seemed to hide something old and dark.</p>

<p>Amidst the familiar snapshots of trees and trails, one photo stood out, like a misplaced puzzle piece. I stared at it in confusion, for I had no memory of capturing this image. It was a peculiar blur, a distortion in the nature of my otherwise ordinary pictures.</p>

<p>As I swiped to the next image, I hoped to dismiss this oddity as a simple mistake. But with each passing second, my heart sank. The forest in the next photo, while clearly the same place, looked nothing like the serene woods I had hiked through earlier. This picture showed a twisted, distorted version of reality. The colors were dim, the trees bent in unnatural ways, and the sky turned an eerie shade of crimson. It felt like the world had shifted, and a creeping sense of fear washed over me.</p>

<p>My thumb swiped to the next image, my curiosity piqued and anxiety started manifesting at my insides. What I saw next sent a chill down my spine. The distortion had spread, like a creeping darkness, and it now shrouded the entire frame. The forest in the photo seemed to reveal an uncanny life of its own, as if it held secrets it had never intended to surface. The more I delved, the more my phone&#39;s screen seemed to protest, flickering and stuttering in its struggle to depict the incomprehensible. It was as if the very device I held in my shaky hand recoiled from the horrors unveiled, a witness to the sinister unraveling of a twisted reality.</p>

<p>With a shiver in my spine, I continued my descent into this abyss of photos. Each one was a descent deeper into the uncanny, the forest growing more distorted and nightmarish with every passing image. The very air seemed to grow heavy, pressing down on me, as if the forest itself disapproved of my presence.</p>

<p>My phone, now a reluctant accomplice in this unfolding nightmare, grew hotter with every image, as though its circuits strained to contain the eldritch force invading its digital realm. The terror I felt mirrored in the device&#39;s erratic behavior, a momentary dance of dread and malfunction that whispered of a cruel intelligence lurking just beyond the frame.</p>

<p>As the seconds turned into minutes, my heart raced. One last photo showed the forest in complete disarray, and there, amidst the chaos of the twisted woods, a formless void seemed to coalesce, lurking in the background.</p>

<p>This indescribable entity defied the very essence of reality. It was a shadowy figure, a blot upon the photograph that should not have been. Its proportions, though vaguely human, were maddeningly incomprehensible. The creature, if it could be called that, emitted an aura of profound wrongness, as though it were a fracture in the very essence of existence.</p>

<p>It lacked eyes, for it existed beyond the realm of vision, yet it gazed into the depths of my soul. Its presence was an disgrace to the senses, an intrusion into the harmony of the natural world. It was a thing of pure darkness, an incarnation of the void, and it appeared to call forth from the fringes of my comprehension, as if tempting me to explore its mystifying abyss.</p>

<p>My phone, seemingly unable to bear the weight of the strange, otherworldly images, emitted an unsettling, high-pitched whine. Extreme heat radiated from the device, and before I could react, it swelled and erupted into a burst of searing smoke, leaving nothing but a charred and twisted shell.</p>

<p>I was left paralyzed, my mind reeling with a terror beyond description. And as the acrid scent of burnt electronics hung in the air, I couldn&#39;t help but glance up, for I felt a presence, an impenetrable darkness, looming before me. It was as though the forest itself had birthed this malevolent entity, and it was now here, before my very eyes.</p>

<p>What happened next, I cannot say. Years have passed, and my memory remains shrouded in mystery, offering no answers. But one thing is certain: that unholy encounter left me forever changed, and I swore off digital devices, for fear of stirring the terrors that lurk beyond the screen.</p>

<p>From that day forward, I embraced nature with renewed compassion, still drawn to the inspiration of the woods. But I chose a different path for documenting my adventures, one free from the digital terror that had haunted me. A trusty notebook and an old ink pen became my companions, capturing the essence of my journeys as I ventured deeper into the heart of the wild. My hikes remained a source of clarity and inspiration, and through the ink-stained pages of my journal, I chronicled the world&#39;s beauty and wonder, preserving memories in the tangible, uncorrupted form of the analog.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: The characters and events portrayed in this story are entirely fictional. Any resemblance to real individuals, living or deceased, or to actual events is purely coincidental. Furthermore, portions of this story were developed with the assistance of artificial intelligence (AI) to enhance storytelling and brainstorm ideas.</p></blockquote>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 076 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                About My Pocket Notebook
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 09 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Since about a month, I&#39;ve been carrying a tiny pocket notebook with me wherever
I go. It&#39;s small enough to fit in every pocket imaginable. It doesn&#39;t need to
be recharged, it doesn&#39;t care if it gets wet. It&#39;s just right there whenever I
need it.</p>

<p><img alt="My Notebook on a recent hike" src="/assets/posts/2023-09-09-about-my-pocket-notebook/hike.jpeg"/></p>

<p>As someone living with ADHD, I often find myself overwhelmed by random thoughts and environmental stimuli. Writing my thoughts down on pen and paper helps a lot in those moments, but until now, I&#39;ve yet to come across a technique that stuck with me for an entire month. I take a lot of notes at work and I feel that it helps me stay organized, but I haven&#39;t found a way to use the same technique in my free time. I once tried keeping a notebook in my backpack, but there are moments where I just don&#39;t have my backpack with me, so I neglected it soon after I started.</p>

<p>That all changed when I stumbled across a video titled <a href="https://youtu.be/0xssCfBiUds?si=vxclEs1UxK5tlkL0">&quot;This pocket notebook is (slowly) replacing my phone&quot;</a>. It instantly clicked for me. Carrying a tiny notebook alongside my phone surely can&#39;t be that hard. And indeed, it isn&#39;t! At night, I put the notebook right next to my phone on my desk. After waking up, I grab my phone, and the notebook is right there for me to take as well. It&#39;s become a habit to check if the notebook is there, just like checking your keys when leaving the house.</p>

<p>Phones are optimized to grab your attention whenever and wherever you are. After hours of mindless scrolling through various feeds, I feel like the phone has won the war over me and I begin to feel tired and overwhelmed. Having a notebook always with me, I now get a sense of control over where I&#39;m allocating my attention. Instead of reaching for my phone, I might as well pull out the notebook and scribble whatever is on my mind in that moment. I get to choose what I&#39;m writing down, instead of mindlessly consuming content I&#39;m not even interested in.</p>

<p>In my current notebook, there are lists of things I did on some random day, ideas for side-projects, long paragraphs of unsorted thoughts, stamps I collected during a hike, and bad doodles of trees. It really doesn&#39;t matter <strong>what</strong> I&#39;m writing. It&#39;s about bringing awareness to what&#39;s on my mind.</p>

<h2>Notebook sizes</h2>

<p>I&#39;m still playing around with different sizes of notebooks. So far, I&#39;ve been using a <a href="https://www.moleskine.com/en-us/shop/notebooks/journals/volant-journals/volant-journals-forget-me-not-blue-and-amber-yellow-8058647620541.html">Moleskine Volant XS</a> notebook, which is 6.5 x 10 cm in size. It fits comfortably in the palm of my hand and easily slides in every pocket imaginable. I&#39;d say it&#39;s the perfect size for this purpose!</p>

<p><img alt="My current notebook" src="/assets/posts/2023-09-09-about-my-pocket-notebook/moleskine.jpeg"/></p>

<p>As this notebook comes to an end (it took about a month to fill), I want to try out the slightly larger <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/products/original-kraft">Field Notes</a> notebook. It&#39;s about 9 x 14 cm and <em>just barely</em> fits in my back pocket. My concern is that it&#39;s too big to carry in tighter pockets, but from what I&#39;ve read online so far, people seem to love this form factor. In my opinion Field Notes have a very unique vibe to them, and although the price is quite hefty (about 15€ for a pack of three, including shipping), they do make it up in style.</p>

<p><img alt="A Field Notes notebook" src="/assets/posts/2023-09-09-about-my-pocket-notebook/field_notes.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Field Notes also have awesome quarterly <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/limited-editions">limited editions</a> that give them an aspect of collectability (just look at their <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/products/national-parks">National Parks</a> series. They&#39;re gorgeous! 🤤). There&#39;s definetely a lot of hype around them, so if you don&#39;t care about the aesthetics, you can always opt for way cheaper alternatives from your local stationary store (around 2€ or lower).</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>After a month of carrying this notebook with me, I do feel that it increased my mental clarity quite a lot. I have a sense of control over my thoughts that I never had before. Whenever I&#39;m sitting down with my notebook and a pen, I instantly notice things around me that I wouldn&#39;t have noticed if I stared at my phone instead.</p>

<p>Notebooks and other so called &quot;EDC&quot; (everyday carry) items are a true rabbit hole (look it up, you&#39;d be surprised), and its easy to get lost in the details. If you&#39;re interested in trying this technique for yourself, just grab whatever tiny notebook you can find and <em>just write</em>.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 075 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                So, you want to win the lottery
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-08-23-so,-you-want-to-win-the-lottery
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-08-23-so,-you-want-to-win-the-lottery?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 23 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>The lottery is often used as a comparison for something that&#39;s far out of reach. But how far out of reach exactly is the lottery?</p>

<h2>1 in 302 Million</h2>

<p>Apparently, you have a 1 in 302 million chance to win the lottery. Well, that sounds like a lot... but how much is that exactly?</p>

<p>Imagine 66 bathtubs.</p>

<p>Now, imagine each of these bathtubs is filled to the brim with <strong>rice</strong>.</p>

<p>One of the grains of rice inside one of the bathtubs is painted gold. This is our jackpot.</p>

<p>Whenever you purchase a lottery ticket, imagine grabbing one grain of rice from this sea of bath tubs. Do you think you&#39;d have a chance to find the golden grain?</p>

<p>Source: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3Yn_3HqfV1w">The Scam No One Sees</a></p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 074 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Principles of DevOps: Flow
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-12-principles-of-devops--flow
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-12-principles-of-devops--flow?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 12 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>This post is part of a series called <a href="/posts?tags=PrinciplesOfDevOps">Principles of DevOps</a>.</p></blockquote>

<p>&quot;Flow&quot; refers to the performance of a system, as opposed to the performance of a specific silo or department.</p>

<p>In our daily work, we often only see what&#39;s inside our own silo. As a developer, we see requirements come in and code going out. In operations, we see code being pushed to a repository and pipelines deploying it to production. However, it&#39;s crucial to understand the flow of work in a broader context.</p>

<p>Most services or products have a &quot;value stream&quot; which describes how work is performed. You can think of the value stream as a carrier belt with multiple work centers. The first work center might be the business department, followed by a design team, a dev team, QA, operations and finally the customer. This structure might look different, depending on what product or service you are building.</p>

<h2>The flow of work should always go in one direction</h2>

<p>Work is typically generated at some point of the value stream. A requirement by the business department, an issue created by the QA team, an incident in operations, feedback from a customer, and so on.</p>

<p>Regardless of where the work originates, the flow of work should always go in one direction: forward. Work moving backwards, or even standing still, introduces bottlenecks that prevent downstream work centers from properly working. Always seek to resolve these bottlenecks as soon as possible.</p>

<h2>Always seek to increase flow</h2>

<p>The goal of almost any product or service is to bring value to the customer. More work flowing through the system means more value generated. But how do we increase the flow of work?</p>

<p><strong>Eliminate work in progress</strong>. This almost always indicates a bottleneck in one of the workcenters. Work should always flow smoothly through the system. If a ticket is stuck in one department for too long, ask why and how this can be avoided in the future.</p>

<p><strong>Match the pace of the customer</strong>. If the value stream is pumping out more features than the customer demands, you are not generating value to the business.</p>

<p><strong>Reduce work batch size</strong>. By <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-05-19-work-batch-sizing">iterating in small steps</a>, you can adapt to changes more quickly. Split up requirements into smaller tickets and increase the amount of deployments.</p>

<p>If you want to learn more about how to increase flow in a system, see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_constraints">theory of constraints</a> and the <a href="https://hbswk.hbs.edu/item/decoding-the-dna-of-the-toyota-production-system">Toyota production system</a>.</p>

<h2>Never unconsciously pass known defects downstream</h2>

<p>Aim to fix problems immedietely as they occur, especially if it&#39;s higher up in the value stream. Everyone should be responsible for the work of the entire value stream instead of just their work center.</p>

<p>If you notice work or problems being introduced multiple times, it&#39;s likely the upstream work center is unaware of this. Immediately seek awareness and work together on resolving it.</p>

<h2>Never allow local optimization to create global degradation</h2>

<p>Optimizing local work is important, but it should never introduce friction in other workcenters and, by extension, decrease performance of the value stream.</p>

<p>Local optimization is often linked to the &quot;tribal warfare&quot; between organizations (e.g. development vs. operations, business vs. development, etc.).</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Understanding and optimizing the flow of work within a value stream is crucial for achieving efficient and effective software delivery. By ensuring that work moves in one direction and continuously seeking to increase the flow, we can generate more value for customers and the business.</p>

<p>Eliminating bottlenecks, matching the pace of the customer, and reducing work batch size are all key strategies to enhance flow. Moreover, actively addressing known defects, promoting collaboration across the value stream, and avoiding local optimizations that hinder overall performance are essential for achieving successful outcomes. By embracing these principles, we can unlock the full potential of DevOps and drive continuous improvement in software delivery processes.</p>

<h2>Resources</h2>

<ul><li><a href="https://itrevolution.com/articles/the-three-ways-principles-underpinning-devops/">The Three Ways: The Principles Underpinning DevOps</a></li><li><a href="https://itrevolution.com/articles/elements-of-the-first-way-and-the-devops-implications/">Elements Of The First Way: And The DevOps Implications</a></li><li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_constraints">Theory Of Constraints</a></li><li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lean_IT">Lean IT</a></li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 073 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                PSA: RSS feed changes
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-06-rss-changes
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-06-rss-changes?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 06 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>If you&#39;re subscribed to this blog via <a href="/rss.xml">RSS</a>, you will soon likely see
a bunch of my posts re-appearing in your feed. For that, I apologize in advance!</p>

<p>I&#39;m planning to make two modifications. Firstly, I want to add a <code>id</code> property
to all entries. So far, your reader has been likely been relying on the URL slug
to identify an entry. Adding the <code>id</code> property makes this more flexible, but it
also means that your reader will think that there are new entries in the feed.
This will only happen once.</p>

<p>Secondly, I want to reduce the amount of the entries. If you look at the
<a href="/rss.xml">feed</a>, you&#39;ll see a lot of junk from way back, containing every word
I wrote on this blog. Remember that this page is fetched periodically (usually
every hour for most readers) by <strong>every</strong> subscriber. That&#39;s a lot of traffic
that could be better put to use somewhere else. Not that it costs me anything -
this site is hosted on <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> - but if this
helps reduce the carbon footprint of the site even by one gram, it&#39;s worth the
effort.</p>

<p>As of the time of writing this post, by restricting the number of posts to 10,
we reduce the amount of traffic per client per hour from 272 kB down to to 24
kB. That&#39;s over <strong>2 GB</strong> of traffic saved each year <strong>per subscriber</strong>!!</p>

<p>That&#39;s all - just a heads up. Thanks for your patience, you&#39;re awesome! ✌️</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 071 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Make a List
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-25-make-a-list
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-25-make-a-list?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 25 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>My dad taught me this important lesson. </p>

<p>Whenever you&#39;re feeling stuck or you don&#39;t know what to do, make a list. The next step will often become clear.</p>

<p>Whether you&#39;re going shopping or you&#39;re feeling mentally overloaded. It helps to write down your thoughts in an actionable form. I don&#39;t care if it&#39;s in some fancy mobile app or on a napkin. Just make a list.</p>

<p>Lists are the answer to almost anything. And where they&#39;re not, a spreadsheet is.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 070 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Single Page Applications on GitHub Pages
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-01-single-page-applications-on-github-pages
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-01-single-page-applications-on-github-pages?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>My latest project, <a href="https://sendpasswords.net/">sendpasswords.net</a> is a <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Glossary/SPA">Single Page Application</a> deployed on GitHub Pages.</p>

<p>GitHub Pages is configured in a way to host static HTML files without any bells and whistles. This means that if you try to fetch a document that&#39;s <em>not</em> the index, for example <code>/foo</code>, the server will try to load the file with that name. </p>

<p>By nature, SPAs only consist of a single HTML entry point (<code>index.html</code> in most cases). It&#39;s responsible for routing the user to the correct page if there are multiple paths. And here&#39;s the crux: if the user tries to load <code>/foo</code>, he will not land at the SPA entry point. Instead, he will see a <code>404</code> error.</p>

<h2>The solution</h2>

<p>A <code>404</code> response will automatically return a file called <code>404.html</code>, which we can use to our advantage. After building the application, simply copy the <code>index.html</code> to <code>404.html</code>, as demonstrated by <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/sendpasswords.net/commit/66bdb68c229a3ac3386f7816a746155e658eb586">this commit</a>. This will use <code>index.html</code> to serve the application on the root level, and <code>404.html</code> to load <em>the same app</em> if the page doesn&#39;t exist as a file. Whether the <code>index.html</code> is needed if there&#39;s already a <code>404.html</code> is up to you. I left it in to make clear that this is just a workaround.</p>

<p>This is a <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/69308662/9046809">well known</a> workaround, but I wanted to bring some extra awareness to it, since it&#39;s a problem I ran into a couple of times so far. Happy SPAing!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 069 (nice) of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Optimizing work batch size
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-05-19-work-batch-sizing
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-05-19-work-batch-sizing?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I&#39;ve been playing 
<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carcassonne_(board_game)">Carcassonne</a> a lot with my girlfriend recently. It&#39;s a boardgame about building cities, roads and farms, and each completed &quot;project&quot; earns you some amount of points. The twist is that there&#39;s only a limited number of tiles, and once all tiles are used, the game is over unfinished projects are discarded.</p>

<p>The first couple of playthroughs I tried to maximize my score by increasing the number of projects I actively had going. I&#39;d start a new city or road whenever I could, thinking that the multipliers you sometimes get would pay off in the end. Boy was I wrong.</p>

<p>Where I&#39;m from, we have multiple sayings for this approach. &quot;Having too many irons in the fire&quot; or &quot;dancing on too many parties&quot;. I was too busy starting new projects instead of making actual progress.</p>

<p>A far better approach is to finish projects early, earning less points, but with a greater certainty that they will pay off. With every project you start, the likelyhood of the other projects paying off decreases.</p>

<p>Keeping batch sizes small was a key concept of the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lean_manufacturing">lean manufacturing movement</a> in the 1980s, and has since been adopted by the <a href="https://de.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps">DevOps movement</a> for the IT industry. If you want to learn more about this topic, you should check out <a href="https://itrevolution.com/product/the-devops-handbook-second-edition/">The DevOps Handbook</a>. It goes well beyond the basics of making IT processes more productive and efficient.</p>

<p>After realizing that small batch sizes are the key to success, I haven&#39;t lost a game of Carcassonne since. I hope you&#39;re not reading this, honey.🤭</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 068 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Serverless Framework Retrospective
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-28-serverless-framework-retrospective
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-28-serverless-framework-retrospective?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>A current project requires the infrastructure to be highly scalable. It&#39;s expected that &gt; 50k Users hit the platform within a five minute period. Regular ECS containers take about one minute to scale up. That just won&#39;t cut it. I decided to go all in on the <a href="https://www.serverless.com/">serverless</a> framework on AWS. Here&#39;s how it went.</p>

<h3>Setup</h3>

<p>Setting up a serverless application was a breeze. You create a config file and use their CLI to deploy the app.</p>

<h3>The rest of the infrastructure</h3>

<p>I decided to define the rest of the infrastructure (VPC, DB, cache, ...) in Terraform. But, since I wasn&#39;t familiar with how the Serverless Framework worked, I struggled to draw the line between what serverless should handle vs. what the rest of the infrastructure (Terraform) should provide. In a more traditional deployment workflow, you might let the CI deploy a container image to ECR and point the ECS service to that new image.</p>

<p>I chose to let Serverless deploy the entire app through CI and build the rest of the infrastructure around it. The problem with this approach is that we lose fine-grained control over what&#39;s deployed where, which leads to a lot of permission errors.</p>

<p>In retrospect, I should&#39;ve probably chosen the location of the S3 archive as the deployment target for the CI, and then point the lambda function to the location of the new artifact. This defeats the purpose of the framework, but it gives you a lot more control over your infrastructure. Once the next project comes along, I&#39;ll probably go that route instead.</p>

<h3>Permissions</h3>

<p>Serverless suggests to use admin permissions for deployments, and I see where they&#39;re coming from. Managing permissions in this framework is an absolute mess. Here&#39;s what the average deployment workflow looks like, if you want to use fine grained permissions:</p>

<ol><li>Wait for CloudFormation to roll back changes (~2 minutes)</li><li>Update IAM role</li><li>Deploy Serverless App</li><li>If there&#39;s an error, go to 1</li></ol>

<p>Thankfully, some people have already gone through the process of figuring this out. <a href="https://serverlessfirst.com/create-iam-deployer-roles-serverless-app/#determining-deploy-time-permissions">Here&#39;s</a> a great guide with a starting point of the needed permissions.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Using the serverless framework is a solid choice if you just want to throw an app out there. Unfortunately the app I was deploying isn&#39;t &quot;just&quot; a dynamic website. The next time I&#39;m building a serverless application it&#39;s probably not going to be with the Serverless Framework, though I learned a lot about serverless applications in general.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 067 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Migrating Homeassistant from SD to SSD
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-27-migrating-homeassistant-from-sd-to-ssd
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-27-migrating-homeassistant-from-sd-to-ssd?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I finally got frustrated with the performance of my Raspberry Pi 4 running Homeassistant on a SD card, so I went ahead and got an SSD.</p>

<p>The migration was <strong>very</strong> easy:</p>

<ol><li>Create and download a full backup through the UI</li><li>Flash Homeassistant onto the SSD</li><li>Remove the SD card and plug the SSD into a USB 3.0 port of the Pi</li><li>Boot</li><li>Go through the onboarding procedure</li><li>Restore Backup</li><li>Profit</li></ol>

<p>It worked like a charm! The speed has improved A LOT, and everything was set up as it should be. </p>

<p>...Until we turned on the lights in the livingroom. My ZigBee-dongle, plugged into another USB port, wasn&#39;t able to communicate with the devices on the network.</p>

<p>After some digging around, I came across several threads stating that an SSD over USB 3.0 apparently creates a lot of interference to surrounding hardware, including my ZigBee dongle. The fix was simple: either get an extension port for the dongle, or plug the SSD into a USB 2.0 port of the Pi. Since I didn&#39;t have an extension cord to get the dongle far away enough from the SSD, I went with the latter option for now. And that fixed it! The performance was much worse, but still better than the SD I used before. My next step will be to grab an extension cord from my parents. I&#39;m sure they won&#39;t mind.</p>

<p>I hope this helps!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 066 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>