<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Notes on pruning chinese elms
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-12-24-notes-on-pruning-chinese-elms
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-12-24-notes-on-pruning-chinese-elms?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I recently bought a chinese elm bonsai. To keep it alive and healthy, I devoted
some time to learning how to properly prune it.</p>

<p>Chinese elms are very robust trees with strong growth. Even in the winter
season, I can prune it on a weekly basis. I just watched <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Nsvc2Ll1X2A">this
video</a> which gives some helpful
tips on pruning.</p>

<p>I noticed that the author let the tree grow heavily to develop stronger
branches. Until now, I pruned the branches back to one leaf whenever it had
about 5 leaves. However, a branch should only be cut on its woody parts in order
to develop more shoots, and a branch needs some growth in order to turn to wood.
<strong>Don&#39;t prune the branches too early</strong>!</p>

<p>Secondly, I thought that cutting the branches just behind a leaf would lead to
more growth, but I found that this is not true. The branches should be cut just
a bit above the leaf to prevent branch to die back and kill the leaf. It could
also lead to the shoot coming out straight instead of angled, which is not
desired.</p>

<p>Lastly I learned that branches pointing upwards should most likely be pruned,
since they take a lot of energy that the tree could use elsewhere, which is also
pointed out in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=93c985zOwhs">this video</a>.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s a picture of my chinese elm just how I bought it. You can clearly tell
that it was cheaply imported from china. It needs a lot of work, but I&#39;m having
a lot of fun learning about this tree!</p>

<p><img alt="Chinese Elm" src="/assets/chinese_elm.jpeg"/></p>

<p>This is post 022 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>