<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Fri, 22 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                10.000 Hours
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-22-10-000-hours
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-22-10-000-hours?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 22 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>In his book <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outliers_(book)">Outliers</a>, Malcolm Gladwell popularized the idea that it takes 10.000 hours of concentrated practice to master a skill.</p>

<p>According to my <a href="https://wakatime.com">WakaTime</a> stats, I spent 2.384 hours writing code in an editor (December 2023). If you&#39;re reading this post in the future, this is my current record:</p>

<p><a href="https://wakatime.com/@811525e7-5cc5-4eef-9e29-3cece3a03847"><img alt="wakatime" src="https://wakatime.com/badge/user/811525e7-5cc5-4eef-9e29-3cece3a03847.svg"/></a></p>

<p>This time is the time actually spent writing code. It doesn&#39;t track the time reading or thinking about it, nor the time spent in editors without the WakaTime plugin. It&#39;s hard to say how much time I spent engulfed in code, but this number is a good indicator as to how far I&#39;ve come in my programming journey.</p>

<p>I believe we should never say that we&#39;ve &quot;mastered&quot; a craft, even after spending 10.000 hours practicing it. There are always so many things to learn, so many novel ideas to catch up with.</p>

<p>So far, each of my 7 years of working as a software developer has advanced me tremendously. I&#39;m curious to see where I am once I reach 10.000 hours of practice.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 099 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Project Hail Mary
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-03-project-hail-mary
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-03-project-hail-mary?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just finished the book <a href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Hail_Mary">Project Hail Mary</a> by Andy Weir. Rating: ⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐</p>

<p>I&#39;m completely nerdsniped. I was looking forward to each chapter, eagerly waiting for what will happen next. This book is full of completely unexpected turns, though I never felt lost. The plot is well thought out. Every chapter is like a puzzle piece that perfectly adds to the greater picture.</p>

<p>When I first heard about this book I was a bit skeptical. &quot;Human stranded in space&quot; surely can&#39;t fill some 500 pages (I&#39;m looking at you, <a href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravity_(2013_film)">Gravity</a>). But having read <a href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Martian_(Weir_novel)#">The Martian</a> some time ago, I knew that Andy Weir&#39;s style of writing would catch me. And catch me he did. The way he describes complex topics completely resonates with me. No matter how unsolvable the problems of the protagonist seem, it&#39;s always an invitation to get your mind blown by the solution.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 080 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>