<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                TIL about CSS Insets
            </title>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-02-19-til-about-css-insets?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Just a quick tip that I thought is worth sharing. Instead of declaring:</p>

<p><code>css
.foo { 
  top: 0;
  right: 0;
  bottom: 0;
  left: 0;
}
</code></p>

<p>you can just use:</p>

<p><code>css
.foo {
  inset: 0;
}
</code></p>

<p>It&#39;s supported everywhere computers are sold!</p>

<p>MDN: https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/inset</p>

<p>Source: https://front-end.social/@estelle/109878532782943511</p>

<p>This is post 047 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Notes about BEM (Block Element Modifier)
            </title>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-02-02-bem-methodology?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 02 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>In the coming weeks, months and years, I will be working on frontend-development as part of my dayjob. These are some personal notes I took during my research about the BEM methodology. If you want to read the official introduction, you should visit <a href="http://getbem.com/">their website</a>.</p>

<h1>Overview - What is BEM?</h1>

<p>BEM — Block Element Modifier is a methodology that helps you to create reusable components and code sharing in front-end development. It aims to group css-classes in a meaningful way, making it easier to understand</p>

<ol><li>where this class is used</li><li>what it describes and</li><li>what state the element is in.</li></ol>

<p>The BEM-notation is divided into three main parts: Blocks, Elements and Modifiers.</p>

<h2>Blocks</h2>

<p>A standalone entity that is meaningful on its own. Some examples might be <strong>headers, containers, menus, inputs, checkboxes</strong>, etc.</p>

<h2>Elements</h2>

<p>A part of a block that has no standalone meaning and is semantically tied to its block. This could be a <strong>menu item or an input placeholder</strong>.</p>

<h2>Modifiers</h2>

<p>A flag on a block or an element. Used to change appearance or behavior. This might be <strong>disabled, checked, fixed, big</strong>, etc.</p>

<h1>Putting it together</h1>

<p>A block itself is referenced though its name.</p>

<p><code>css
.button {
}
</code></p>

<p>To reference elements inside of the block, you add it to the block element with two underscores (<code>__</code>):</p>

<p><code>css
.button {
}
.button__text {
}
</code></p>

<p>If you want to add a modifier to a block or an element, you separate it with two dashes (<code>--</code>):</p>

<p><code>css
.button {
}
.button--disabled {
}
.button__text--inverted {
}
</code></p>

<h1>Benefits of BEM</h1>

<p><strong>Modularity</strong>: Block styles never depend on one another. They can easily be moved to other parts of the app.</p>

<p><strong>Reusability</strong>: Composing styles in a meaningful way reduces the amount of code duplication.</p>

<p><strong>Structure</strong>: BEM gives your code a solid structure that is both easy to understand and to expand.</p>

<h1>References</h1>

<ul><li>http://getbem.com/</li><li>https://csswizardry.com/2013/01/mindbemding-getting-your-head-round-bem-syntax/</li></ul>

<p>This is post 009 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>