<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Custom Entities in Home Assistant
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2025-12-11-custom-entities-in-home-assistant
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2025-12-11-custom-entities-in-home-assistant?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>My local gym has a gauge on their website that shows an approximation of how many people are currently there. Being an avid <a href="https://www.home-assistant.io/">Home Assistant</a> user, of course I had to pipe that data into my dashboard somehow. For that, I created a simple <a href="https://n8n.io/">n8n</a> workflow that scrapes the data off the gym&#39;s site and dumps it into a custom entity.</p>

<p>Because creating a custom entity was not quite so straight forward as I&#39;d hoped, I wanted to share how I did it.</p>

<p>I ended up using the <code>input_number</code> integration (which seems to come with Home Assistant) and defined an entity that I could reference through the API:</p>

<p><code></code>`yaml</p>

<h1>configuration.yaml</h1>

<p>input<em>number:
  easyfitness</em>auslastung:
    name: EasyFitness Auslastung
    initial: 0
    min: 0
    max: 100
    step: 1
<code></code>`</p>

<p>After reloading the configuration, the entity was ready to be written to.</p>

<p>As mentioned, I&#39;m using a self-hosted instance of n8n on a Raspberry Pi to automate this. Using their <a href="https://n8n.io/integrations/home-assistant/">Home Assistant Integration</a>, you can simply address the new entity and update its state. And just like that, I was able to add a new Gauge to my dashboard!</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Migrating Homeassistant from SD to SSD
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-27-migrating-homeassistant-from-sd-to-ssd
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-27-migrating-homeassistant-from-sd-to-ssd?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I finally got frustrated with the performance of my Raspberry Pi 4 running Homeassistant on a SD card, so I went ahead and got an SSD.</p>

<p>The migration was <strong>very</strong> easy:</p>

<ol><li>Create and download a full backup through the UI</li><li>Flash Homeassistant onto the SSD</li><li>Remove the SD card and plug the SSD into a USB 3.0 port of the Pi</li><li>Boot</li><li>Go through the onboarding procedure</li><li>Restore Backup</li><li>Profit</li></ol>

<p>It worked like a charm! The speed has improved A LOT, and everything was set up as it should be. </p>

<p>...Until we turned on the lights in the livingroom. My ZigBee-dongle, plugged into another USB port, wasn&#39;t able to communicate with the devices on the network.</p>

<p>After some digging around, I came across several threads stating that an SSD over USB 3.0 apparently creates a lot of interference to surrounding hardware, including my ZigBee dongle. The fix was simple: either get an extension port for the dongle, or plug the SSD into a USB 2.0 port of the Pi. Since I didn&#39;t have an extension cord to get the dongle far away enough from the SSD, I went with the latter option for now. And that fixed it! The performance was much worse, but still better than the SD I used before. My next step will be to grab an extension cord from my parents. I&#39;m sure they won&#39;t mind.</p>

<p>I hope this helps!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 066 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>