<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Overcoming "air hunger"
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>For as long as I can remember, I often had the feeling of not being able to get a full breath. I&#39;m taking deep breaths and sometimes forcing a yawn to overcome this feeling, sometimes successful, sometimes failing and trying again. This feeling gets worse the more I focus on my breath.</p>

<p>I always felt like this is somewhat uncommon, since none of my friends and family can relate to this feeling, but it wasn&#39;t worse enough to justify consulting a doctor about it either.</p>

<p>Doing some research, it seems like this phenomenon is called <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortness_of_breath">dyspnea</a>, or &quot;air hunger&quot;. Some guy even made <a href="https://airhunger.org/">a website</a> about it. In a nutshell, it is caused by your body not being able to regulate carbon levels in your blood, which leads to an urge to breath unnaturally.</p>

<p>In a <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=XliOGg8Tl98">video</a>, the author points out that this might be caused by irregular breathing patterns. Indeed, I often find myself breathing through the mouth or sitting in awkward positions with a humpback when the symptoms are at its worst. In fact, what led me to look this up was because I was annoyed by the feeling while I&#39;m laying in bed staring down at my screen, which is a very unnatural position.</p>

<p>A simple trick to get into a more regular breathing pattern is apparently to force yourself to breathe through the nose. Mouth breathing lets your body take in way more air than you need, which throws off the balance of the carbon levels in your lungs.</p>

<p>It seems like nose breathing does work very well. Where I&#39;ve just been struggling with air hunger, once I forced myself to nose breathe, the urge to breathe doesn&#39;t come nearly as often anymore.</p>

<p>These are just my results after some quick research. The topic of short breathing seems to be quite broad. Perhaps you&#39;re struggling with this as well. In that case, I hope this post was helpful to you!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 095 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                I'm finally off coffee
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Disclaimer: There&#39;s no real story here — just a dump of my thoughts.</p>

<p>I used to drink two cups of coffee a day on average. One during breakfast and one during the day.</p>

<p>On days where it was difficult to get my hands on coffee — during camping for example, or on some days where I don&#39;t really have time to brew a coffee — I would routinely get headaches. This might have been a coincidence, but it&#39;s not unlikely that my body was craving this delicious drink. Waking up was always accompanied by this nagging feeling of how I&#39;m gonna get my dose of coffee today.</p>

<p>That all changed when I got sick a few weeks ago. I wasn&#39;t feeling well for a few days, and as a result I didn&#39;t drink coffee at all. Knowing that caffeine is a huge stress-inducing factor in my day to day life, I decided to just not start drinking it again once I felt better.</p>

<p>Quitting caffeine cold turkey can be difficult, but two cups isn&#39;t much. Some of my peers drink way more than that. While being sick, my body quickly adjusted to the missing two cups each day. I wasn&#39;t feeling good anyway, so what&#39;s an extra mild headache?</p>

<p>Now, about two weeks later, I feel great. There&#39;s one stress-factor less in my life. I occasionally still drink coffee with friends, but it&#39;s not something I crave directly after waking up. I opted for caffeine-free tea in the morning. We also have decaffeinated coffee at home, but it feels to me like brewing decaffeinated coffee isn&#39;t worth the effort. It&#39;s still a nice alternative for nice breakfasts on the weekend.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 094 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Field Notes #3
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Hooray! I just finished my third pocket notebook. If you have no idea what I mean, check out my <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">About My Pocket Notebook</a> post.</p>

<p>This notebook lasted from 2023-10-09 to 2023-12-01, which is a bit longer than my last two notebooks. I believe my inner hype around this topic slowly but surely fades into the background, which is a good thing. Instead of writing almost every single day, I only write in it when I feel that something is important.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3.jpeg"/></p>

<p>It aged quite well for a white notebook. You can clearly tell that I got some brand new pairs of jeans, looking at the color [before I used it](/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2#what&#39;s-next?) vs. now. Just like last time, I used this notebook for all sorts of things. Todo lists, bill calculations, random thoughts and sketches for blog posts.</p>

<p>What&#39;s different this time is that I started the book off with some &quot;meta pages&quot;. The first two pages serve as an index for the book. I ripped this idea stright from the <a href="https://bulletjournal.com/">Bullet Journal</a> movement, but that&#39;s about the only thing I stole from BuJos.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3 Index" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3_index.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I also dedicated one page to a general purpose packing list, which I used multiple times to check if I forgot anything for an overnight stay. This page served me very well, so I&#39;m transfering it into my new notebook.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>My next notebook will once again be a FIELD NOTES. I just love the size, the feel and the quality of them. This time, I&#39;m using the &quot;National Parks&quot; edition, or more specifically the &quot;Glacier National Park&quot; notebook from a set. It started to snow, so this is an obvious choice.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #4" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_4.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Thanks for sticking with me through this weird and awesome hobby!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 091 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                My App Defaults (Late 2023)
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-07-app-defaults
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-07-app-defaults?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 07 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Apparently there&#39;s currently a thing where people share their preferred apps. If you like this format, check out Robb Knight&#39;s <a href="https://defaults.rknight.me/">list of App Defaults blog posts</a>.</p>

<p>Without further ado, here&#39;s my list:</p>

<ul><li>📨 Mail Client: Thunderbird</li><li>📮 Mail Server: Purelymail</li><li>📝 Notes: <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">Pen &amp; Paper</a></li><li>✅ To-Do: <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">Pen &amp; Paper</a></li><li>🟦 Photo Management: Google Photos</li><li>📆 Calendar: Google Calendar</li><li>📁 Cloud File Storage: Google Drive</li><li>📖 RSS: Miniflux</li><li>🙍🏻‍♂️ Contacts: Google Contacts</li><li>🌐 Browser: Firefox</li><li>💬 Chat: WhatsApp</li><li>🔖 Bookmarks: Firefox</li><li>📑 Read It Later: Pocket</li><li>📜 Word Processing: Markdown, Google Docs</li><li>📈 Spreadsheets: Google Sheets</li><li>📊 Presentations: Google Slides</li><li>🛒 Shopping Lists: <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">Pen &amp; Paper</a></li><li>🍴 Meal Planning: <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">Pen &amp; Paper</a></li><li>💰 Budgeting and Personal Finance: GnuCash</li><li>📰 News: Mostly HackerNews via Miniflux</li><li>🎵 Music: Spotify</li><li>🎤 Podcasts: AntennaPod</li><li>🔐 Password Management: Bitwarden</li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 085 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Did you try turning it off?
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-10-did-you-try-turning-it-off
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-10-did-you-try-turning-it-off?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Planning our week, checking the time, suming up two numbers, reading a book. Often, digital devices are our default answer to a problem at hand. We&#39;ve become so used to being around a computer that we neglect that certain tasks could also be accomplished without it.</p>

<p>Often, we just need to <a href="/posts/2023-06-25-make-a-list">make a list</a>. Many of us have 10 todo-apps on our phone, each with its own bells and whistles. But do we really need those reminder notifications, tags, and priority levels? Most commonly, a pen and paper are all we need to remember what&#39;s on todays agenda.</p>

<p>The next time you&#39;re faced with a foreign problem, try asking yourself if whatever you&#39;re doing is worth the complexity of the solution. Often, though of course not always, the analog solution is most efficient.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 082 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Field Notes #2
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 09 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Today marks the completion of my second pocket notebook. You may view my <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">About My Pocket Notebook</a> post as part one of this series, since I wrote it near the end of my first notebook. I think it would be interesting to share my experience with this each notebook. One day I&#39;ll maybe have a nice history of posts that I can look back at. 🙂</p>

<p>This notebook lasted from 2023-09-10 to 2023-10-09, roughly one month. Here&#39;s a picture of it, after living in my back pocket every single day:</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #2" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_2.jpeg"/></p>

<h3>What&#39;s in it?</h3>

<p>I used this notebook as a todo list, a travel journal, quick sketches, braindumps, simple calculations and much more. It&#39;s become a place to dump thoughts whenever and wherever I want to. Sometimes, it&#39;s genuinely interesting facts, like how to find north when all you have is a clear night sky.</p>

<p><img alt="Notes on how to find north at night" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_2_page_5.jpeg"/></p>

<p>And sometimes it&#39;s just a random collection of uninteresting thoughts that wouldn&#39;t leave my head.</p>

<p><img alt="Random collection of notes" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_2_page_32.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Some of these notes may mature into a project or blog post, like <a href="/posts/2023-09-29-undo-on-mobile-phones">the second to last note on that page</a>, while others just fade into the abyss. But that&#39;s okay! The point is to get these thoughts out of my head to work with them more easily.</p>

<h3>What&#39;s next?</h3>

<p>I&#39;ll keep on writing! I got a bunch of new FIELD NOTES notebooks to fill up. Since my next notebook will likely live with me through the halloween season, I opted for the <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/products/harvest">Harvest</a> edition as my next notebook. 🎃</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_3.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I&#39;m curious to see where this one takes me.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 081 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                The Mind Rope Experiment
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-01-the-mind-rope-experiment
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-01-the-mind-rope-experiment?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Close your eyes. Picture yourself standing at a ledge with a rope tied to another ledge that&#39;s 10 steps away. Now, step by step, slowly walk across this rope until you&#39;re at the other side.</p>

<p>I often use this experiment as an indication for how focused I am at a given moment. As easy as this sounds, I rarely make it to the other side. On some days, I can&#39;t even step on the rope before my mind gets distracted and I have to start over. On some other days, I may get a few steps before falling off. With enough practice however, I may get to the other side.</p>

<p>This technique also works very well for short meditation sessions. I close my eyes and try to get to the other side. Whenever I fall off, I try again until my mind is focused enough to walk the entire rope.</p>

<p>I&#39;m curious: are you able to walk the entire rope, or are you also struggling to take control over this mindscape?</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 079 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                About My Pocket Notebook
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 09 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Since about a month, I&#39;ve been carrying a tiny pocket notebook with me wherever
I go. It&#39;s small enough to fit in every pocket imaginable. It doesn&#39;t need to
be recharged, it doesn&#39;t care if it gets wet. It&#39;s just right there whenever I
need it.</p>

<p><img alt="My Notebook on a recent hike" src="/assets/posts/2023-09-09-about-my-pocket-notebook/hike.jpeg"/></p>

<p>As someone living with ADHD, I often find myself overwhelmed by random thoughts and environmental stimuli. Writing my thoughts down on pen and paper helps a lot in those moments, but until now, I&#39;ve yet to come across a technique that stuck with me for an entire month. I take a lot of notes at work and I feel that it helps me stay organized, but I haven&#39;t found a way to use the same technique in my free time. I once tried keeping a notebook in my backpack, but there are moments where I just don&#39;t have my backpack with me, so I neglected it soon after I started.</p>

<p>That all changed when I stumbled across a video titled <a href="https://youtu.be/0xssCfBiUds?si=vxclEs1UxK5tlkL0">&quot;This pocket notebook is (slowly) replacing my phone&quot;</a>. It instantly clicked for me. Carrying a tiny notebook alongside my phone surely can&#39;t be that hard. And indeed, it isn&#39;t! At night, I put the notebook right next to my phone on my desk. After waking up, I grab my phone, and the notebook is right there for me to take as well. It&#39;s become a habit to check if the notebook is there, just like checking your keys when leaving the house.</p>

<p>Phones are optimized to grab your attention whenever and wherever you are. After hours of mindless scrolling through various feeds, I feel like the phone has won the war over me and I begin to feel tired and overwhelmed. Having a notebook always with me, I now get a sense of control over where I&#39;m allocating my attention. Instead of reaching for my phone, I might as well pull out the notebook and scribble whatever is on my mind in that moment. I get to choose what I&#39;m writing down, instead of mindlessly consuming content I&#39;m not even interested in.</p>

<p>In my current notebook, there are lists of things I did on some random day, ideas for side-projects, long paragraphs of unsorted thoughts, stamps I collected during a hike, and bad doodles of trees. It really doesn&#39;t matter <strong>what</strong> I&#39;m writing. It&#39;s about bringing awareness to what&#39;s on my mind.</p>

<h2>Notebook sizes</h2>

<p>I&#39;m still playing around with different sizes of notebooks. So far, I&#39;ve been using a <a href="https://www.moleskine.com/en-us/shop/notebooks/journals/volant-journals/volant-journals-forget-me-not-blue-and-amber-yellow-8058647620541.html">Moleskine Volant XS</a> notebook, which is 6.5 x 10 cm in size. It fits comfortably in the palm of my hand and easily slides in every pocket imaginable. I&#39;d say it&#39;s the perfect size for this purpose!</p>

<p><img alt="My current notebook" src="/assets/posts/2023-09-09-about-my-pocket-notebook/moleskine.jpeg"/></p>

<p>As this notebook comes to an end (it took about a month to fill), I want to try out the slightly larger <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/products/original-kraft">Field Notes</a> notebook. It&#39;s about 9 x 14 cm and <em>just barely</em> fits in my back pocket. My concern is that it&#39;s too big to carry in tighter pockets, but from what I&#39;ve read online so far, people seem to love this form factor. In my opinion Field Notes have a very unique vibe to them, and although the price is quite hefty (about 15€ for a pack of three, including shipping), they do make it up in style.</p>

<p><img alt="A Field Notes notebook" src="/assets/posts/2023-09-09-about-my-pocket-notebook/field_notes.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Field Notes also have awesome quarterly <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/limited-editions">limited editions</a> that give them an aspect of collectability (just look at their <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/products/national-parks">National Parks</a> series. They&#39;re gorgeous! 🤤). There&#39;s definetely a lot of hype around them, so if you don&#39;t care about the aesthetics, you can always opt for way cheaper alternatives from your local stationary store (around 2€ or lower).</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>After a month of carrying this notebook with me, I do feel that it increased my mental clarity quite a lot. I have a sense of control over my thoughts that I never had before. Whenever I&#39;m sitting down with my notebook and a pen, I instantly notice things around me that I wouldn&#39;t have noticed if I stared at my phone instead.</p>

<p>Notebooks and other so called &quot;EDC&quot; (everyday carry) items are a true rabbit hole (look it up, you&#39;d be surprised), and its easy to get lost in the details. If you&#39;re interested in trying this technique for yourself, just grab whatever tiny notebook you can find and <em>just write</em>.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 075 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                So, you want to win the lottery
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-08-23-so,-you-want-to-win-the-lottery
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-08-23-so,-you-want-to-win-the-lottery?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 23 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>The lottery is often used as a comparison for something that&#39;s far out of reach. But how far out of reach exactly is the lottery?</p>

<h2>1 in 302 Million</h2>

<p>Apparently, you have a 1 in 302 million chance to win the lottery. Well, that sounds like a lot... but how much is that exactly?</p>

<p>Imagine 66 bathtubs.</p>

<p>Now, imagine each of these bathtubs is filled to the brim with <strong>rice</strong>.</p>

<p>One of the grains of rice inside one of the bathtubs is painted gold. This is our jackpot.</p>

<p>Whenever you purchase a lottery ticket, imagine grabbing one grain of rice from this sea of bath tubs. Do you think you&#39;d have a chance to find the golden grain?</p>

<p>Source: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3Yn_3HqfV1w">The Scam No One Sees</a></p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 074 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Make a List
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-25-make-a-list
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-06-25-make-a-list?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 25 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>My dad taught me this important lesson. </p>

<p>Whenever you&#39;re feeling stuck or you don&#39;t know what to do, make a list. The next step will often become clear.</p>

<p>Whether you&#39;re going shopping or you&#39;re feeling mentally overloaded. It helps to write down your thoughts in an actionable form. I don&#39;t care if it&#39;s in some fancy mobile app or on a napkin. Just make a list.</p>

<p>Lists are the answer to almost anything. And where they&#39;re not, a spreadsheet is.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 070 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>