<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Making family IT support effortless (and free)
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2025-09-15-making-family-it-support-effortless-and-free
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2025-09-15-making-family-it-support-effortless-and-free?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Yesterday was one of those days where a family member had an issue with their computer. &quot;It doesn&#39;t open when I click it&quot; was all the information I had going into it. Debugging that through the telephone is just not happening.</p>

<p>I always stayed away from TeamViewer, because I was never really sure if that had a free plan, and the possibility of finding out mid-session that they don&#39;t have one was reason enough to save the hassle of yelling the installation instructions through the phone.</p>

<p>I remember hearing about <a href="https://rustdesk.com/">RustDesk</a> in a podcast a couple of years ago. The host claimed it to be a hassle-free open source replacement for TeamViewer, but by the time the next IT-support session arrived, I already forgot about it. Until yesterday!</p>

<p>Yesterday, I just didn&#39;t get enough information to be useful. I just needed a way to remotely access the computer, and that&#39;s then I remembered the promise of RustDesk. Going in blind, I quickly installed the client on my laptop and sent a mail with the instructions to my family member:</p>

<ol><li>Click here (a download link to the executable file)</li><li>Press the windows key</li><li>Type &quot;rust&quot; (to search for the file)</li><li>Press enter</li><li>Tell me the ID and the onetime password on the screen</li></ol>

<p>These instructions are fool-proof! And sure enough, they worked. I logged in and debugged the issue. No paywall, no corporate bullsh**, just a simple client that just works as intended out of the box. I was delighted to see that the plan has worked out. Going forward, Rustdesk will be my primary choice for remote IT support.</p>

<p>If you&#39;re interested: for some reason the browser window on their screen was resized to a tiny box near the edge of the screen, so whenever they clicked a bookmarked link on their desktop, instead of &quot;nothing happening&quot;, they just didn&#39;t see the page opening in the browser.</p>

<h2>TL;DR</h2>

<p>Use <a href="https://rustdesk.com/">RustDesk</a> instead of TeamViewer for a free and easy way to access your family&#39;s computer remotely.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                No matter what you do, always leave a breadcrumb
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2025-05-20-no-matter-what-you-do-always-leave-a-breadcrumb
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2025-05-20-no-matter-what-you-do-always-leave-a-breadcrumb?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This applies to work tasks just as much as it applies to hobbies. No matter what you do, always create some sort of breadcrumb that you or someone else can pick up down the line.</p>

<p>If you build a feature into your app, you&#39;ve generated an output, and therefore value. But what if you bang your head against the wall and don&#39;t make any progress? Write about it. Write about your challenges, document what you&#39;ve learned and share it with your peers. Not reaching a set goal doesn&#39;t mean failure. It&#39;s an opportunity to create value in a way you didn&#39;t anticipate.</p>

<p>If you&#39;re out on a run and a thought pops into your head, record a memo on your phone, or better yet: <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">keep a tiny notebook with you at all times</a>. Thoughts slip in and out of our heads at a very rapid pace. Capturing thoughts, even if you don&#39;t share them with anyone else, is a great way to generate value out of thin air.</p>

<p>If you&#39;re into crafty hobbies like woodworking, painting or baking, you likely know how important it is to finish a project. No matter how good or bad the outcome is, every finished project is an artifact that you can look back at later and see the progress you&#39;ve made.</p>

<p>Output always means value, even if it&#39;s not immediately apparent. Just keep on laying down those breadcrumbs.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                2024 in Review
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-12-29-2024-in-review
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-12-29-2024-in-review?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>It&#39;s super exciting looking back at 2024. So much has happened! I haven&#39;t been very active on this blog lately, mainly because I&#39;ve been super busy in other areas of life.</p>

<p>The biggest change for me this year is one that I can cross off of my <a href="/impossible">impossible list</a>: We bought a house! I&#39;ve been wanting to write post about this for a few weeks, and now that things are settling in, I might have the time to do that. In short: We moved from Brunswick (Germany) back to a more rural town just outside Brunswick. It&#39;s closer to my girlfriends workplace, closer to my family and overall way cheaper than properties in Brunswick. We&#39;re super happy about the house and have yet to find any major annoyances. The neighbors are nice, and the community is incredibly wholesome.</p>

<p>As for other personal projects, there hasn’t been as much traction as there used to be. My interests have partially shifted to hobbies that don’t involve a computer, which I’m grateful for. I still love building software projects – especially now that it’s become so easy to get started with a project using an AI brainstorming companion – I just do it less often. I picked up running as a hobby (more on that later), gather with friends to play Dungeons &amp; Dragons and work on stuff in my new basement.</p>

<h2>Goal Results</h2>

<p>These are the goals <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review">I set myself for 2024</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Build a side project that generated at least 100€ of value</p></blockquote>

<p>That’s a bust. As mentioned, I haven’t really spent a lot of time building side projects. And the ones I did build, I consider tools rather than an income stream.</p>

<blockquote><p>Get a scuba diving license</p></blockquote>

<p>I’m a certified PADI Open Water Diver! You can see some impressions <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket">here</a> and <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam">here</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Do a 10 km run (I really need to start moving again)</p></blockquote>

<p>I ran three 10k runs this year. <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/11416831567">The first in May</a>, then in <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/11768631707">June</a> and finally, <a href="https://strava.app.link/P0Ulu4L1IPb">in September</a>, I improved my 2018 personal best by a few minutes!</p>

<blockquote><p>Sell my car</p></blockquote>

<p>Check. More infos <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car">here</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Write at least 50 blog posts</p></blockquote>

<p>I didn’t reach this goal, but I’m also not disappointed by it. <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity">The frequency of my posts varies</a>, and this year it was just lower than before.</p>

<h2>2025 Goals</h2>

<p>Here are some new goals for this year:</p>

<ul><li>Build a side project that generated at least 100€ of value (I’m keeping this goal until I reach it!)</li><li>Run a half marathon (and optionally <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/985747064">beat my PB</a>)</li><li>Learn woodworking and build something that takes at least 3 days to complete</li></ul>

<h2>Prediction Results</h2>

<p>The results for <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review">last years predictions</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Bitcoin will at last reach a value of 100,000$, following the<a href="https://www.nicehash.com/countdown/btc-halving-2024-05-10-12-00"> halving</a> likely happening in 2024</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/business/markets/bitcoin-100000-rcna181008">Bitcoin did reach 100,000$</a>, though not following the halving event. Still, I’d call this a pass!</p>

<blockquote><p>SpaceX will use a <a href="https://www.spacex.com/vehicles/starship/">Starship</a> prototype to launch Starlink satellites into orbit</p></blockquote>

<p>Nope, they didn’t. But they made incredible leaps.</p>

<blockquote><p>Tesla cars a still not fully self driving (<a href="https://motherfrunker.ca/fsd/">reference</a>)</p></blockquote>

<p>They claim to launch it in Europe <a href="https://www.euronews.com/next/2024/09/05/tesla-says-full-self-driving-car-expected-in-europe-early-next-year-pending-regulatory-app">earlier next year</a>. It’s currently in closed testing. Still, I wouldn’t give it a pass.</p>

<blockquote><p>Google will replace their main search with an AI chat bot (see<a href="https://bard.google.com/"> Bard</a>)</p></blockquote>

<p>Not sure if I’d call Gemini a full replacement, but it does have a wrapper around their traditional search engine. The product is shit compared to Anthropic and OpenAI, but I would call this a pass, since you can use Gemini instead of Google Search.</p>

<h2>2025 Predictions</h2>

<ul><li>Apple will not ship a successor to the Apple Vision Pro</li><li>At least one country will mandate AI watermarking for all AI-generated content used in commercial applications</li><li>Russia and Ukraine will come to a consensus and end the war. Ukraine will have lost territory</li></ul>

<p>And that&#39;s a wrap. I hope you all had a wonderful Christmas (if celebrated), and are as excited as I am for the new year!</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Mental AI Fog and how to cure it
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-09-01-AI-fog
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-09-01-AI-fog?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>The term &quot;AI Slop&quot; is currently on the rise. It describes all the AI generated images and texts we see on the internet. I&#39;d like to propose a term that basically describes reverse AI Slop: <strong>Mental AI Fog</strong>.</p>

<p>Instead of <em>consuming</em> too much AI generated content (which also applies), AI Fog describes the inability to <em>produce</em> content without the help of AI. We&#39;re surrounded by flowery written articles and resources that we think that it&#39;s not worth it to put in the effort to write a text ourselves. This is comparable to how computer keyboards, spellchecking and autocorrection have rendered my generation and the ones to come incapable of comfortably writing longform text.</p>

<p>I&#39;m currently strongly suffering from AI fog. I&#39;m so used to letting some LLM flesh out a quick and dirty prompt nowadays that it&#39;s hard for me to write this text, get the point across and not feel insecure about my style of writing. This site is supposed to be a way to persist my thoughts whenever I want to, but are they still <em>my</em> thoughts if they have been proofread and corrected by a computer?</p>

<p>As a result, all these thoughts are piling up in my head. Where I previously braindumped thoughts on a piece of paper, I now only come up with a couple of words and let the AI elaborate. <strong>I&#39;m consuming what are supposed to be my own thoughts</strong>, which perpetuates the cycle.</p>

<p>This needs to stop. I need to get back <strong>creating</strong> things myself. I decided to abandon the use of LLMs for most content on this site. And where AI has been used, it will be clearly mentioned. I&#39;m contemplating adding some sort of &quot;Backed by AI&quot; label for certain pages to make it harder for myself to fall back to a helping hand. I will likely still be using LLMs, but making it obvious will force me to mindfully choose where it will be used.</p>

<p>Is this something you can relate to? Is AI fog even a fitting term for this? I don&#39;t know. And if it isn&#39;t, that&#39;s okay because I came up with it myself.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                About my 'smart' G-Shock
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-10-about-my-smart-g-shock
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-10-about-my-smart-g-shock?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 10 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>About two weeks ago, I got myself my very first G-Shock. My entry ticket to the <a href="https://mastodon.social/tags/CasioCult">#CasioCult</a>! Since I didn&#39;t want to miss out on any fitness features, I went with the <a href="https://www.casio.com/de/watches/gshock/product.DW-H5600-1/">G-Shock GW-H5600</a>, which comes with heart rate monitoring, step tracking and some other nice to have features.</p>

<p><img alt="A G-Shock DW-H5600" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/ab17acee-5997-4a3d-8536-c8c8243d72d2"/></p>

<p>Having read every review I could find, I knew that the watch had some quirks, but I ultimately loved the look of it. But two weeks later, I&#39;m forced to return the watch. Let me first go over what I liked and dislike about this watch.</p>

<h2>Pros</h2>

<p><strong>It&#39;s a G-Shock</strong></p>

<p>I love the look and feel of a G-Shock and other Casio watches. This is my first G-Shock, but I&#39;ve had an eye on this brand for quite some time. It&#39;s tough, sturdy, waterproof and probably also bullet proof.</p>

<p><strong>The display</strong></p>

<p>Oh, the display! It&#39;s gorgeous. Many people are complaining why this MIP display hasn&#39;t found its way to the rest of the G-Shock lineup. But I&#39;m sure they will retrofit other models soon.</p>

<p><strong>Proper paper manual</strong></p>

<p>My first impression after the unboxing was &quot;holy sheers, the manual is a <strong>book</strong>&quot;! And I mean that in the best way possible. Every little feature of the watch is explained in extreme detail in the manual. You rarely see this in other watches or gadgets these days.</p>

<h2>Cons</h2>

<p><strong>Questionable UI and UX decisions</strong></p>

<p>G-Shocks are known for user interfaces that &quot;just work&quot;. In this watch however, there are a few things that really make the watch frustrating to operate. Just to name a few quirks:</p>

<ul><li>There&#39;s only &quot;forward&quot;. If you scrolled passed something, you have to go aaaaall the way through the menu.</li><li>The timer can only be increased in 30 second steps. The UI is quite laggy, so setting a 10 minute timer takes about 1 minute of mashing buttons. There&#39;s also no press and hold.</li><li>The stopwatch only counts in seconds. No milliseconds.</li><li>You&#39;re locked to one task at a time. If you have a timer running, you can&#39;t go out of the menu. If you&#39;re recording a workout, you can&#39;t change the settings. And my favorite: You have to be on the home screen to sync settings from your phone to your watch. Just ... why?!</li><li>With a more or less recent update, the light now always turns on when you press any button. This makes the &quot;light&quot; button on the top right completely obsolete.</li><li>Unspecific battery indicator. You have four bars in the battery icon, that&#39;s it. The watch is solar powered, but it&#39;s to top up the battery at best. Don&#39;t expect to run fully off solar with this watch.</li></ul>

<p><strong>A bit thick</strong></p>

<p>Below the already thick bezel of the G-Shock sits the heart rate monitor, which is obnoxiously huge. I personally didn&#39;t feel like it irritated my skin, but it does add to the thickness.</p>

<p><strong>Fitness Features</strong></p>

<p>This is a two-edged sword. I originally wanted to list this as a pro. Features like run tracking, cardio status and sleep analysis are there, and they work fine. The step tracking and heart rate monitoring can be a bit off from time to time, but it&#39;s fine for the occasional run.</p>

<p>What&#39;s really bothering me is the mediocre implementation. There&#39;s no workout detection, the autopause feature barely works and you&#39;re limited to running, walking, gym workout and interval training. I also want to log my bike rides, which will always show up as a running activity in my app.</p>

<p>They recently added Strava integration, which sort of works. The data is all there, but for some reason the pace and moving time that Strava computes are completely off. For example, I ran 55 minutes straight with an average pace of 9 minutes / km. But with the data the watch sends, Strava thinks I only moved for 26 minutes with a pace of 4 minutes / km. If that were true, I could compete in the olympics! 😅</p>

<p><strong>Notifications barely work</strong></p>

<p>During the time I owned the watch, there was only one random day where the watch received notifications from my phone. I can&#39;t explain why, but I just didn&#39;t get this to work properly.</p>

<p><strong>Case is not screwed in. Could fall off</strong></p>

<p>This is just a minor thing if you really care about durability. All G-Shock squares so far had screwed in bezels. On this model, you can pull off the bezel with enough force. I&#39;ve never done it, but losing the bezel might be a concern.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>I enjoyed my time with this watch, but I filed a return. As pretty as the watch is, it is just too frustrating to use. Smart watches aren&#39;t a core part of Casio&#39;s business, and you can feel that in the lack of quality of the software. The app was likely developed as a one-off contract by some random agency, and once the contract ends, the watch won&#39;t ever be improved again.</p>

<p>I&#39;ve now ordered the <a href="https://www.garmin.com/de-DE/p/741462">Garmin Instinct 2S Solar</a>, which is very similar in terms of specs. MIP display, top-up solar charging, long-lasting battery and fitness features. But on top of that, it has features like music control, GPS, contactless payment and a compass. Contrary to Casio, Smartwatches are a core part of Garmin&#39;s business, which makes me believe that they go out of their way to develop the best possible watch they can. I will likely follow up with how this new watch compares to my G-Shock.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                I sold my car
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 08 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I grew up in the countryside, where busses only came once an hour, but only until 7 PM. And on the weekend, you <strong>really</strong> had to plan ahead. Living without a car was almost unthinkable.</p>

<p><img alt="My car" src="/assets/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car/my-car.jpeg"/></p>

<p>After moving to the city in 2020, I found that I used my car less and less. My commute to work was easier with the bike (if I wasn&#39;t working from home), and for anything else, busses and trams were the way to go. The occasional family visit was the only excuse to use my car.</p>

<p>Owning a car doesn&#39;t &quot;feel&quot; expensive. Sure, gas is expensive, but simply owning one doesn&#39;t feel like a huge burden on your wallet. Just to get a rough estimate, I jotted down all running costs.</p>

<p><img alt="Running costs" src="/assets/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car/running-costs.jpeg"/></p>

<p>My car costs <strong>over 1000€ per year</strong>, or about 85€ per month, just to be moved about twice a month! So, a few weeks ago, I decided to sell it.</p>

<p>I created a posting on <a href="https://www.kleinanzeigen.de/">Kleinanzeigen</a> (a german descendant of - and previously owned by - eBay), and after about two weeks, the car had a new owner. I hope that it&#39;s in better hands now and lives on to be a happy and frequently used car.</p>

<p>Going forward, I&#39;m not worried about my mobility at all. My partner still owns her car and has the option to take the bus to work. So, if we&#39;re not on the road together, I can always fall back to using her car. And if she needs her car and I&#39;m desperate to go somewhere afar, there&#39;s also multiple ride-sharing options available in my town. They are a bit expensive to use, but spending 40€ for a day trip to my family every two months is still way less than paying 85€ a month for a car that&#39;s sitting there idle.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Beating Elden Ring
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-10-beating-elden-ring
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-10-beating-elden-ring?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p><strong>⚠️ WARNING ⚠️</strong>: This post contains a lot of spoilers for the game Elden Ring.</p></blockquote>

<p>So, I just beat Elden Ring. It took me 120 hours and, coincidentally, I was level 120 when I beat the final boss. That damn final boss... but more on that later.</p>

<p>Elden Ring won me over instantly, even though I&#39;ve never played any of the other Souls games. After beating <a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Legend_of_Zelda:_Breath_of_the_Wild">Breath of the Wild</a>, I called it my favorite game. I just needed more games like this. When Elden Ring came out, people compared The Lands Between to the open world of Hyrule, and I quickly agreed. The freedom these games give you is absolutely unbeaten. You almost never really get &quot;stuck&quot; on something. You can always wonder off and explore until you&#39;re ready to take on the fight.</p>

<p>After about 50 hours into playing Elden Ring, I kind of lost my focus and stopped playing for a while. It was too huge of a game to beat at the time, so I gave up.</p>

<p>But then, <a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Legend_of_Zelda:_Tears_of_the_Kingdom">Tears of the Kingdom</a> came out and doubled up on the world of Hyrule. I absolutely adored this game. I spent day and night playing until I finally beat it. This game also motivated me to beat Elden Ring one more time. Despite failing over and over, each play session gave me a feeling of progression. I might not have beaten a boss yet, but there was always something happening the side that got me closer to beating it. Be it exploring and getting better gear or learning as much as I can about a boss to find ways to deal damange, I always got a small step closer to my goal. I&#39;d go as far as to say I never felt so determined to reach a goal ever before in my life.</p>

<p>The boss fights in Elden Ring are obviously extremely difficult, but they&#39;re always fair. The bosses in this game never make mistakes, you&#39;re the one that screwed up. You just keep failing and failing, but with each run, you learn something new about the fight that makes it easier in the next run. And when you finally overcoming this challenge gives you a feeling of accomplishment like nothing else could.</p>

<p>What I didn&#39;t realize in the beginning of my playthough is how extremely well rounded the world and the lore of this game is. I spent days and nights indulging myself in the lore through numerous YouTube videos, guides and Wikis. Only then did I begin to understand the scale of this game. Every action of each character, every building and every item fits in the grand scheme of the world.</p>

<p>Going out of this, the biggest thing that stuck with me is the determination. Failing is part of your life, and that is okay. No matter how daunting a task is, there&#39;s <strong>always</strong> a way to overcome it. The Elden Beast is the final boss of the game, and it&#39;s also where I spent about a quarter of my playtime. This thing has absurd attacks, immense health, and did I mention that you have to beat it after beating another extremely difficult boss, without being able to top up your health? This fight is ridiculous. I spent multiple weeks trying to beat it. I was really close to giving up, but as I mentioned earlier, each run gets you a tiny bit closer to the finish line, so I pushed through. I refined my build, I leveled up my stats and I learned how to dance with the beast. Eventually, I won the fight not by luck, but by determination. I now feel like I understand every attack well enough to dodge it. My mind was on autopilot when I beat it.</p>

<p>Knowing this much about a game didn&#39;t teach me any practical skills. There&#39;s nothing I can do now that I couldn&#39;t do before I knew that Rykard (Lord of Blasphemy), son of Rennala and Radagon (also known as Queen Marika), chose to go against the Erdtree and eventually fed himself to a serpent to devour the entire world (which you prevented). But there&#39;s something about this game that left me craving for more. It&#39;s truly a masterpiece.</p>

<h2>Bonus</h2>

<p>In case you&#39;re interested, I uploaded some of the bossfights during my playthrough in this YouTube playlist:</p>

<p>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?si=j1Ue2lrrLy1JTOM9&amp;amp;list=PLS8TKBZz1x5S6ojf24SMF1h_HYb4AyTxc&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Toil
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-01-toil
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-01-toil?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>After cheating death himself, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sisyphus">Sisyphus</a> was punished to push a large boulder up a steep hill for eternity. Every time he reached the top, the boulder would roll back down and Sisyphus had to start over.</p>

<p>Our life is full of such toil. Mowing the lawn, cleaning the dishes and doing our taxes are examples of toil that prevents us from doing sustainable work. We should always seek to minimize toil where possible. We have dishwashers and spam filters to help us fight toil, but there are some reoccurring tasks that cannot be automated.</p>

<p>Sisyphus eventually found peace with his fate. Instead of seeing his punishment as an eternal burden, he saw it as his life&#39;s purpose. Maybe those comparatively small annoyances in our life are worth enjoying. They&#39;re part of what makes us human.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Dive Log: Vietnam
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>So, after our <a href="/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket">adventures in Phuket</a>, we journeyed on to Nha Trang in Vietnam, where we also went diving.</p>

<p>Unfortunately the visibility was average, and the wildlife in Nha Trang wasn&#39;t as diverse as in Phuket, but that only made the hermit crabs or the occasional lionfish feel just that much more special.</p>

<p>In total, we did 4 dives in Nha Trang. Here&#39;s a full list, taken from my logbook:</p>

<p>| Title       | Date       | Site       | Depth (m) | Time (min) | Highlights                   |
| ----------- | ---------- | ---------- | --------- | ---------- | ---------------------------- |
| Nha Trang 1 | 2024-02-25 | Dam Bay    | 12        | 45         | Cold water and sandy bottom  |
| Nha Trang 2 | 2024-02-25 | Mot Island | 13.5      | 45         | Squids and lots of anemones  |
| Nha Trang 3 | 2024-02-26 | Tam Island | 11.2      | 37         | Playing around with bouyancy |
| Nha Trang 4 | 2024-02-26 | Tam Island | 10        | 46         | Hermit crabs                 |</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Dive Log: Phuket
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just became a certified diver! 🥳</p>

<p>I got my license through the <a href="https://rumblefishadventure.com/">Rumblefish Adventure</a> divecenter in Kata Beach, as per a recommendation from a friend who happened to be around in the area when we were there.</p>

<p>Kata Beach is a great dive spot. It has crazy wildlife, it&#39;s just a short swim away from the beach and the visibility is quite good if you haven&#39;t seen many reefs yet (like myself).</p>

<p>After doing our PADI Open Water license, we went to Phi Phi Islands to do a fun dive. The experience swimming through the reefs there can simply not be put into words.</p>

<p>In total, we did 7 dives in Thailand. Here&#39;s a full list, taken from my logbook:</p>

<p>| Title                 | Date       | Site              | Depth (m) | Time (min) | Highlights                                         |
|-----------------------|------------|-------------------|-----------|------------|----------------------------------------------------|
| Open Water Training 1 | 2024-02-16 | Kata Beach        | 6.4       | 39         | First time seeing the reef!                        |
| Open Water Training 2 | 2024-02-18 | Kata Beach        | 10.9      | 62         | Almost finished all mandatory training             |
| Open Water Training 3 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 16.3      | 44         | Artificial reefs with lots of interesting wildlife |
| Open Water Training 4 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 12.9      | 48         | Even more crazy wildlife                           |
| Phi Phi Islands 1     | 2024-02-20 | Koh Bida Nok      | 20.5      | 51         | Sharks!                                            |
| Phi Phi Islands 2     | 2024-02-20 | Turtle Rock       | 17.6      | 55         | Turtles, Sharks, Cave                              |
| Phi Phi Islands 3     | 2024-02-20 | Shark Point       | 20.4      | 46         | Lots of verticality                                |</p>

<h2>Photos</h2>

<p><img alt="P2170670 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1d00d17d-a889-417d-a4c9-8dd83eff58f9"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170752 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d3b80e60-2155-481f-8232-a5a57b3898ab"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170727 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/25e75fb1-dec7-4ad2-89a9-d929144cd60a"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170759 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1f9c2c0f-cc2e-440a-9bba-2a03c984f301"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180898.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/7f33d8a9-1d5f-4f94-87de-6078233be6a8"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180901.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/e1caf403-4ea2-4dce-a48c-1a0b5b5ce360"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180859.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/6fe5e666-0099-445f-bdcc-35bc0e5e9943"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170749 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d6a239a8-fb98-478a-9e38-d15e3587a7b4"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180837 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/50fe5c89-f1cb-4a73-aac0-f1311a3116fc"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170733 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d44f52a2-2228-4a3e-801d-930f0eddf975"/></p>

<p>After Phuket, we went to Vietnam where we&#39;re currently also on a lot of fun diving trips. But I&#39;ll save that for another dive log post.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>