<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Wed, 08 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                I sold my car
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 08 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I grew up in the countryside, where busses only came once an hour, but only until 7 PM. And on the weekend, you <strong>really</strong> had to plan ahead. Living without a car was almost unthinkable.</p>

<p><img alt="My car" src="/assets/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car/my-car.jpeg"/></p>

<p>After moving to the city in 2020, I found that I used my car less and less. My commute to work was easier with the bike (if I wasn&#39;t working from home), and for anything else, busses and trams were the way to go. The occasional family visit was the only excuse to use my car.</p>

<p>Owning a car doesn&#39;t &quot;feel&quot; expensive. Sure, gas is expensive, but simply owning one doesn&#39;t feel like a huge burden on your wallet. Just to get a rough estimate, I jotted down all running costs.</p>

<p><img alt="Running costs" src="/assets/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car/running-costs.jpeg"/></p>

<p>My car costs <strong>over 1000€ per year</strong>, or about 85€ per month, just to be moved about twice a month! So, a few weeks ago, I decided to sell it.</p>

<p>I created a posting on <a href="https://www.kleinanzeigen.de/">Kleinanzeigen</a> (a german descendant of - and previously owned by - eBay), and after about two weeks, the car had a new owner. I hope that it&#39;s in better hands now and lives on to be a happy and frequently used car.</p>

<p>Going forward, I&#39;m not worried about my mobility at all. My partner still owns her car and has the option to take the bus to work. So, if we&#39;re not on the road together, I can always fall back to using her car. And if she needs her car and I&#39;m desperate to go somewhere afar, there&#39;s also multiple ride-sharing options available in my town. They are a bit expensive to use, but spending 40€ for a day trip to my family every two months is still way less than paying 85€ a month for a car that&#39;s sitting there idle.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Beating Elden Ring
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-10-beating-elden-ring
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-10-beating-elden-ring?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p><strong>⚠️ WARNING ⚠️</strong>: This post contains a lot of spoilers for the game Elden Ring.</p></blockquote>

<p>So, I just beat Elden Ring. It took me 120 hours and, coincidentally, I was level 120 when I beat the final boss. That damn final boss... but more on that later.</p>

<p>Elden Ring won me over instantly, even though I&#39;ve never played any of the other Souls games. After beating <a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Legend_of_Zelda:_Breath_of_the_Wild">Breath of the Wild</a>, I called it my favorite game. I just needed more games like this. When Elden Ring came out, people compared The Lands Between to the open world of Hyrule, and I quickly agreed. The freedom these games give you is absolutely unbeaten. You almost never really get &quot;stuck&quot; on something. You can always wonder off and explore until you&#39;re ready to take on the fight.</p>

<p>After about 50 hours into playing Elden Ring, I kind of lost my focus and stopped playing for a while. It was too huge of a game to beat at the time, so I gave up.</p>

<p>But then, <a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Legend_of_Zelda:_Tears_of_the_Kingdom">Tears of the Kingdom</a> came out and doubled up on the world of Hyrule. I absolutely adored this game. I spent day and night playing until I finally beat it. This game also motivated me to beat Elden Ring one more time. Despite failing over and over, each play session gave me a feeling of progression. I might not have beaten a boss yet, but there was always something happening the side that got me closer to beating it. Be it exploring and getting better gear or learning as much as I can about a boss to find ways to deal damange, I always got a small step closer to my goal. I&#39;d go as far as to say I never felt so determined to reach a goal ever before in my life.</p>

<p>The boss fights in Elden Ring are obviously extremely difficult, but they&#39;re always fair. The bosses in this game never make mistakes, you&#39;re the one that screwed up. You just keep failing and failing, but with each run, you learn something new about the fight that makes it easier in the next run. And when you finally overcoming this challenge gives you a feeling of accomplishment like nothing else could.</p>

<p>What I didn&#39;t realize in the beginning of my playthough is how extremely well rounded the world and the lore of this game is. I spent days and nights indulging myself in the lore through numerous YouTube videos, guides and Wikis. Only then did I begin to understand the scale of this game. Every action of each character, every building and every item fits in the grand scheme of the world.</p>

<p>Going out of this, the biggest thing that stuck with me is the determination. Failing is part of your life, and that is okay. No matter how daunting a task is, there&#39;s <strong>always</strong> a way to overcome it. The Elden Beast is the final boss of the game, and it&#39;s also where I spent about a quarter of my playtime. This thing has absurd attacks, immense health, and did I mention that you have to beat it after beating another extremely difficult boss, without being able to top up your health? This fight is ridiculous. I spent multiple weeks trying to beat it. I was really close to giving up, but as I mentioned earlier, each run gets you a tiny bit closer to the finish line, so I pushed through. I refined my build, I leveled up my stats and I learned how to dance with the beast. Eventually, I won the fight not by luck, but by determination. I now feel like I understand every attack well enough to dodge it. My mind was on autopilot when I beat it.</p>

<p>Knowing this much about a game didn&#39;t teach me any practical skills. There&#39;s nothing I can do now that I couldn&#39;t do before I knew that Rykard (Lord of Blasphemy), son of Rennala and Radagon (also known as Queen Marika), chose to go against the Erdtree and eventually fed himself to a serpent to devour the entire world (which you prevented). But there&#39;s something about this game that left me craving for more. It&#39;s truly a masterpiece.</p>

<h2>Bonus</h2>

<p>In case you&#39;re interested, I uploaded some of the bossfights during my playthrough in this YouTube playlist:</p>

<p>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?si=j1Ue2lrrLy1JTOM9&amp;amp;list=PLS8TKBZz1x5S6ojf24SMF1h_HYb4AyTxc&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Toil
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-01-toil
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-01-toil?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>After cheating death himself, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sisyphus">Sisyphus</a> was punished to push a large boulder up a steep hill for eternity. Every time he reached the top, the boulder would roll back down and Sisyphus had to start over.</p>

<p>Our life is full of such toil. Mowing the lawn, cleaning the dishes and doing our taxes are examples of toil that prevents us from doing sustainable work. We should always seek to minimize toil where possible. We have dishwashers and spam filters to help us fight toil, but there are some reoccurring tasks that cannot be automated.</p>

<p>Sisyphus eventually found peace with his fate. Instead of seeing his punishment as an eternal burden, he saw it as his life&#39;s purpose. Maybe those comparatively small annoyances in our life are worth enjoying. They&#39;re part of what makes us human.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Dive Log: Vietnam
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>So, after our <a href="/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket">adventures in Phuket</a>, we journeyed on to Nha Trang in Vietnam, where we also went diving.</p>

<p>Unfortunately the visibility was average, and the wildlife in Nha Trang wasn&#39;t as diverse as in Phuket, but that only made the hermit crabs or the occasional lionfish feel just that much more special.</p>

<p>In total, we did 4 dives in Nha Trang. Here&#39;s a full list, taken from my logbook:</p>

<p>| Title       | Date       | Site       | Depth (m) | Time (min) | Highlights                   |
| ----------- | ---------- | ---------- | --------- | ---------- | ---------------------------- |
| Nha Trang 1 | 2024-02-25 | Dam Bay    | 12        | 45         | Cold water and sandy bottom  |
| Nha Trang 2 | 2024-02-25 | Mot Island | 13.5      | 45         | Squids and lots of anemones  |
| Nha Trang 3 | 2024-02-26 | Tam Island | 11.2      | 37         | Playing around with bouyancy |
| Nha Trang 4 | 2024-02-26 | Tam Island | 10        | 46         | Hermit crabs                 |</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Dive Log: Phuket
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just became a certified diver! 🥳</p>

<p>I got my license through the <a href="https://rumblefishadventure.com/">Rumblefish Adventure</a> divecenter in Kata Beach, as per a recommendation from a friend who happened to be around in the area when we were there.</p>

<p>Kata Beach is a great dive spot. It has crazy wildlife, it&#39;s just a short swim away from the beach and the visibility is quite good if you haven&#39;t seen many reefs yet (like myself).</p>

<p>After doing our PADI Open Water license, we went to Phi Phi Islands to do a fun dive. The experience swimming through the reefs there can simply not be put into words.</p>

<p>In total, we did 7 dives in Thailand. Here&#39;s a full list, taken from my logbook:</p>

<p>| Title                 | Date       | Site              | Depth (m) | Time (min) | Highlights                                         |
|-----------------------|------------|-------------------|-----------|------------|----------------------------------------------------|
| Open Water Training 1 | 2024-02-16 | Kata Beach        | 6.4       | 39         | First time seeing the reef!                        |
| Open Water Training 2 | 2024-02-18 | Kata Beach        | 10.9      | 62         | Almost finished all mandatory training             |
| Open Water Training 3 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 16.3      | 44         | Artificial reefs with lots of interesting wildlife |
| Open Water Training 4 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 12.9      | 48         | Even more crazy wildlife                           |
| Phi Phi Islands 1     | 2024-02-20 | Koh Bida Nok      | 20.5      | 51         | Sharks!                                            |
| Phi Phi Islands 2     | 2024-02-20 | Turtle Rock       | 17.6      | 55         | Turtles, Sharks, Cave                              |
| Phi Phi Islands 3     | 2024-02-20 | Shark Point       | 20.4      | 46         | Lots of verticality                                |</p>

<h2>Photos</h2>

<p><img alt="P2170670 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1d00d17d-a889-417d-a4c9-8dd83eff58f9"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170752 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d3b80e60-2155-481f-8232-a5a57b3898ab"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170727 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/25e75fb1-dec7-4ad2-89a9-d929144cd60a"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170759 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1f9c2c0f-cc2e-440a-9bba-2a03c984f301"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180898.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/7f33d8a9-1d5f-4f94-87de-6078233be6a8"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180901.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/e1caf403-4ea2-4dce-a48c-1a0b5b5ce360"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180859.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/6fe5e666-0099-445f-bdcc-35bc0e5e9943"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170749 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d6a239a8-fb98-478a-9e38-d15e3587a7b4"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180837 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/50fe5c89-f1cb-4a73-aac0-f1311a3116fc"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170733 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d44f52a2-2228-4a3e-801d-930f0eddf975"/></p>

<p>After Phuket, we went to Vietnam where we&#39;re currently also on a lot of fun diving trips. But I&#39;ll save that for another dive log post.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Temporal vs. fundamental content
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just read <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38829907">this comment</a> on a thread on HackerNews which resonated with me:</p>

<blockquote><p>I&#39;m trying to read less temporal (things that matter now) and more fundamental (stuff that mattered 1+ year ago and will still matter in 1+ year, with even wider intervals for non-tech content).
This does result in missing ~important things occasionally (e.g. I still don&#39;t know what happened with SamA at OpenAI, and yes, I am curious), but that&#39;s a small price to pay for greater intellectual sanctity and an increased attention budget to distribute across important tasks or funnel into something hyper focussed.</p></blockquote>

<p>Is this news important <em>now</em> or do I benefit from it in the long term? Our time is the most precious resource we have, and we should be careful how we spend it.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                2023 in Review
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>That&#39;s a wrap! 2023 was an exciting year for me. I started my new role as a <a href="/posts/2023-04-22-the-role-of-a-devops-engineer">DevOps Engineer</a> at my current company, I got <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/open-source-der-patch-basierte-git-workflow-soll-bleiben-2302-171585.html">two</a> <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/wertestrom-in-devops-das-projekt-am-laufen-halten-2312-180174.html">articles</a> published on a prominent German news site and finally finished my <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a> challenge!</p>

<p>This year, I launched two projects: <a href="https://sendpasswords.net/">sendpasswords.net</a> and <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/positive_hackernews">Positive Hacker News</a>.</p>

<p>In <a href="/posts/2023-01-02-welcome-2023">last year&#39;s review</a>, I said I wanted to launch <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/fling">Fling</a>, my household management app. Fling is currently in open alpha, so you can try it out <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=de.garritfra.fling">on Android</a> or via the <a href="https://fling-list.web.app">hosted website</a> to give feedback! I&#39;m planning a public release very soon.</p>

<p>Furthermore, I wanted to launch <a href="https://docs.kubinity.com/">Kubinity</a>. This was a very ambitious project, and although it technically works, it&#39;s very hard to maintain due to high running costs, which I&#39;m not ready to pay yet.</p>

<p>I have some more drafts for projects in private repositories. One project that I&#39;m feeling comfortable to release next year is a website for the #10ShittyProjects (working title) hashtag. More on that hopefully later!</p>

<h2>Goals for 2024</h2>

<p>Here are some personal goals that I want to set myself for the upcoming year. Some of them are already defined on my <a href="/impossible">impossible list</a>.</p>

<ul><li>Build a side project that generated at least 100€ of value</li><li>Get a scuba diving license</li><li>Do a 10 km run (I really need to start moving again)</li><li>Sell my car</li><li>Write at least 50 blog posts</li></ul>

<h2>Prediction results</h2>

<p><strong>&quot;Meta will change course (again), and kill the &quot;Metaverse&quot;&quot;</strong></p>

<p>A <a href="https://labs.sogeti.com/the-metaverse-is-dead/#:~:text=The%20Real%20Promise%20of%20VR%2FAR%20Lies%20in%20Training%20Simulations&amp;text=Yet%2C%20as%20of%202023%2C%20we,Reality%20(AR)%20has%20diminished.">quick Google search</a> reveals that the metaverse as originally imagined is not dead, but it&#39;s focus shifted to a more enterprise-y approach. I must admit that this prediction was quite vague. Depending on whom you ask, the metaverse is <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schr%C3%B6dinger%27s_cat">both alive and dead at the same time</a>.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Cheap matter devices will enter the market. As a reference point: I predict that there will be a matter-ready smart plug for under 20€ on Amazon&quot;</strong></p>

<p>I found <a href="https://amzn.eu/d/iA9ZBQf">this</a> matter-enabled smart plug on Amazon for 19,54€. If this is a real product, I&#39;d say my prediction is a pass!</p>

<p><strong>&quot;AI generated content will be regulated in some way&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Also a pass! On December 9th, the European union agreed on the <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/headlines/society/20230601STO93804/eu-ai-act-first-regulation-on-artificial-intelligence">EU AI Act</a> and will now become EU law.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Twitter is still around, but it&#39;s still not profitable&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Twitter is in fact <a href="https://www.businessofapps.com/data/twitter-statistics/#:~:text=Twitter%20generated%20%244.4%20billion%20revenue%20in%202022%2C%20a%2011%25%20decrease,a%20loss%20of%20advertising%20revenue.">still not profitable</a>. I&#39;ll leave the &quot;Twitter is still around&quot; part up for debate, as it&#39;s now called X.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;I still won&#39;t have finished my #100DaysToOffload challenge from 2021&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Wrong!! In early December, I decided to push through and whip out one post a day. I <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it">finished the challenge</a>!</p>

<h2>2024 Predictions</h2>

<ul><li>Bitcoin will at last reach a value of 100,000$, following the <a href="https://www.nicehash.com/countdown/btc-halving-2024-05-10-12-00">halving</a> likely happening in 2024</li><li>SpaceX will use a <a href="https://www.spacex.com/vehicles/starship/">Starship</a> prototype to launch Starlink satellites into orbit</li><li>Tesla cars a still not fully self driving (<a href="https://motherfrunker.ca/fsd/">reference</a>)</li><li>Google will replace their main search with an AI chat bot (see <a href="https://bard.google.com">Bard</a>)</li></ul>

<p>Let&#39;s see what 2024 brings to the table!</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Overcoming "air hunger"
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>For as long as I can remember, I often had the feeling of not being able to get a full breath. I&#39;m taking deep breaths and sometimes forcing a yawn to overcome this feeling, sometimes successful, sometimes failing and trying again. This feeling gets worse the more I focus on my breath.</p>

<p>I always felt like this is somewhat uncommon, since none of my friends and family can relate to this feeling, but it wasn&#39;t worse enough to justify consulting a doctor about it either.</p>

<p>Doing some research, it seems like this phenomenon is called <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortness_of_breath">dyspnea</a>, or &quot;air hunger&quot;. Some guy even made <a href="https://airhunger.org/">a website</a> about it. In a nutshell, it is caused by your body not being able to regulate carbon levels in your blood, which leads to an urge to breath unnaturally.</p>

<p>In a <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=XliOGg8Tl98">video</a>, the author points out that this might be caused by irregular breathing patterns. Indeed, I often find myself breathing through the mouth or sitting in awkward positions with a humpback when the symptoms are at its worst. In fact, what led me to look this up was because I was annoyed by the feeling while I&#39;m laying in bed staring down at my screen, which is a very unnatural position.</p>

<p>A simple trick to get into a more regular breathing pattern is apparently to force yourself to breathe through the nose. Mouth breathing lets your body take in way more air than you need, which throws off the balance of the carbon levels in your lungs.</p>

<p>It seems like nose breathing does work very well. Where I&#39;ve just been struggling with air hunger, once I forced myself to nose breathe, the urge to breathe doesn&#39;t come nearly as often anymore.</p>

<p>These are just my results after some quick research. The topic of short breathing seems to be quite broad. Perhaps you&#39;re struggling with this as well. In that case, I hope this post was helpful to you!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 095 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                I'm finally off coffee
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Disclaimer: There&#39;s no real story here — just a dump of my thoughts.</p>

<p>I used to drink two cups of coffee a day on average. One during breakfast and one during the day.</p>

<p>On days where it was difficult to get my hands on coffee — during camping for example, or on some days where I don&#39;t really have time to brew a coffee — I would routinely get headaches. This might have been a coincidence, but it&#39;s not unlikely that my body was craving this delicious drink. Waking up was always accompanied by this nagging feeling of how I&#39;m gonna get my dose of coffee today.</p>

<p>That all changed when I got sick a few weeks ago. I wasn&#39;t feeling well for a few days, and as a result I didn&#39;t drink coffee at all. Knowing that caffeine is a huge stress-inducing factor in my day to day life, I decided to just not start drinking it again once I felt better.</p>

<p>Quitting caffeine cold turkey can be difficult, but two cups isn&#39;t much. Some of my peers drink way more than that. While being sick, my body quickly adjusted to the missing two cups each day. I wasn&#39;t feeling good anyway, so what&#39;s an extra mild headache?</p>

<p>Now, about two weeks later, I feel great. There&#39;s one stress-factor less in my life. I occasionally still drink coffee with friends, but it&#39;s not something I crave directly after waking up. I opted for caffeine-free tea in the morning. We also have decaffeinated coffee at home, but it feels to me like brewing decaffeinated coffee isn&#39;t worth the effort. It&#39;s still a nice alternative for nice breakfasts on the weekend.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 094 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Field Notes #3
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Hooray! I just finished my third pocket notebook. If you have no idea what I mean, check out my <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">About My Pocket Notebook</a> post.</p>

<p>This notebook lasted from 2023-10-09 to 2023-12-01, which is a bit longer than my last two notebooks. I believe my inner hype around this topic slowly but surely fades into the background, which is a good thing. Instead of writing almost every single day, I only write in it when I feel that something is important.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3.jpeg"/></p>

<p>It aged quite well for a white notebook. You can clearly tell that I got some brand new pairs of jeans, looking at the color [before I used it](/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2#what&#39;s-next?) vs. now. Just like last time, I used this notebook for all sorts of things. Todo lists, bill calculations, random thoughts and sketches for blog posts.</p>

<p>What&#39;s different this time is that I started the book off with some &quot;meta pages&quot;. The first two pages serve as an index for the book. I ripped this idea stright from the <a href="https://bulletjournal.com/">Bullet Journal</a> movement, but that&#39;s about the only thing I stole from BuJos.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3 Index" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3_index.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I also dedicated one page to a general purpose packing list, which I used multiple times to check if I forgot anything for an overnight stay. This page served me very well, so I&#39;m transfering it into my new notebook.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>My next notebook will once again be a FIELD NOTES. I just love the size, the feel and the quality of them. This time, I&#39;m using the &quot;National Parks&quot; edition, or more specifically the &quot;Glacier National Park&quot; notebook from a set. It started to snow, so this is an obvious choice.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #4" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_4.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Thanks for sticking with me through this weird and awesome hobby!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 091 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>