<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Dive Log: Vietnam
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>So, after our <a href="/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket">adventures in Phuket</a>, we journeyed on to Nha Trang in Vietnam, where we also went diving.</p>

<p>Unfortunately the visibility was average, and the wildlife in Nha Trang wasn&#39;t as diverse as in Phuket, but that only made the hermit crabs or the occasional lionfish feel just that much more special.</p>

<p>In total, we did 4 dives in Nha Trang. Here&#39;s a full list, taken from my logbook:</p>

<p>| Title       | Date       | Site       | Depth (m) | Time (min) | Highlights                   |
| ----------- | ---------- | ---------- | --------- | ---------- | ---------------------------- |
| Nha Trang 1 | 2024-02-25 | Dam Bay    | 12        | 45         | Cold water and sandy bottom  |
| Nha Trang 2 | 2024-02-25 | Mot Island | 13.5      | 45         | Squids and lots of anemones  |
| Nha Trang 3 | 2024-02-26 | Tam Island | 11.2      | 37         | Playing around with bouyancy |
| Nha Trang 4 | 2024-02-26 | Tam Island | 10        | 46         | Hermit crabs                 |</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Dive Log: Phuket
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just became a certified diver! 🥳</p>

<p>I got my license through the <a href="https://rumblefishadventure.com/">Rumblefish Adventure</a> divecenter in Kata Beach, as per a recommendation from a friend who happened to be around in the area when we were there.</p>

<p>Kata Beach is a great dive spot. It has crazy wildlife, it&#39;s just a short swim away from the beach and the visibility is quite good if you haven&#39;t seen many reefs yet (like myself).</p>

<p>After doing our PADI Open Water license, we went to Phi Phi Islands to do a fun dive. The experience swimming through the reefs there can simply not be put into words.</p>

<p>In total, we did 7 dives in Thailand. Here&#39;s a full list, taken from my logbook:</p>

<p>| Title                 | Date       | Site              | Depth (m) | Time (min) | Highlights                                         |
|-----------------------|------------|-------------------|-----------|------------|----------------------------------------------------|
| Open Water Training 1 | 2024-02-16 | Kata Beach        | 6.4       | 39         | First time seeing the reef!                        |
| Open Water Training 2 | 2024-02-18 | Kata Beach        | 10.9      | 62         | Almost finished all mandatory training             |
| Open Water Training 3 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 16.3      | 44         | Artificial reefs with lots of interesting wildlife |
| Open Water Training 4 | 2024-02-18 | Ko Pu, Kata Beach | 12.9      | 48         | Even more crazy wildlife                           |
| Phi Phi Islands 1     | 2024-02-20 | Koh Bida Nok      | 20.5      | 51         | Sharks!                                            |
| Phi Phi Islands 2     | 2024-02-20 | Turtle Rock       | 17.6      | 55         | Turtles, Sharks, Cave                              |
| Phi Phi Islands 3     | 2024-02-20 | Shark Point       | 20.4      | 46         | Lots of verticality                                |</p>

<h2>Photos</h2>

<p><img alt="P2170670 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1d00d17d-a889-417d-a4c9-8dd83eff58f9"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170752 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d3b80e60-2155-481f-8232-a5a57b3898ab"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170727 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/25e75fb1-dec7-4ad2-89a9-d929144cd60a"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170759 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/1f9c2c0f-cc2e-440a-9bba-2a03c984f301"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180898.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/7f33d8a9-1d5f-4f94-87de-6078233be6a8"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180901.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/e1caf403-4ea2-4dce-a48c-1a0b5b5ce360"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180859.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/6fe5e666-0099-445f-bdcc-35bc0e5e9943"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170749 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d6a239a8-fb98-478a-9e38-d15e3587a7b4"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2180837 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/50fe5c89-f1cb-4a73-aac0-f1311a3116fc"/></p>

<p><img alt="P2170733 - Kopie.JPG" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/d44f52a2-2228-4a3e-801d-930f0eddf975"/></p>

<p>After Phuket, we went to Vietnam where we&#39;re currently also on a lot of fun diving trips. But I&#39;ll save that for another dive log post.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Temporal vs. fundamental content
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just read <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38829907">this comment</a> on a thread on HackerNews which resonated with me:</p>

<blockquote><p>I&#39;m trying to read less temporal (things that matter now) and more fundamental (stuff that mattered 1+ year ago and will still matter in 1+ year, with even wider intervals for non-tech content).
This does result in missing ~important things occasionally (e.g. I still don&#39;t know what happened with SamA at OpenAI, and yes, I am curious), but that&#39;s a small price to pay for greater intellectual sanctity and an increased attention budget to distribute across important tasks or funnel into something hyper focussed.</p></blockquote>

<p>Is this news important <em>now</em> or do I benefit from it in the long term? Our time is the most precious resource we have, and we should be careful how we spend it.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                2023 in Review
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>That&#39;s a wrap! 2023 was an exciting year for me. I started my new role as a <a href="/posts/2023-04-22-the-role-of-a-devops-engineer">DevOps Engineer</a> at my current company, I got <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/open-source-der-patch-basierte-git-workflow-soll-bleiben-2302-171585.html">two</a> <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/wertestrom-in-devops-das-projekt-am-laufen-halten-2312-180174.html">articles</a> published on a prominent German news site and finally finished my <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a> challenge!</p>

<p>This year, I launched two projects: <a href="https://sendpasswords.net/">sendpasswords.net</a> and <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/positive_hackernews">Positive Hacker News</a>.</p>

<p>In <a href="/posts/2023-01-02-welcome-2023">last year&#39;s review</a>, I said I wanted to launch <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/fling">Fling</a>, my household management app. Fling is currently in open alpha, so you can try it out <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=de.garritfra.fling">on Android</a> or via the <a href="https://fling-list.web.app">hosted website</a> to give feedback! I&#39;m planning a public release very soon.</p>

<p>Furthermore, I wanted to launch <a href="https://docs.kubinity.com/">Kubinity</a>. This was a very ambitious project, and although it technically works, it&#39;s very hard to maintain due to high running costs, which I&#39;m not ready to pay yet.</p>

<p>I have some more drafts for projects in private repositories. One project that I&#39;m feeling comfortable to release next year is a website for the #10ShittyProjects (working title) hashtag. More on that hopefully later!</p>

<h2>Goals for 2024</h2>

<p>Here are some personal goals that I want to set myself for the upcoming year. Some of them are already defined on my <a href="/impossible">impossible list</a>.</p>

<ul><li>Build a side project that generated at least 100€ of value</li><li>Get a scuba diving license</li><li>Do a 10 km run (I really need to start moving again)</li><li>Sell my car</li><li>Write at least 50 blog posts</li></ul>

<h2>Prediction results</h2>

<p><strong>&quot;Meta will change course (again), and kill the &quot;Metaverse&quot;&quot;</strong></p>

<p>A <a href="https://labs.sogeti.com/the-metaverse-is-dead/#:~:text=The%20Real%20Promise%20of%20VR%2FAR%20Lies%20in%20Training%20Simulations&amp;text=Yet%2C%20as%20of%202023%2C%20we,Reality%20(AR)%20has%20diminished.">quick Google search</a> reveals that the metaverse as originally imagined is not dead, but it&#39;s focus shifted to a more enterprise-y approach. I must admit that this prediction was quite vague. Depending on whom you ask, the metaverse is <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schr%C3%B6dinger%27s_cat">both alive and dead at the same time</a>.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Cheap matter devices will enter the market. As a reference point: I predict that there will be a matter-ready smart plug for under 20€ on Amazon&quot;</strong></p>

<p>I found <a href="https://amzn.eu/d/iA9ZBQf">this</a> matter-enabled smart plug on Amazon for 19,54€. If this is a real product, I&#39;d say my prediction is a pass!</p>

<p><strong>&quot;AI generated content will be regulated in some way&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Also a pass! On December 9th, the European union agreed on the <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/headlines/society/20230601STO93804/eu-ai-act-first-regulation-on-artificial-intelligence">EU AI Act</a> and will now become EU law.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Twitter is still around, but it&#39;s still not profitable&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Twitter is in fact <a href="https://www.businessofapps.com/data/twitter-statistics/#:~:text=Twitter%20generated%20%244.4%20billion%20revenue%20in%202022%2C%20a%2011%25%20decrease,a%20loss%20of%20advertising%20revenue.">still not profitable</a>. I&#39;ll leave the &quot;Twitter is still around&quot; part up for debate, as it&#39;s now called X.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;I still won&#39;t have finished my #100DaysToOffload challenge from 2021&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Wrong!! In early December, I decided to push through and whip out one post a day. I <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it">finished the challenge</a>!</p>

<h2>2024 Predictions</h2>

<ul><li>Bitcoin will at last reach a value of 100,000$, following the <a href="https://www.nicehash.com/countdown/btc-halving-2024-05-10-12-00">halving</a> likely happening in 2024</li><li>SpaceX will use a <a href="https://www.spacex.com/vehicles/starship/">Starship</a> prototype to launch Starlink satellites into orbit</li><li>Tesla cars a still not fully self driving (<a href="https://motherfrunker.ca/fsd/">reference</a>)</li><li>Google will replace their main search with an AI chat bot (see <a href="https://bard.google.com">Bard</a>)</li></ul>

<p>Let&#39;s see what 2024 brings to the table!</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Overcoming "air hunger"
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>For as long as I can remember, I often had the feeling of not being able to get a full breath. I&#39;m taking deep breaths and sometimes forcing a yawn to overcome this feeling, sometimes successful, sometimes failing and trying again. This feeling gets worse the more I focus on my breath.</p>

<p>I always felt like this is somewhat uncommon, since none of my friends and family can relate to this feeling, but it wasn&#39;t worse enough to justify consulting a doctor about it either.</p>

<p>Doing some research, it seems like this phenomenon is called <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortness_of_breath">dyspnea</a>, or &quot;air hunger&quot;. Some guy even made <a href="https://airhunger.org/">a website</a> about it. In a nutshell, it is caused by your body not being able to regulate carbon levels in your blood, which leads to an urge to breath unnaturally.</p>

<p>In a <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=XliOGg8Tl98">video</a>, the author points out that this might be caused by irregular breathing patterns. Indeed, I often find myself breathing through the mouth or sitting in awkward positions with a humpback when the symptoms are at its worst. In fact, what led me to look this up was because I was annoyed by the feeling while I&#39;m laying in bed staring down at my screen, which is a very unnatural position.</p>

<p>A simple trick to get into a more regular breathing pattern is apparently to force yourself to breathe through the nose. Mouth breathing lets your body take in way more air than you need, which throws off the balance of the carbon levels in your lungs.</p>

<p>It seems like nose breathing does work very well. Where I&#39;ve just been struggling with air hunger, once I forced myself to nose breathe, the urge to breathe doesn&#39;t come nearly as often anymore.</p>

<p>These are just my results after some quick research. The topic of short breathing seems to be quite broad. Perhaps you&#39;re struggling with this as well. In that case, I hope this post was helpful to you!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 095 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                I'm finally off coffee
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Disclaimer: There&#39;s no real story here — just a dump of my thoughts.</p>

<p>I used to drink two cups of coffee a day on average. One during breakfast and one during the day.</p>

<p>On days where it was difficult to get my hands on coffee — during camping for example, or on some days where I don&#39;t really have time to brew a coffee — I would routinely get headaches. This might have been a coincidence, but it&#39;s not unlikely that my body was craving this delicious drink. Waking up was always accompanied by this nagging feeling of how I&#39;m gonna get my dose of coffee today.</p>

<p>That all changed when I got sick a few weeks ago. I wasn&#39;t feeling well for a few days, and as a result I didn&#39;t drink coffee at all. Knowing that caffeine is a huge stress-inducing factor in my day to day life, I decided to just not start drinking it again once I felt better.</p>

<p>Quitting caffeine cold turkey can be difficult, but two cups isn&#39;t much. Some of my peers drink way more than that. While being sick, my body quickly adjusted to the missing two cups each day. I wasn&#39;t feeling good anyway, so what&#39;s an extra mild headache?</p>

<p>Now, about two weeks later, I feel great. There&#39;s one stress-factor less in my life. I occasionally still drink coffee with friends, but it&#39;s not something I crave directly after waking up. I opted for caffeine-free tea in the morning. We also have decaffeinated coffee at home, but it feels to me like brewing decaffeinated coffee isn&#39;t worth the effort. It&#39;s still a nice alternative for nice breakfasts on the weekend.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 094 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Field Notes #3
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Hooray! I just finished my third pocket notebook. If you have no idea what I mean, check out my <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">About My Pocket Notebook</a> post.</p>

<p>This notebook lasted from 2023-10-09 to 2023-12-01, which is a bit longer than my last two notebooks. I believe my inner hype around this topic slowly but surely fades into the background, which is a good thing. Instead of writing almost every single day, I only write in it when I feel that something is important.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3.jpeg"/></p>

<p>It aged quite well for a white notebook. You can clearly tell that I got some brand new pairs of jeans, looking at the color [before I used it](/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2#what&#39;s-next?) vs. now. Just like last time, I used this notebook for all sorts of things. Todo lists, bill calculations, random thoughts and sketches for blog posts.</p>

<p>What&#39;s different this time is that I started the book off with some &quot;meta pages&quot;. The first two pages serve as an index for the book. I ripped this idea stright from the <a href="https://bulletjournal.com/">Bullet Journal</a> movement, but that&#39;s about the only thing I stole from BuJos.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3 Index" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3_index.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I also dedicated one page to a general purpose packing list, which I used multiple times to check if I forgot anything for an overnight stay. This page served me very well, so I&#39;m transfering it into my new notebook.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>My next notebook will once again be a FIELD NOTES. I just love the size, the feel and the quality of them. This time, I&#39;m using the &quot;National Parks&quot; edition, or more specifically the &quot;Glacier National Park&quot; notebook from a set. It started to snow, so this is an obvious choice.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #4" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_4.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Thanks for sticking with me through this weird and awesome hobby!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 091 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                My App Defaults (Late 2023)
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-07-app-defaults
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-07-app-defaults?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 07 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Apparently there&#39;s currently a thing where people share their preferred apps. If you like this format, check out Robb Knight&#39;s <a href="https://defaults.rknight.me/">list of App Defaults blog posts</a>.</p>

<p>Without further ado, here&#39;s my list:</p>

<ul><li>📨 Mail Client: Thunderbird</li><li>📮 Mail Server: Purelymail</li><li>📝 Notes: <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">Pen &amp; Paper</a></li><li>✅ To-Do: <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">Pen &amp; Paper</a></li><li>🟦 Photo Management: Google Photos</li><li>📆 Calendar: Google Calendar</li><li>📁 Cloud File Storage: Google Drive</li><li>📖 RSS: Miniflux</li><li>🙍🏻‍♂️ Contacts: Google Contacts</li><li>🌐 Browser: Firefox</li><li>💬 Chat: WhatsApp</li><li>🔖 Bookmarks: Firefox</li><li>📑 Read It Later: Pocket</li><li>📜 Word Processing: Markdown, Google Docs</li><li>📈 Spreadsheets: Google Sheets</li><li>📊 Presentations: Google Slides</li><li>🛒 Shopping Lists: <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">Pen &amp; Paper</a></li><li>🍴 Meal Planning: <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">Pen &amp; Paper</a></li><li>💰 Budgeting and Personal Finance: GnuCash</li><li>📰 News: Mostly HackerNews via Miniflux</li><li>🎵 Music: Spotify</li><li>🎤 Podcasts: AntennaPod</li><li>🔐 Password Management: Bitwarden</li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 085 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Did you try turning it off?
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-10-did-you-try-turning-it-off
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-10-did-you-try-turning-it-off?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Planning our week, checking the time, suming up two numbers, reading a book. Often, digital devices are our default answer to a problem at hand. We&#39;ve become so used to being around a computer that we neglect that certain tasks could also be accomplished without it.</p>

<p>Often, we just need to <a href="/posts/2023-06-25-make-a-list">make a list</a>. Many of us have 10 todo-apps on our phone, each with its own bells and whistles. But do we really need those reminder notifications, tags, and priority levels? Most commonly, a pen and paper are all we need to remember what&#39;s on todays agenda.</p>

<p>The next time you&#39;re faced with a foreign problem, try asking yourself if whatever you&#39;re doing is worth the complexity of the solution. Often, though of course not always, the analog solution is most efficient.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 082 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Field Notes #2
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 09 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Today marks the completion of my second pocket notebook. You may view my <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">About My Pocket Notebook</a> post as part one of this series, since I wrote it near the end of my first notebook. I think it would be interesting to share my experience with this each notebook. One day I&#39;ll maybe have a nice history of posts that I can look back at. 🙂</p>

<p>This notebook lasted from 2023-09-10 to 2023-10-09, roughly one month. Here&#39;s a picture of it, after living in my back pocket every single day:</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #2" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_2.jpeg"/></p>

<h3>What&#39;s in it?</h3>

<p>I used this notebook as a todo list, a travel journal, quick sketches, braindumps, simple calculations and much more. It&#39;s become a place to dump thoughts whenever and wherever I want to. Sometimes, it&#39;s genuinely interesting facts, like how to find north when all you have is a clear night sky.</p>

<p><img alt="Notes on how to find north at night" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_2_page_5.jpeg"/></p>

<p>And sometimes it&#39;s just a random collection of uninteresting thoughts that wouldn&#39;t leave my head.</p>

<p><img alt="Random collection of notes" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_2_page_32.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Some of these notes may mature into a project or blog post, like <a href="/posts/2023-09-29-undo-on-mobile-phones">the second to last note on that page</a>, while others just fade into the abyss. But that&#39;s okay! The point is to get these thoughts out of my head to work with them more easily.</p>

<h3>What&#39;s next?</h3>

<p>I&#39;ll keep on writing! I got a bunch of new FIELD NOTES notebooks to fill up. Since my next notebook will likely live with me through the halloween season, I opted for the <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/products/harvest">Harvest</a> edition as my next notebook. 🎃</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_3.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I&#39;m curious to see where this one takes me.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 081 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>