<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                How embedding models encode semantic meaning
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-08-03-how-embedding-models-encode-semantic-meaning
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-08-03-how-embedding-models-encode-semantic-meaning?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Embedding models have long been a daunting concept for me. But what are they? And why are they so useful? Let&#39;s break it down in simple terms.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s an embedding?</h2>

<p>An embedding is basically a numerical representation of a piece of information - it could be text, audio, an image, or even a video. Think of it as a way to capture the essence or meaning of that information in a list of numbers.</p>

<p>For example, let&#39;s say we have this text: &quot;show me a list of ground transportation at boston airport&quot;. An embedding model might turn that into something like this:</p>

<p><code>
[0.03793335, -0.008010864, -0.002319336, -0.0110321045, -0.019882202, -0.023864746, 0.011428833, -0.030349731, -0.044830322, 0.028289795, -0.02810669, -0.0032749176, -0.04208374, -0.0077705383, -0.0033798218, -0.06335449, ... ]
</code></p>

<p>At first, thus looks like a jumble of numbers. But each of these numbers points to a specific area within the embedding model&#39;s &quot;space&quot;, where similar words or concepts might be located.</p>

<h2>Visualizing embeddings</h2>

<p>To help wrap our heads around this, let&#39;s look at a visualization. This beautiful image shows the entirety of the <a href="https://huggingface.co/nomic-ai/nomic-embed-text-v1.5">nomic-embed-text-v1.5</a> embedding model, as generated by <a href="https://atlas.nomic.ai/map/nomic-text-embed-v1-5m-sample">this visualization tool</a>:</p>

<p><img alt="nomic-embed-text-v1.5-full" src="/assets/posts/2024-08-03-how-embedding-models-encode-semantic-meaning/nomic-embed-text-v1.5-full.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Now, if we take our example text about Boston airport transportation and plot its embeddings on this map, we&#39;d see that some clusters are lit up, especially around &quot;transportation&quot;. This means that the model has figured out that the topic of the query must be related to transportation in some way.</p>

<p><img alt="nomic-embed-text-v1.5-query" src="/assets/posts/2024-08-03-how-embedding-models-encode-semantic-meaning/nomic-embed-text-v1.5-query.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Zooming into this image, we can see more specific topics around transportation, like &quot;Airport&quot;, &quot;Travel&quot; or &quot;Highways&quot; are lit up, which more closely matches our query.</p>

<p><img alt="nomic-embed-text-v1.5-transportation" src="/assets/posts/2024-08-03-how-embedding-models-encode-semantic-meaning/nomic-embed-text-v1.5-transportation.jpeg"/></p>

<p>In a nutshell, embedding models are able to group terms by topics that are related to each other.</p>

<h2>Why should we care about embeddings?</h2>

<p>Encoding meaning in text has tons of different use cases. One that I&#39;m particularly excited about is building RAG applications. RAG stands for Retrieval-Augmented Generation and refers to a method for Large Language Models (LLMs), where, given a question, you enrich the original question with relevant bits of information before answering it.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s how embeddings are useful for RAG:</p>

<ol><li>You have a bunch of documents in your data source.</li><li>You use an embedding model to turn each document into a list of numbers (like we saw earlier).</li><li>When someone asks a question, you also turn that question into a list of numbers.</li><li>Then, you find the documents whose number lists are most similar to your question&#39;s number list.</li><li>Voila! You&#39;ve found the most relevant documents to answer the question.</li></ol>

<p>This method is way better than previously used techniques like just searching for exact words in the documents. It&#39;s like the difference between having a librarian who only looks at book titles, and one who actually understands what the books are about.</p>

<h2>Other things you can do with embeddings</h2>

<p>Beyond RAG applications, embeddings are super useful for all sorts of things:</p>

<ol><li><strong>Smarter searches</strong>: Find related stuff even if the exact words don&#39;t match.</li><li><strong>Better recommendations</strong>: &quot;You liked this? You might also like these similar things!&quot;</li><li><strong>Language translation</strong>: Help computers understand that &quot;dog&quot; in English and &quot;perro&quot; in Spanish mean the same thing.</li><li><strong>Sentiment analysis</strong>: Figure out if someone&#39;s happy or grumpy based on their tweet.</li></ol>

<h2>Wrapping it up</h2>

<p>Embeddings are a clever way to turn words (or images, or sounds) into numbers that computers can understand and compare. By doing this, we can make emerging AI technologies a whole lot smarter at understanding language and finding connections between ideas.</p>

<p>Next time you&#39;re chatting with an AI or getting scarily accurate recommendations online, you can nod knowingly and think, &quot;Ah yes, embeddings at work!&quot;</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Another reason why you can&apos;t divide by zero
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-19-another-reason-you-can-t-divide-by-zero
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-19-another-reason-you-can-t-divide-by-zero?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>So, I recently wrote about [why you can&#39;t divide by zero](/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can&#39;t-divide-by-zero). In that post, I argued that dividing a number by zero breaks the rules of <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverse_function">inverse functions</a>. Of course that&#39;s not the only way to prove that the result of dividing a number by zero is not defined, so here&#39;s another.</p>

<p>If you approach the number zero from some arbitrary number as the divisor, you will find that the result is getting larger and larger: <code>1 / 1 = 1</code>, <code>1 / 0.5 = 2</code>, <code>1 / 0.1 = 10</code> and so on. If we keep dividing by smaller numbers, the result will get bigger and bigger. It&#39;s obvious that if we go all the way down to zero as the divisor, we will see infinity as the result, right? Well, no.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s flip this around and start from a negative number, going up towards the number zero: <code>1 / -1 = -1</code>, <code>1 / -0.5 = -2</code>, <code>1 / -0.1 = -10</code>. As you can see, the numbers are getting <strong>smaller</strong>, the more we approach the number zero! This shows that the results differ if we change the perspective on the problem. The result cannot be defined.</p>

<p>After writing the first post on this topic, I honestly didn&#39;t realize how complex this seemingly simple problem is. I&#39;m not a mathematician, but I&#39;m starting to like maths. Fascinating stuff!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 096 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Why you can&apos;t divide by zero
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can't-divide-by-zero
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can't-divide-by-zero?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 30 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I&#39;ve always been wondering why dividing by zero is considered undefined. My intuitive answer would have always been &quot;infinity&quot; or &quot;zero&quot;. I just had a discussion about this with a collegue who happens to have a degree in mathematics, and the way they explained it made it absolutely clear why it doesn&#39;t make sense to divide by zero.</p>

<h2>Inverse Operations</h2>

<p>Before understanding why dividing by zero is undefined, you first need to know about inverse operations. It&#39;s quite simple!</p>

<p>An example: <code>3 + 2 = 5</code>. The inverse of addition is <em>subtraction</em>, so the inverse of this equation is <code>5 - 2 = 3</code> or <code>5 - 3 = 2</code>.</p>

<p>The same applies to multiplication. The inverse of multiplation is <em>division</em>. So the inverse of <code>6 * 2 = 12</code> is <code>12 / 2 = 6</code> or <code>12 / 6 = 2</code>.</p>

<h2>Dividing by zero</h2>

<p>Let&#39;s try to apply the inverse rule to the number zero, starting with addition. If <code>2 + 0 = 2</code>, then <code>2 - 0 = 2</code>.</p>

<p>But if we have <code>2 * 0 = 0</code>, the inverse of that would be <code>0 / 0 = 2</code>, which is just not true.</p>

<p>Dividing by zero breaks some fundamental laws of mathematics, which is why there&#39;s a general consensus that any equasion dividing by zero has no valid answer.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 090 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>