<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Another reason you can't divide by zero
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-19-another-reason-you-can-t-divide-by-zero
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-19-another-reason-you-can-t-divide-by-zero?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>So, I recently wrote about [why you can&#39;t divide by zero](/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can&#39;t-divide-by-zero). In that post, I argued that dividing a number by zero breaks the rules of <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverse_function">inverse functions</a>. Of course that&#39;s not the only way to prove that the result of dividing a number by zero is not defined, so here&#39;s another.</p>

<p>If you approach the number zero from some arbitrary number as the divisor, you will find that the result is getting larger and larger: <code>1 / 1 = 1</code>, <code>1 / 0.5 = 2</code>, <code>1 / 0.1 = 10</code> and so on. If we keep dividing by smaller numbers, the result will get bigger and bigger. It&#39;s obvious that if we go all the way down to zero as the divisor, we will see infinity as the result, right? Well, no.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s flip this around and start from a negative number, going up towards the number zero: <code>1 / -1 = -1</code>, <code>1 / -0.5 = -2</code>, <code>1 / -0.1 = -10</code>. As you can see, the numbers are getting <strong>smaller</strong>, the more we approach the number zero! This shows that the results differ if we change the perspective on the problem. The result cannot be defined.</p>

<p>After writing the first post on this topic, I honestly didn&#39;t realize how complex this seemingly simple problem is. I&#39;m not a mathematician, but I&#39;m starting to like maths. Fascinating stuff!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 096 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Why you can't divide by zero
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can't-divide-by-zero
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can't-divide-by-zero?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 30 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I&#39;ve always been wondering why dividing by zero is considered undefined. My intuitive answer would have always been &quot;infinity&quot; or &quot;zero&quot;. I just had a discussion about this with a collegue who happens to have a degree in mathematics, and the way they explained it made it absolutely clear why it doesn&#39;t make sense to divide by zero.</p>

<h2>Inverse Operations</h2>

<p>Before understanding why dividing by zero is undefined, you first need to know about inverse operations. It&#39;s quite simple!</p>

<p>An example: <code>3 + 2 = 5</code>. The inverse of addition is <em>subtraction</em>, so the inverse of this equation is <code>5 - 2 = 3</code> or <code>5 - 3 = 2</code>.</p>

<p>The same applies to multiplication. The inverse of multiplation is <em>division</em>. So the inverse of <code>6 * 2 = 12</code> is <code>12 / 2 = 6</code> or <code>12 / 6 = 2</code>.</p>

<h2>Dividing by zero</h2>

<p>Let&#39;s try to apply the inverse rule to the number zero, starting with addition. If <code>2 + 0 = 2</code>, then <code>2 - 0 = 2</code>.</p>

<p>But if we have <code>2 * 0 = 0</code>, the inverse of that would be <code>0 / 0 = 2</code>, which is just not true.</p>

<p>Dividing by zero breaks some fundamental laws of mathematics, which is why there&#39;s a general consensus that any equasion dividing by zero has no valid answer.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 090 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>