<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                A simple search bar
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-11-a-simple-search-bar
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-11-a-simple-search-bar?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just added a simple search bar to my <a href="/links">&quot;More ...&quot;</a> page. It just redirects to a <a href="https://duckduckgo.com">DuckDuckGo</a> search with your search term and limits it to my site. Simple, yet effective!</p>

<p>Here&#39;s the snippet, feel free to steal it for your own site:</p>

<p><code>jsx
&lt;form className=&quot;search&quot; method=&quot;get&quot; action=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
    &lt;input id=&quot;search&quot; type=&quot;search&quot; name=&quot;q&quot; placeholder=&quot;Search via DDG&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;sites&quot; value=&quot;garrit.xyz&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; value=&quot;Search&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
</code></p>

<h2>Try it out</h2>

<p>Try searching for anything!</p>

<p>&lt;form className=&quot;search&quot; method=&quot;get&quot; action=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
    &lt;input id=&quot;search&quot; type=&quot;search&quot; name=&quot;q&quot; placeholder=&quot;Search via DDG&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;sites&quot; value=&quot;garrit.xyz&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; value=&quot;Search&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Five Years of Blogging
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-07-five-years-of-blogging
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-07-five-years-of-blogging?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>My blog just turned five years old! 🎉</p>

<p>To celebrate this unique occasion, I want to announce something I&#39;ve been secretly working on: I wrote a book!</p>

<p><img alt="The cover of Five Years of Blogging" src="/assets/five-years-of-blogging-cover-3d.png"/></p>

<p><a href="https://www.buymeacoffee.com/garrit/e/233695"><em>Five Years of Blogging: Ideas, Opinions and Guides written 2019 to 2024</em></a> serves as a memoir for the first five years of this blog. It&#39;s a collection of not all, but my most valuable blog posts capturing my ideas, opinions and the lessons I learned. The book is quite messy, but that&#39;s by design. I want to preserve all posts in the state that they have originally been written in. Where necessary, you may find introductory paragraphs or footnotes to explain something in more detail, but the original posts have all been left untouched.</p>

<p>Getting a copy of this book is the best way to support my writing. You can either <a href="https://www.buymeacoffee.com/garrit/extras">buy the book directly on Buy Me a Coffee</a>, or you can <a href="https://www.buymeacoffee.com/garrit/membership">become a monthly supporter</a>, which grants you a free copy after signing up.</p>

<p>I&#39;m extremely grateful for the journey this blog has taken me on, and the people I met along the way. Who knows, maybe there will be a &quot;Ten Years of Blogging&quot; book in the future?</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                A better publishing workflow for static blogs
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-06-a-better-publishing-workflow-for-static-blogs
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-06-a-better-publishing-workflow-for-static-blogs?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 06 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it">post</a> celebrating the completion of my <code>#100DaysToOffload</code> challenge, I teased that &quot;I built myself a handy script that turns the contents of a GitHub issue into a pull request, ready to be merged as a blog post&quot;. I didn&#39;t believe this was such a big deal, but a couple of readers actually reached out to me to ask about this.</p>

<p>First, some background. My site is built using a static site generator (not that it matters, but I use <a href="https://nextjs.org/">Next.js</a>). The beauty of using a SSG is that every blog post is literally just a markdown file in <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/tree/main/content/posts">a directory</a>. </p>

<h2>The story so far</h2>

<p>Before coming up with an automation, I had to</p>

<ol><li>Copy an older post to a new file</li><li>Rename the file</li><li>Fix the metadata/frontmatter</li><li>Delete the contents of the post</li><li><strong>Write the actual post</strong></li><li>Commit the file</li></ol>

<p>Putting out content on my blog involved quite a bit of friction. I felt like there was a barrier between my thoughts and the blog.</p>

<h2>The solution</h2>

<p>I&#39;ve been looking into how I could solve this issue for quite some time. I even had thoughts to build a custom blogging backend that would commit files to the <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz">repository</a>, which is of course quite silly.</p>

<p>But then it struck me: GitHub issues fully support markdown! The idea was born:</p>

<ol><li>Open an issue in the repository of this blog</li><li>Write the post</li><li>Kick off an automation that takes the content of the issue and dumps it in a new file</li><li>Create a pull request to generate a preview of the post</li><li>Merge the PR once I&#39;m done reviewing the post</li></ol>

<h2>So, how does the automation work?</h2>

<p>The magic lies in <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/blob/main/.github/workflows/publish_via_issue.yaml">this GitHub Action</a>. It is kicked off whenever the <code>action:publish</code> label is added to an issue.</p>

<p>If for some reason this link will not be there anymore in the future, this is the action as of the time of writing:</p>

<p>&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Expand me!&lt;/summary&gt;</p>

<p><code></code>`yaml
on:
  issues:
    types: [labeled]</p>

<p>name: Publish issue as post
jobs:
  publish-issue:
    if: github.event.label.name == &#39;action:publish&#39;
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    env:
      POST<em>BODY: &#39;${{ github.event.issue.body }}&#39;
    steps:
      - uses: actions/checkout@v4
      - name: Create commits
        run: |
          export POST</em>DATE=$(date +&quot;%Y-%m-%d&quot;)
          export POST<em>TITLE=&quot;${{ github.event.issue.title }}&quot;
          export POST</em>TAGS=$(echo &quot;${{ join(github.event.issue.labels.<em>.name, &#39;, &#39;) }}&quot; | grep -o &#39;tag:[^,]</em>&#39; | cut -d: -f2- | paste -sd &quot; &quot; - | sed &#39;s/ /, /g&#39;)
          export FILE<em>TITLE=$(printf &quot;$POST</em>TITLE&quot; | tr -cs &#39;[:alnum:]&#39; &#39;-&#39; | tr &#39;A-Z&#39; &#39;a-z&#39; | sed &#39;s/--/-/g&#39; | sed &#39;s/^-\|-$//g&#39;)
          export FILE<em>NAME=&quot;$POST</em>DATE-$FILE<em>TITLE.md&quot;
          export FULL</em>PATH=&quot;content/posts/$FILE_NAME&quot;
          git config user.name &#39;Publish Bot&#39;
          git config user.email &#39;publish-bot@github.com&#39;</p>

<pre><code>      cat &lt;&lt; EOF &gt; $FULL_PATH
      ---
      title: &quot;$POST_TITLE&quot;
      date: &quot;$POST_DATE&quot;
      tags: &quot;$POST_TAGS&quot;
      ---

      EOF

      echo &quot;$POST_BODY&quot; &gt;&gt; $FULL_PATH

      git add $FULL_PATH
      git commit -m &quot;Publish $POST_TITLE&quot;

  - name: Create Pull Request
    uses: peter-evans/create-pull-request@v5
    with:
      title: &quot;New Post: ${{ github.event.issue.title }}&quot;
      body: &quot;Closes #${{ github.event.issue.number }}.\n\n This PR has been generated automatically.&quot;
  - uses: actions-ecosystem/action-remove-labels@v1
    with:
      labels: action:publish</code></pre>

<p><code></code>`</p>

<p>&lt;/details&gt;</p>

<p>So, when I&#39;m done writing the post, I simply label the issue as <code>action:publish</code>, and the action turns it into a new file, commits it and ultimately opens a PR for me to review. You can see this in action by looking at <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/issues/432">the issue for this post</a>. The action also handles tags for blog posts. You can see that there are a bunch of labels on the issues that correspond to the tags of this post.</p>

<p>One additional benefit of using a static site generator is that I can generate a preview site for each pull request. So, once I&#39;m done writing and the pull request is generated, I can just wait for Netlify to build the preview to read the blog post as if it is published to the site! This is very helpful for spotting typos or formatting issues, especially if I&#39;m writing a post on my phone.</p>

<h2>Further improvements</h2>

<p>There are two things the current setup is lacking:</p>

<p>Firstly, GitHub doesn&#39;t really highlight typos when writing an issue. I&#39;m sure there are ways to address this post-publish, I just didn&#39;t get around to doing that yet.</p>

<p>Secondly, there&#39;s no sustainable way to add images to the repository this way. I have an <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/tree/main/public/assets">assets directory</a> where I put all my images for blog posts. You can paste images directly into the issue, which is really handy, but that generates a permalink on a GitHub CDN, somewhere that I don&#39;t control. For the future, it would be nice to teach the GH action to take these images and dump them into the asset directory.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Using this workflow, I can pump out ideas whenever and whereever I feel like it. It drastically reduced the time from idea to written article, which helps me organize my thoughts a lot better. I also frequently create drafts for things I want to write about but is not fully fleshed out yet.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                #100DaysToOffload: I made it!
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 23 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This marks post 100 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com">#100DaysToOffload</a>. These last couple of days, I&#39;ve been sprinting towards the finish line with one post every day to finish the challenge until the end of the year. And I finally made it!</p>

<p>I started this challenge with <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-01-11-100daystooffload">this</a> post on January 11th, 2021, which means it took me almost three full years to finish it. The original challenge was to write 100 posts in <strong>one</strong> year, so I&#39;m way overdue. 😅 But that doesn&#39;t make me less proud to finish it!</p>

<p>If you&#39;re interested, you can find the list of all 100 of my posts <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts?tags=100DaysToOffload">here</a>.</p>

<h2>What I learned</h2>

<p>Before starting this challenge, I sometimes struggled with putting out content on this blog. It felt like each post had to be perfect, and if it wasn&#39;t, I was scared to publish it.</p>

<p>The idea of #100DaysToOffload is to let go of this fear and <em>Just. Write.</em> This absolutely worked. I accepted the fact that not every post is perfect and <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity">sometimes posting more often with worse quality makes way for better posts</a>.</p>

<p>In order to post more often, I also found ways to reduce the friction between me writing a text and publishing it to the blog. I&#39;ve yet to cover this in a post, but I built myself <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/blob/main/.github/workflows/publish_via_issue.yaml">a handy script</a> that turns the contents of a GitHub issue into a pull request, ready to be merged as a blog post. This enables me to write posts everywhere I want (like the one right now, which is written on my phone), instead of having to open my laptop, create a new file, write the post and commit it to the repository.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>I will continue posting when I feel like it! I set myself the goal to publish at least 50 posts a year, but that&#39;s just a rough estimate. If I don&#39;t feel like blogging, I won&#39;t force myself to do it.</p>

<p>All in all, I&#39;m very thankful for having taken part in this challenge. I met <a href="https://kevquirk.com/">a</a> <a href="https://joelchrono.xyz/">bunch</a> <a href="https://claytonerrington.com/">of</a> <a href="https://dougbelshaw.com/">like-minded</a> <a href="https://jlelse.blog/">folks</a> that are happy to discuss whatever I&#39;m rambling about, and it&#39;s great to read whatever they are rambling about as well! I&#39;m also thankful for all the nuggets of information I got to share with you, and also with my future self (seriously, you won&#39;t believe how often I&#39;m looking up old posts and being happy that I wrote that down!).</p>

<p>Thanks for reading, until next time!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 100 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                re: Giving context to a blogroll
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-20-giving-my-blogroll-more-context
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-20-giving-my-blogroll-more-context?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 20 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>This is a reply to Simone Silvestroni&#39;s <a href="https://minutestomidnight.co.uk/blog/giving-context-to-a-blogroll/">blog post</a> about blogrolls, which itself is a reply to a <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site">call for feedback</a> for my site.</p></blockquote>

<p>Simone argues that Blogroll entries without an explaination are just random links with a name. The reader doesn&#39;t know what&#39;s behind those links and therefore doesn&#39;t benefit from the blogroll. It would be better to give some context to the entries by explaining why they are on this list.</p>

<p>I absolutely support this idea. In response, I added context to all of my <a href="/blogroll">Blogroll</a> entries. I hope this helps you discover more awesome content on the web. Also, if you know a website that might fit on this list (maybe your own?), feel free to <a href="/contact">let me know</a>. I&#39;d be happy to read it!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 097 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Roast my Site!
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 12 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Let&#39;s try something: <code>#RoastMySite</code>!</p>

<p>I want to hear your honest feedback about my website. (Not so) constructive criticism, funny bug reports and savage burns. 🔥</p>

<p><a href="/contact">Shoot me a mail</a> with your roast and I&#39;ll include it on this site!</p>

<p>Got your own site? I&#39;ll roast it! Just ping me via mail or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@garritfra">on Mastodon</a>.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 093 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                PSA: RSS feed changes
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-06-rss-changes
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-07-06-rss-changes?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 06 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>If you&#39;re subscribed to this blog via <a href="/rss.xml">RSS</a>, you will soon likely see
a bunch of my posts re-appearing in your feed. For that, I apologize in advance!</p>

<p>I&#39;m planning to make two modifications. Firstly, I want to add a <code>id</code> property
to all entries. So far, your reader has been likely been relying on the URL slug
to identify an entry. Adding the <code>id</code> property makes this more flexible, but it
also means that your reader will think that there are new entries in the feed.
This will only happen once.</p>

<p>Secondly, I want to reduce the amount of the entries. If you look at the
<a href="/rss.xml">feed</a>, you&#39;ll see a lot of junk from way back, containing every word
I wrote on this blog. Remember that this page is fetched periodically (usually
every hour for most readers) by <strong>every</strong> subscriber. That&#39;s a lot of traffic
that could be better put to use somewhere else. Not that it costs me anything -
this site is hosted on <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> - but if this
helps reduce the carbon footprint of the site even by one gram, it&#39;s worth the
effort.</p>

<p>As of the time of writing this post, by restricting the number of posts to 10,
we reduce the amount of traffic per client per hour from 272 kB down to to 24
kB. That&#39;s over <strong>2 GB</strong> of traffic saved each year <strong>per subscriber</strong>!!</p>

<p>That&#39;s all - just a heads up. Thanks for your patience, you&#39;re awesome! ✌️</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 071 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Quality vs. Quantity
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>The amount and quality of the posts on this blog strongly depends on my mood. Some times I want to write about every thought that crosses my mind, leading to 4+ average- to low-quality posts a week. I think I&#39;m in one of these phases right now.</p>

<p>Some other times, I feel like most of my thoughts are not worth the effort to write about, but the ones that I <strong>do</strong> write about, often become the ones that I&#39;m <a href="/posts/2021-04-07-pgp-guide">most</a> <a href="/posts/2021-10-04-server-side-caching-with-apollo-graphql">proud</a> <a href="/posts/2021-01-18-reasons-the-fediverse-is-better">of</a>.</p>

<p>These phases act like opposing forces that coexist very well. Pumping out more thoughts of lesser quality frees up my mind for higher quality ones, and when I&#39;m writing about higher quality thoughts, I get the urge to write more often, completing the circuit.</p>

<p>In the end, it&#39;s not about <strong>what</strong> you write about, but about the process of writing itself. Every post on a personal blog is <a href="https://kevquirk.com/thoughts-on-editing-posts/">a snapshot of your thoughts at a point in time</a>, no matter if you&#39;re feeling qualitative or quantitative.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 062 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                A simple guestbook
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-10-05-simple-guestbook
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-10-05-simple-guestbook?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p><strong>TL;DR</strong>: Click <a href="/guestbook">here</a> to view the guestbook.</p></blockquote>

<p>For a while now, I wanted to have a quick way to update the pages on my website.</p>

<p>GitHub has the
<a href="https://docs.github.com/en/get-started/using-github/keyboard-shortcuts#source-code-editing">&quot;.&quot;</a>
hotkey, which opens a web based editor for the file you&#39;re currently viewing.
This site now has this feature as well! To try it out, just hit <code>.</code>, and you&#39;ll
be redirected to the file editor for this page.</p>

<p>To see how I implemented this feature, you take a look at
<a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/commit/658efa3a3ebfebebbf74d0eb6aae6c1cc9566516">this</a>
commit. It boils down to this snippet of code:</p>

<p><code></code><code>js
window.addEventListener(&quot;keypress&quot;, (e) =&gt; {
	if (e.key === &quot;.&quot;) {
		const baseUrl = &quot;https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/edit/main/content&quot;;
		const filePath = window.location.pathname;
		const url = </code>${baseUrl}${filePath}.md`;</p>

<pre><code>	window.location.href = url;
}</code></pre>

<p>});
<code></code>`</p>

<p>Pretty simple, huh?</p>

<p>Since this doesn&#39;t work on mobile devices, I also added <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/commit/8c374a8bc0b66192c454300489fee52e7299c9dd#diff-2cbafea0c9dff483ebab9ad670b1cdb3eb7aac552f9c161e42fee84c2efe3a69">a custom 404
page</a>
which also redirects to the editor, if the filepath ends with in <code>/edit</code>.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s have some fun and put this feature to use. I added a simple
<a href="/guestbook">guestbook</a> to this site, which is open to receive pull requests.
I&#39;d love to hear from you!</p>

<p>This is post 040 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Thoughts after 10 Days of 100DaysToOffload
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-02-11-10-percent-100daystooffload
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-02-11-10-percent-100daystooffload?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 11 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Coming into this, I didn&#39;t know what to expect. I&#39;m not a huge writer, but so far I am pleasantly surprised about how relaxing this challenge is.</p>

<p>At first glance, writing a blog post every 3-5 days seems daunting. But the more I write, the more it becomes an enjoyable habit. I&#39;m oftentimes looking forward to writing these posts. Whenever I have something on my mind, I jot it down without a plan or structure. And that&#39;s exactly the point of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>: <strong>Just. Write.</strong></p>

<p>So far, these blog posts have helped me get a lot of my thoughts out of my head and onto paper (or on a screen). While writing, I reflect on what I think. I sometimes realize that what I thought is utter nonsense, but this in itself is an important reflection. With each post, I feel like I am getting more confident about the process.</p>

<p>If you&#39;re reading this and you don&#39;t have a blog yet, I would encourage you to give this technique a try. It doesn&#39;t matter that you produce quality content, nor does anyone have to see this. It&#39;s not the content that matters, but the process of producing it. Set up your own blog on <a href="https://write.as/">write.as</a> or simply open your text editor of your choice and <strong>Just. Write.</strong></p>

<p>This is post 011 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>