<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Another reason you can't divide by zero
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-19-another-reason-you-can-t-divide-by-zero
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-19-another-reason-you-can-t-divide-by-zero?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>So, I recently wrote about [why you can&#39;t divide by zero](/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can&#39;t-divide-by-zero). In that post, I argued that dividing a number by zero breaks the rules of <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverse_function">inverse functions</a>. Of course that&#39;s not the only way to prove that the result of dividing a number by zero is not defined, so here&#39;s another.</p>

<p>If you approach the number zero from some arbitrary number as the divisor, you will find that the result is getting larger and larger: <code>1 / 1 = 1</code>, <code>1 / 0.5 = 2</code>, <code>1 / 0.1 = 10</code> and so on. If we keep dividing by smaller numbers, the result will get bigger and bigger. It&#39;s obvious that if we go all the way down to zero as the divisor, we will see infinity as the result, right? Well, no.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s flip this around and start from a negative number, going up towards the number zero: <code>1 / -1 = -1</code>, <code>1 / -0.5 = -2</code>, <code>1 / -0.1 = -10</code>. As you can see, the numbers are getting <strong>smaller</strong>, the more we approach the number zero! This shows that the results differ if we change the perspective on the problem. The result cannot be defined.</p>

<p>After writing the first post on this topic, I honestly didn&#39;t realize how complex this seemingly simple problem is. I&#39;m not a mathematician, but I&#39;m starting to like maths. Fascinating stuff!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 096 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Overcoming "air hunger"
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-18-overcoming-air-hunger?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>For as long as I can remember, I often had the feeling of not being able to get a full breath. I&#39;m taking deep breaths and sometimes forcing a yawn to overcome this feeling, sometimes successful, sometimes failing and trying again. This feeling gets worse the more I focus on my breath.</p>

<p>I always felt like this is somewhat uncommon, since none of my friends and family can relate to this feeling, but it wasn&#39;t worse enough to justify consulting a doctor about it either.</p>

<p>Doing some research, it seems like this phenomenon is called <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortness_of_breath">dyspnea</a>, or &quot;air hunger&quot;. Some guy even made <a href="https://airhunger.org/">a website</a> about it. In a nutshell, it is caused by your body not being able to regulate carbon levels in your blood, which leads to an urge to breath unnaturally.</p>

<p>In a <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=XliOGg8Tl98">video</a>, the author points out that this might be caused by irregular breathing patterns. Indeed, I often find myself breathing through the mouth or sitting in awkward positions with a humpback when the symptoms are at its worst. In fact, what led me to look this up was because I was annoyed by the feeling while I&#39;m laying in bed staring down at my screen, which is a very unnatural position.</p>

<p>A simple trick to get into a more regular breathing pattern is apparently to force yourself to breathe through the nose. Mouth breathing lets your body take in way more air than you need, which throws off the balance of the carbon levels in your lungs.</p>

<p>It seems like nose breathing does work very well. Where I&#39;ve just been struggling with air hunger, once I forced myself to nose breathe, the urge to breathe doesn&#39;t come nearly as often anymore.</p>

<p>These are just my results after some quick research. The topic of short breathing seems to be quite broad. Perhaps you&#39;re struggling with this as well. In that case, I hope this post was helpful to you!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 095 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                I'm finally off coffee
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-15-i-m-finally-off-coffee?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Disclaimer: There&#39;s no real story here — just a dump of my thoughts.</p>

<p>I used to drink two cups of coffee a day on average. One during breakfast and one during the day.</p>

<p>On days where it was difficult to get my hands on coffee — during camping for example, or on some days where I don&#39;t really have time to brew a coffee — I would routinely get headaches. This might have been a coincidence, but it&#39;s not unlikely that my body was craving this delicious drink. Waking up was always accompanied by this nagging feeling of how I&#39;m gonna get my dose of coffee today.</p>

<p>That all changed when I got sick a few weeks ago. I wasn&#39;t feeling well for a few days, and as a result I didn&#39;t drink coffee at all. Knowing that caffeine is a huge stress-inducing factor in my day to day life, I decided to just not start drinking it again once I felt better.</p>

<p>Quitting caffeine cold turkey can be difficult, but two cups isn&#39;t much. Some of my peers drink way more than that. While being sick, my body quickly adjusted to the missing two cups each day. I wasn&#39;t feeling good anyway, so what&#39;s an extra mild headache?</p>

<p>Now, about two weeks later, I feel great. There&#39;s one stress-factor less in my life. I occasionally still drink coffee with friends, but it&#39;s not something I crave directly after waking up. I opted for caffeine-free tea in the morning. We also have decaffeinated coffee at home, but it feels to me like brewing decaffeinated coffee isn&#39;t worth the effort. It&#39;s still a nice alternative for nice breakfasts on the weekend.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 094 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Roast my Site!
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 12 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Let&#39;s try something: <code>#RoastMySite</code>!</p>

<p>I want to hear your honest feedback about my website. (Not so) constructive criticism, funny bug reports and savage burns. 🔥</p>

<p><a href="/contact">Shoot me a mail</a> with your roast and I&#39;ll include it on this site!</p>

<p>Got your own site? I&#39;ll roast it! Just ping me via mail or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@garritfra">on Mastodon</a>.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 093 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Formula E is essentially Mario Kart
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-11-formula-e-is-essentially-mario-kart
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-11-formula-e-is-essentially-mario-kart?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 11 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I never actively watched a Formula E race, let alone Formula 1. Racing just isn&#39;t on my radar. However, I just came across <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=En-__5ewnAk">this</a> video about the driving style in Formula E races, and I was instantly hooked. Formula E is basically Mario Kart.</p>

<p>In a race, drivers can enter a so called &quot;attack mode&quot;, in which they can leave the optimal route in a turn to activate a significant power burst for a short while.</p>

<p><img alt="grafik" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/712c8317-a669-4a20-8d29-c746aea54392"/></p>

<p>Sound familiar? You bet!</p>

<p><img alt="grafik" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/22c8cf0f-6ac4-491d-8814-a24f937ec3a7"/></p>

<p>Additionally, drivers have the strategic option to &quot;hyperboost&quot; for some time. During a race, the drivers have to balance speed and efficiency. If your battery is empty, you&#39;re out of the race. The cars usually don&#39;t drive with full power to conserve energy, until the &quot;hyperboost&quot; is activated. So thinking about <strong>when</strong> to overtake a car plays a huge strategic role. Does that ring a bell?</p>

<p><img alt="grafik" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/18b326c6-e4db-495e-8cfb-1039f9c39691"/></p>

<p>Formula 1 cars generate <strong>a lot</strong> of data which is analyzed by the pit to predict tire wear, fuel usage, weather conditions and so on. In Formula E, no data is streamed to the pit at all. It&#39;s entirely up to the skill of the driver to make decisions. Again, just like in Mario Kart.</p>

<p>Although I have no stakes in car races whatsoever, I was blown away by this video about Formula E. If you liked this post, I suggest you <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=En-__5ewnAk">watch it by yourself</a> and let it be explained by an expert.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 092 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Field Notes #3
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Hooray! I just finished my third pocket notebook. If you have no idea what I mean, check out my <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">About My Pocket Notebook</a> post.</p>

<p>This notebook lasted from 2023-10-09 to 2023-12-01, which is a bit longer than my last two notebooks. I believe my inner hype around this topic slowly but surely fades into the background, which is a good thing. Instead of writing almost every single day, I only write in it when I feel that something is important.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3.jpeg"/></p>

<p>It aged quite well for a white notebook. You can clearly tell that I got some brand new pairs of jeans, looking at the color [before I used it](/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2#what&#39;s-next?) vs. now. Just like last time, I used this notebook for all sorts of things. Todo lists, bill calculations, random thoughts and sketches for blog posts.</p>

<p>What&#39;s different this time is that I started the book off with some &quot;meta pages&quot;. The first two pages serve as an index for the book. I ripped this idea stright from the <a href="https://bulletjournal.com/">Bullet Journal</a> movement, but that&#39;s about the only thing I stole from BuJos.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3 Index" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3_index.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I also dedicated one page to a general purpose packing list, which I used multiple times to check if I forgot anything for an overnight stay. This page served me very well, so I&#39;m transfering it into my new notebook.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>My next notebook will once again be a FIELD NOTES. I just love the size, the feel and the quality of them. This time, I&#39;m using the &quot;National Parks&quot; edition, or more specifically the &quot;Glacier National Park&quot; notebook from a set. It started to snow, so this is an obvious choice.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #4" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_4.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Thanks for sticking with me through this weird and awesome hobby!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 091 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Why you can't divide by zero
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can't-divide-by-zero
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-30-why-you-can't-divide-by-zero?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 30 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I&#39;ve always been wondering why dividing by zero is considered undefined. My intuitive answer would have always been &quot;infinity&quot; or &quot;zero&quot;. I just had a discussion about this with a collegue who happens to have a degree in mathematics, and the way they explained it made it absolutely clear why it doesn&#39;t make sense to divide by zero.</p>

<h2>Inverse Operations</h2>

<p>Before understanding why dividing by zero is undefined, you first need to know about inverse operations. It&#39;s quite simple!</p>

<p>An example: <code>3 + 2 = 5</code>. The inverse of addition is <em>subtraction</em>, so the inverse of this equation is <code>5 - 2 = 3</code> or <code>5 - 3 = 2</code>.</p>

<p>The same applies to multiplication. The inverse of multiplation is <em>division</em>. So the inverse of <code>6 * 2 = 12</code> is <code>12 / 2 = 6</code> or <code>12 / 6 = 2</code>.</p>

<h2>Dividing by zero</h2>

<p>Let&#39;s try to apply the inverse rule to the number zero, starting with addition. If <code>2 + 0 = 2</code>, then <code>2 - 0 = 2</code>.</p>

<p>But if we have <code>2 * 0 = 0</code>, the inverse of that would be <code>0 / 0 = 2</code>, which is just not true.</p>

<p>Dividing by zero breaks some fundamental laws of mathematics, which is why there&#39;s a general consensus that any equasion dividing by zero has no valid answer.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 090 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Real vs. Fake Trends
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-29-real-vs.-fake-trends
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-29-real-vs.-fake-trends?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 29 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>The most important indicator to figure out if an emerging trend will be successful is to ask yourself if people tell their friends about it.</p>

<p>To figure out if a product/market will live through the hype-cycle and succeed in the long run, see if the people are actually <strong>using it</strong> obsessively.</p>

<p>When the iPhone first came out, it barely sold any units compared to the big players at the time. But it succeeded because people who owned an iPhone used it for hours every day.</p>

<p>VR on the other hand gained a lot of traction in the press, but despite telling their friends about it, hardly anyone owning a VR headset actually uses it (I use mine about once a month).</p>

<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href="https://youtu.be/0lJKucu6HJc?si=HwIpCJ3g0uqwmtQf">Sam Altman - How to Succeed with a Startup</a></p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 089 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                The speed of light
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-26-the-speed-of-light
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-26-the-speed-of-light?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 26 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>If you could bend light, it could orbit the earth 7.5 times in one second.</p>

<p>The light we see from our sun is around 8 <strong>minutes</strong> old. That&#39;s how much time it takes light to travel from the sun to our earth.</p>

<p>It takes light 4.26 <strong>years</strong> to reach the nearest star (Alpha Centauri). Many stars we see at night are about 1.000 light years away. The next galaxy (Andromeda), 27.000 light years.</p>

<p>Many of these lights have already faded — their death just hasn&#39;t reached us yet.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 088 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                A Positive Hacker News RSS Feed
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-24-positive-hackernews
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-24-positive-hackernews?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 24 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Tech news can often be overwhelmingly negative. Scrolling through <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com">HackerNews</a>, I often feel myself getting angrier at the state of the industry with each headline I read.</p>

<p>I don&#39;t want to give up on the amazing content I&#39;m discovering every day on this platform, so I built an alternative RSS feed for HackerNews. It selectively presents stories that have a positive sentiment, making my news-reading experience more enjoyable and less stressful. Here&#39;s a link to the feed:</p>

<p>https://garritfra.github.io/positive_hackernews/feed.xml</p>

<p>It&#39;s not a pretty link, but who looks at the link of an RSS feed anyway? ;)</p>

<h2>Comparison</h2>

<p>Here&#39;s an example of the HackerNews feed provided by <a href="https://hnrss.github.io/">hnrss.github.io</a>:</p>

<p><img alt="Before" src="/assets/posts/2023-11-24-positive-hackernews/before.png"/></p>

<p>And here&#39;s the filtered, positive-only feed:</p>

<p><img alt="After" src="/assets/posts/2023-11-24-positive-hackernews/after.png"/></p>

<p>I don&#39;t want to urge anyone to stop reading HackerNews, but if you also struggle with seeing the bright side of tech, this could be a nice alternative.</p>

<h2>Contributing</h2>

<p>The source code behind this project can be found on <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/positive_hackernews">GitHub</a>. It&#39;s licensed as <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/positive_hackernews/blob/main/LICENSE">MIT</a>, so feel free to fork and build your own feed. Happy hacking!</p>

<h2>Responses</h2>

<ul><li><a href="https://cosmicqbit.dev/positive-hacker-news-feed/">cosmicqbit.dev</a></li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 087 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>