<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Field Notes #3
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Hooray! I just finished my third pocket notebook. If you have no idea what I mean, check out my <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">About My Pocket Notebook</a> post.</p>

<p>This notebook lasted from 2023-10-09 to 2023-12-01, which is a bit longer than my last two notebooks. I believe my inner hype around this topic slowly but surely fades into the background, which is a good thing. Instead of writing almost every single day, I only write in it when I feel that something is important.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3.jpeg"/></p>

<p>It aged quite well for a white notebook. You can clearly tell that I got some brand new pairs of jeans, looking at the color [before I used it](/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2#what&#39;s-next?) vs. now. Just like last time, I used this notebook for all sorts of things. Todo lists, bill calculations, random thoughts and sketches for blog posts.</p>

<p>What&#39;s different this time is that I started the book off with some &quot;meta pages&quot;. The first two pages serve as an index for the book. I ripped this idea stright from the <a href="https://bulletjournal.com/">Bullet Journal</a> movement, but that&#39;s about the only thing I stole from BuJos.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3 Index" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_3_index.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I also dedicated one page to a general purpose packing list, which I used multiple times to check if I forgot anything for an overnight stay. This page served me very well, so I&#39;m transfering it into my new notebook.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>My next notebook will once again be a FIELD NOTES. I just love the size, the feel and the quality of them. This time, I&#39;m using the &quot;National Parks&quot; edition, or more specifically the &quot;Glacier National Park&quot; notebook from a set. It started to snow, so this is an obvious choice.</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #4" src="/assets/posts/2023-12-01-field-notes-3/field_notes_4.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Thanks for sticking with me through this weird and awesome hobby!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 091 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Field Notes #2
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 09 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Today marks the completion of my second pocket notebook. You may view my <a href="/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks">About My Pocket Notebook</a> post as part one of this series, since I wrote it near the end of my first notebook. I think it would be interesting to share my experience with this each notebook. One day I&#39;ll maybe have a nice history of posts that I can look back at. 🙂</p>

<p>This notebook lasted from 2023-09-10 to 2023-10-09, roughly one month. Here&#39;s a picture of it, after living in my back pocket every single day:</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #2" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_2.jpeg"/></p>

<h3>What&#39;s in it?</h3>

<p>I used this notebook as a todo list, a travel journal, quick sketches, braindumps, simple calculations and much more. It&#39;s become a place to dump thoughts whenever and wherever I want to. Sometimes, it&#39;s genuinely interesting facts, like how to find north when all you have is a clear night sky.</p>

<p><img alt="Notes on how to find north at night" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_2_page_5.jpeg"/></p>

<p>And sometimes it&#39;s just a random collection of uninteresting thoughts that wouldn&#39;t leave my head.</p>

<p><img alt="Random collection of notes" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_2_page_32.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Some of these notes may mature into a project or blog post, like <a href="/posts/2023-09-29-undo-on-mobile-phones">the second to last note on that page</a>, while others just fade into the abyss. But that&#39;s okay! The point is to get these thoughts out of my head to work with them more easily.</p>

<h3>What&#39;s next?</h3>

<p>I&#39;ll keep on writing! I got a bunch of new FIELD NOTES notebooks to fill up. Since my next notebook will likely live with me through the halloween season, I opted for the <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/products/harvest">Harvest</a> edition as my next notebook. 🎃</p>

<p><img alt="Field Notes #3" src="/assets/posts/2023-10-09-field-notes-2/field_notes_3.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I&#39;m curious to see where this one takes me.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 081 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                About My Pocket Notebook
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-09-everyday-carry-notebooks?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 09 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Since about a month ago, I&#39;ve been carrying a tiny pocket notebook with me wherever
I go. It&#39;s small enough to fit in every pocket imaginable. It doesn&#39;t need to
be recharged, it doesn&#39;t care if it gets wet. It&#39;s just right there whenever I
need it.</p>

<p><img alt="My Notebook on a recent hike" src="/assets/posts/2023-09-09-about-my-pocket-notebook/hike.jpeg"/></p>

<p>As someone living with ADHD, I often find myself overwhelmed by random thoughts and environmental stimuli. Writing my thoughts down on pen and paper helps a lot in those moments, but until now, I&#39;ve yet to come across a technique that stuck with me for an entire month. I take a lot of notes at work and I feel that it helps me stay organized, but I haven&#39;t found a way to use the same technique in my free time. I once tried keeping a notebook in my backpack, but there are moments where I just don&#39;t have my backpack with me, so I neglected it soon after I started.</p>

<p>That all changed when I stumbled across a video titled <a href="https://youtu.be/0xssCfBiUds?si=vxclEs1UxK5tlkL0">&quot;This pocket notebook is (slowly) replacing my phone&quot;</a>. It instantly clicked for me. Carrying a tiny notebook alongside my phone surely can&#39;t be that hard. And indeed, it isn&#39;t! At night, I put the notebook right next to my phone on my desk. After waking up, I grab my phone, and the notebook is right there for me to take as well. It&#39;s become a habit to check if the notebook is there, just like checking your keys when leaving the house.</p>

<p>Phones are optimized to grab your attention whenever and wherever you are. After hours of mindless scrolling through various feeds, I feel like the phone has won the war over me and I begin to feel tired and overwhelmed. Having a notebook always with me, I now get a sense of control over where I&#39;m allocating my attention. Instead of reaching for my phone, I might as well pull out the notebook and scribble whatever is on my mind in that moment. I get to choose what I&#39;m writing down, instead of mindlessly consuming content I&#39;m not even interested in.</p>

<p>In my current notebook, there are lists of things I did on some random day, ideas for side-projects, long paragraphs of unsorted thoughts, stamps I collected during a hike, and bad doodles of trees. It really doesn&#39;t matter <strong>what</strong> I&#39;m writing. It&#39;s about bringing awareness to what&#39;s on my mind.</p>

<h2>Notebook sizes</h2>

<p>I&#39;m still playing around with different sizes of notebooks. So far, I&#39;ve been using a <a href="https://www.moleskine.com/en-us/shop/notebooks/journals/volant-journals/volant-journals-forget-me-not-blue-and-amber-yellow-8058647620541.html">Moleskine Volant XS</a> notebook, which is 6.5 x 10 cm in size. It fits comfortably in the palm of my hand and easily slides in every pocket imaginable. I&#39;d say it&#39;s the perfect size for this purpose!</p>

<p><img alt="My current notebook" src="/assets/posts/2023-09-09-about-my-pocket-notebook/moleskine.jpeg"/></p>

<p>As this notebook comes to an end (it took about a month to fill), I want to try out the slightly larger <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/products/original-kraft">Field Notes</a> notebook. It&#39;s about 9 x 14 cm and <em>just barely</em> fits in my back pocket. My concern is that it&#39;s too big to carry in tighter pockets, but from what I&#39;ve read online so far, people seem to love this form factor. In my opinion Field Notes have a very unique vibe to them, and although the price is quite hefty (about 15€ for a pack of three, including shipping), they do make it up in style.</p>

<p><img alt="A Field Notes notebook" src="/assets/posts/2023-09-09-about-my-pocket-notebook/field_notes.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Field Notes also have awesome quarterly <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/limited-editions">limited editions</a> that give them an aspect of collectability (just look at their <a href="https://fieldnotesbrand.com/products/national-parks">National Parks</a> series. They&#39;re gorgeous! 🤤). There&#39;s definetely a lot of hype around them, so if you don&#39;t care about the aesthetics, you can always opt for way cheaper alternatives from your local stationary store (around 2€ or lower).</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>After a month of carrying this notebook with me, I do feel that it increased my mental clarity quite a lot. I have a sense of control over my thoughts that I never had before. Whenever I&#39;m sitting down with my notebook and a pen, I instantly notice things around me that I wouldn&#39;t have noticed if I stared at my phone instead.</p>

<p>Notebooks and other so called &quot;EDC&quot; (everyday carry) items are a true rabbit hole (look it up, you&#39;d be surprised), and its easy to get lost in the details. If you&#39;re interested in trying this technique for yourself, just grab whatever tiny notebook you can find and <em>just write</em>.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 075 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>