<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Sun, 26 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Software is not defined by the language it's written in
            </title>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-03-26-software-is-not-defined-by-the-language-it's-written-in?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 26 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Rust is not just a programming language, it&#39;s also a status symbol. By now, it kind of became a meme that people writing programs in Rust have to make explicit that &quot;X is written in Rust&quot;.</p>

<p>How fast or safe the language is doesn&#39;t define how good the software is. Software in TypeScript can be just as good as software written in C, if written by the right people.</p>

<p>When starting a new project, try to focus on the domain of the problem and pick a language based on that. Don&#39;t decide on the language before you know what problem you&#39;re trying to solve. If the answer to this is always one option (like Rust), <a href="https://seths.blog/2023/03/the-answer-to-every-question/">you might be in a bubble</a>.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 060 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                I won't buy a YubiKey
            </title>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-03-21-i-wont-buy-a-yubikey?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 21 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I have a YubiKey that I use for work, and I love using it. But I won&#39;t get one for my personal life.</p>

<p>I&#39;ve been thinking about this for some time now, but I ultimately don&#39;t think the benefits outweigh the hassle of always carrying around another device that I risk losing or breaking.</p>

<p>A Yubikey provides a very good second factor, but so does my phone. My phone, just like a Yubikey, is locked behind a third factor (a pin or biometric sensor), so my phone essentially <em>is</em> a Yubikey. You can argue that the authenticator app on my phone (bitwarden) can be hacked, but I&#39;m willing to take that risk if it means I have to reset all security measures on all accounts if I lose the key.</p>

<p>So, I&#39;m not getting a Yubikey.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 058 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>