<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Notes on &quot;Immutability Changes Everything&quot;
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-21-notes-on-immutability
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-21-notes-on-immutability?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Published books are immutable. Accountants don&#39;t use erasers or they go to jail.</p></blockquote>

<p>The paper <a href="https://www.cidrdb.org/cidr2015/Papers/CIDR15_Paper16.pdf">Immutability Changes Everything</a> by Pat Helland talks about the trend towards immutability in data storage thoughout all layers of the stack. From append-only apps (Record changes, then derive the current state), down to how bits are stored on a hard drive (e.g. Copy on Write).</p>

<p>I stumbled upon this paper through the <a href="https://paperswelove.org/">Papers We Love</a> collection. I was specifically looking for a paper that&#39;s short and easy to comprehend, since I don&#39;t have much experience in reading scientific papers. This is absolutely both short and easy to comprehend. If you&#39;re a beginner like me, I can highly recommend this one to you.</p>

<p>Key takeaways:</p>

<ul><li>Immutability enables clean replication</li><li>Change logs (e.g. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Write-ahead_logging">write-ahead logs</a>) are the source of truth. The database is a cache of a subset of those change logs</li><li>It&#39;s okay to consider violating <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Database_normalization">normalization</a> rules to trade storage cost for read speed</li><li>Modern SSDs minimize wear by storing new versions of data to other blocks instead of mutating the data in place</li><li>The cost of immutability is increased storage</li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 098 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>