<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                To proof something is true, try disproofing it first
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-30-to-proof-something-is-true-try-disproofing-it-first
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-30-to-proof-something-is-true-try-disproofing-it-first?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>We&#39;ve been taught that, to proof that a thing is true, we should point out what&#39;s true about it.</p>

<p>However, we can learn much more about why something is true by trying to <strong>disproof</strong> it first. If you think something is true, try as hard as you can to proof that it&#39;s false.</p>

<p>Disproofing a theory is core to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_method">scientific method</a>. Only when we validate that something cannot be false, we come closer to proofing that it&#39;s true.</p>

<h2>Source</h2>

<p>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vKA4w2O61Xo?si=2dtApWo8JmHOwqff&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Temporal vs. fundamental content
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-02-temporal-vs-fundamental-content?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just read <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38829907">this comment</a> on a thread on HackerNews which resonated with me:</p>

<blockquote><p>I&#39;m trying to read less temporal (things that matter now) and more fundamental (stuff that mattered 1+ year ago and will still matter in 1+ year, with even wider intervals for non-tech content).
This does result in missing ~important things occasionally (e.g. I still don&#39;t know what happened with SamA at OpenAI, and yes, I am curious), but that&#39;s a small price to pay for greater intellectual sanctity and an increased attention budget to distribute across important tasks or funnel into something hyper focussed.</p></blockquote>

<p>Is this news important <em>now</em> or do I benefit from it in the long term? Our time is the most precious resource we have, and we should be careful how we spend it.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Real vs. Fake Trends
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-29-real-vs.-fake-trends
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-11-29-real-vs.-fake-trends?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 29 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>The most important indicator to figure out if an emerging trend will be successful is to ask yourself if people tell their friends about it.</p>

<p>To figure out if a product/market will live through the hype-cycle and succeed in the long run, see if the people are actually <strong>using it</strong> obsessively.</p>

<p>When the iPhone first came out, it barely sold any units compared to the big players at the time. But it succeeded because people who owned an iPhone used it for hours every day.</p>

<p>VR on the other hand gained a lot of traction in the press, but despite telling their friends about it, hardly anyone owning a VR headset actually uses it (I use mine about once a month).</p>

<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href="https://youtu.be/0lJKucu6HJc?si=HwIpCJ3g0uqwmtQf">Sam Altman - How to Succeed with a Startup</a></p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 089 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                A software requirements checklist
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-03-11-a-software-requirements-checklist
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-03-11-a-software-requirements-checklist?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 11 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just found a <a href="https://www.etsy.com/codeascraft/a-checklist-manifetsy">great post</a> on the Etsy Engineering blog suggesting a possible checklist for new product requirements. In reality, this checklist is very hard to fulfill, but it&#39;s a nice reminder of what a well thought out requirement could look like.</p>

<h3>Scope</h3>

<ul><li>Is the feature meant to be very polished and finished or are we just trying to get user feedback as an MVP?</li><li>If we are running a MVP, is the current feature a true MVP? How can we simplify or cut scope?</li></ul>

<h3>Eligibility</h3>

<ul><li>What populations should be included or excluded from the experiment? When should users see this feature? (Which pages, signed in/signed out, mobile, desktop, etc.)
Where/when should bucketing occur?</li><li>Will the experiment conflict with any other experiments? Do the experiments need to run exclusively?</li><li>What countries should the experiment run in (can impact translations)?</li></ul>

<h3>A11Y</h3>

<ul><li>Is there any special accessibility work this feature will require? If extra work is anticipated, check in early with our a11y team.</li><li>When testing and developing we should keep two users in mind - a keyboard user and a voice over user, do we need to add other code for these users?</li></ul>

<h3>Translations</h3>

<ul><li>Are there any strings to be translated that should be submitted ASAP?</li><li>Do we need to translate any labels for a11y?</li></ul>

<h3>Observability</h3>

<ul><li>How will we know that the feature is working? Are there existing graphs we can use or do we need new ones?</li><li>Should any of these metrics have a threshold or alerting?</li><li>Are we missing any key events to obtain user feedback?</li><li>How will we compare our control and variant?</li></ul>

<h3>Performance</h3>

<ul><li>Is there anything in my experiment that could degrade performance of the site?</li><li>Do I need an operational experiment to verify that I’m not impacting performance?</li></ul>

<h3>Error States</h3>

<ul><li>Do we have designs for loading states?</li><li>Do we have designs for unsuccessful requests and error handling?</li><li>Do we have informative logging when there are errors?</li></ul>

<h3>QA</h3>

<ul><li>What set of browsers and devices should we test our new feature against?</li><li>Which user perspectives do we need to test?</li></ul>

<h3>Ramping</h3>

<ul><li>What will our ramping strategy be?</li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://www.etsy.com/codeascraft/a-checklist-manifetsy">original post</a> for a full writeup and the intentions behind this checklist.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 056 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>