<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                2023 in review
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>That&#39;s a wrap! 2023 was an exciting year for me. I started my new role as a <a href="/posts/2023-04-22-the-role-of-a-devops-engineer">DevOps Engineer</a> at my current company, I got <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/open-source-der-patch-basierte-git-workflow-soll-bleiben-2302-171585.html">two</a> <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/wertestrom-in-devops-das-projekt-am-laufen-halten-2312-180174.html">articles</a> published on a prominent German news site and finally finished my <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a> challenge!</p>

<p>This year, I launched two projects: <a href="https://sendpasswords.net/">sendpasswords.net</a> and <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/positive_hackernews">Positive Hacker News</a>.</p>

<p>In <a href="/posts/2023-01-02-welcome-2023">last year&#39;s review</a>, I said I wanted to launch <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/fling">Fling</a>, my household management app. Fling is currently in open alpha, so you can try it out <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=de.garritfra.fling">on Android</a> or via the <a href="https://fling-list.web.app">hosted website</a> to give feedback! I&#39;m planning a public release very soon.</p>

<p>Furthermore, I wanted to launch <a href="https://docs.kubinity.com/">Kubinity</a>. This was a very ambitious project, and although it technically works, it&#39;s very hard to maintain due to high running costs, which I&#39;m not ready to pay yet.</p>

<p>I have some more drafts for projects in private repositories. One project that I&#39;m feeling comfortable to release next year is a website for the #10ShittyProjects (working title) hashtag. More on that hopefully later!</p>

<h2>Goals for 2024</h2>

<p>Here are some personal goals that I want to set myself for the upcoming year. Some of them are already defined on my <a href="/impossible">impossible list</a>.</p>

<ul><li>Build a side project that generated at least 100€ of value</li><li>Get a scuba diving license</li><li>Do a 10 km run (I really need to start moving again)</li><li>Sell my car</li><li>Write at least 50 blog posts</li></ul>

<h2>Prediction results</h2>

<p><strong>&quot;Meta will change course (again), and kill the &quot;Metaverse&quot;&quot;</strong></p>

<p>A <a href="https://labs.sogeti.com/the-metaverse-is-dead/#:~:text=The%20Real%20Promise%20of%20VR%2FAR%20Lies%20in%20Training%20Simulations&amp;text=Yet%2C%20as%20of%202023%2C%20we,Reality%20(AR)%20has%20diminished.">quick Google search</a> reveals that the metaverse as originally imagined is not dead, but it&#39;s focus shifted to a more enterprise-y approach. I must admit that this prediction was quite vague. Depending on whom you ask, the metaverse is <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schr%C3%B6dinger%27s_cat">both alive and dead at the same time</a>.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Cheap matter devices will enter the market. As a reference point: I predict that there will be a matter-ready smart plug for under 20€ on Amazon&quot;</strong></p>

<p>I found <a href="https://amzn.eu/d/iA9ZBQf">this</a> matter-enabled smart plug on Amazon for 19,54€. If this is a real product, I&#39;d say my prediction is a pass!</p>

<p><strong>&quot;AI generated content will be regulated in some way&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Also a pass! On December 9th, the European union agreed on the <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/headlines/society/20230601STO93804/eu-ai-act-first-regulation-on-artificial-intelligence">EU AI Act</a> and will now become EU law.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Twitter is still around, but it&#39;s still not profitable&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Twitter is in fact <a href="https://www.businessofapps.com/data/twitter-statistics/#:~:text=Twitter%20generated%20%244.4%20billion%20revenue%20in%202022%2C%20a%2011%25%20decrease,a%20loss%20of%20advertising%20revenue.">still not profitable</a>. I&#39;ll leave the &quot;Twitter is still around&quot; part up for debate, as it&#39;s now called X.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;I still won&#39;t have finished my #100DaysToOffload challenge from 2021&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Wrong!! In early December, I decided to push through and whip out one post a day. I <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it">finished the challenge</a>!</p>

<h2>2023 Predictions</h2>

<ul><li>Bitcoin will at last reach a value of 100,000$, following the <a href="https://www.nicehash.com/countdown/btc-halving-2024-05-10-12-00">halving</a> likely happening in 2024</li><li>SpaceX will send a <a href="https://www.spacex.com/vehicles/starship/">Starship</a> prototype to moon or Mars</li><li>Tesla cars a still not fully self driving (<a href="https://motherfrunker.ca/fsd/">reference</a>)</li><li>Google will replace their main search with an AI chat bot (see <a href="https://bard.google.com">Bard</a>)</li></ul>

<p>Let&#39;s see what 2024 brings to the table!</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Notes on "Immutability Changes Everything"
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-21-notes-on-immutability
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-21-notes-on-immutability?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Published books are immutable. Accountants don&#39;t use erasers or they go to jail.</p></blockquote>

<p>The paper <a href="https://www.cidrdb.org/cidr2015/Papers/CIDR15_Paper16.pdf">Immutability Changes Everything</a> by Pat Helland talks about the trend towards immutability in data storage thoughout all layers of the stack. From append-only apps (Record changes, then derive the current state), down to how bits are stored on a hard drive (e.g. Copy on Write).</p>

<p>I stumbled upon this paper through the <a href="https://paperswelove.org/">Papers We Love</a> collection. I was specifically looking for a paper that&#39;s short and easy to comprehend, since I don&#39;t have much experience in reading scientific papers. This is absolutely both short and easy to comprehend. If you&#39;re a beginner like me, I can highly recommend this one to you.</p>

<p>Key takeaways:</p>

<ul><li>Immutability enables clean replication</li><li>Change logs (e.g. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Write-ahead_logging">write-ahead logs</a>) are the source of truth. The database is a cache of a subset of those change logs</li><li>It&#39;s okay to consider violating <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Database_normalization">normalization</a> rules to trade storage cost for read speed</li><li>Modern SSDs minimize wear by storing new versions of data to other blocks instead of mutating the data in place</li><li>The cost of immutability is increased storage</li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 098 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Project Hail Mary
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-03-project-hail-mary
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-03-project-hail-mary?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just finished the book <a href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Hail_Mary">Project Hail Mary</a> by Andy Weir. Rating: ⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐</p>

<p>I&#39;m completely nerdsniped. I was looking forward to each chapter, eagerly waiting for what will happen next. This book is full of completely unexpected turns, though I never felt lost. The plot is well thought out. Every chapter is like a puzzle piece that perfectly adds to the greater picture.</p>

<p>When I first heard about this book I was a bit skeptical. &quot;Human stranded in space&quot; surely can&#39;t fill some 500 pages (I&#39;m looking at you, <a href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravity_(2013_film)">Gravity</a>). But having read <a href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Martian_(Weir_novel)#">The Martian</a> some time ago, I knew that Andy Weir&#39;s style of writing would catch me. And catch me he did. The way he describes complex topics completely resonates with me. No matter how unsolvable the problems of the protagonist seem, it&#39;s always an invitation to get your mind blown by the solution.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 080 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>