<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                2024 in Review
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-12-29-2024-in-review
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-12-29-2024-in-review?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>It&#39;s super exciting looking back at 2024. So much has happened! I haven&#39;t been very active on this blog lately, mainly because I&#39;ve been super busy in other areas of life.</p>

<p>The biggest change for me this year is one that I can cross off of my <a href="/impossible">impossible list</a>: We bought a house! I&#39;ve been wanting to write post about this for a few weeks, and now that things are settling in, I might have the time to do that. In short: We moved from Brunswick (Germany) back to a more rural town just outside Brunswick. It&#39;s closer to my girlfriends workplace, closer to my family and overall way cheaper than properties in Brunswick. We&#39;re super happy about the house and have yet to find any major annoyances. The neighbors are nice, and the community is incredibly wholesome.</p>

<p>As for other personal projects, there hasn’t been as much traction as there used to be. My interests have partially shifted to hobbies that don’t involve a computer, which I’m grateful for. I still love building software projects – especially now that it’s become so easy to get started with a project using an AI brainstorming companion – I just do it less often. I picked up running as a hobby (more on that later), gather with friends to play Dungeons &amp; Dragons and work on stuff in my new basement.</p>

<h2>Goal Results</h2>

<p>These are the goals <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review">I set myself for 2024</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Build a side project that generated at least 100€ of value</p></blockquote>

<p>That’s a bust. As mentioned, I haven’t really spent a lot of time building side projects. And the ones I did build, I consider tools rather than an income stream.</p>

<blockquote><p>Get a scuba diving license</p></blockquote>

<p>I’m a certified PADI Open Water Diver! You can see some impressions <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-26-dive-log-phuket">here</a> and <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-03-12-dive-log-vietnam">here</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Do a 10 km run (I really need to start moving again)</p></blockquote>

<p>I ran three 10k runs this year. <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/11416831567">The first in May</a>, then in <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/11768631707">June</a> and finally, <a href="https://strava.app.link/P0Ulu4L1IPb">in September</a>, I improved my 2018 personal best by a few minutes!</p>

<blockquote><p>Sell my car</p></blockquote>

<p>Check. More infos <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-08-i-sold-my-car">here</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Write at least 50 blog posts</p></blockquote>

<p>I didn’t reach this goal, but I’m also not disappointed by it. <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity">The frequency of my posts varies</a>, and this year it was just lower than before.</p>

<h2>2025 Goals</h2>

<p>Here are some new goals for this year:</p>

<ul><li>Build a side project that generated at least 100€ of value (I’m keeping this goal until I reach it!)</li><li>Run a half marathon (and optionally <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/985747064">beat my PB</a>)</li><li>Learn woodworking and build something that takes at least 3 days to complete</li></ul>

<h2>Prediction Results</h2>

<p>The results for <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review">last years predictions</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Bitcoin will at last reach a value of 100,000$, following the<a href="https://www.nicehash.com/countdown/btc-halving-2024-05-10-12-00"> halving</a> likely happening in 2024</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/business/markets/bitcoin-100000-rcna181008">Bitcoin did reach 100,000$</a>, though not following the halving event. Still, I’d call this a pass!</p>

<blockquote><p>SpaceX will use a <a href="https://www.spacex.com/vehicles/starship/">Starship</a> prototype to launch Starlink satellites into orbit</p></blockquote>

<p>Nope, they didn’t. But they made incredible leaps.</p>

<blockquote><p>Tesla cars a still not fully self driving (<a href="https://motherfrunker.ca/fsd/">reference</a>)</p></blockquote>

<p>They claim to launch it in Europe <a href="https://www.euronews.com/next/2024/09/05/tesla-says-full-self-driving-car-expected-in-europe-early-next-year-pending-regulatory-app">earlier next year</a>. It’s currently in closed testing. Still, I wouldn’t give it a pass.</p>

<blockquote><p>Google will replace their main search with an AI chat bot (see<a href="https://bard.google.com/"> Bard</a>)</p></blockquote>

<p>Not sure if I’d call Gemini a full replacement, but it does have a wrapper around their traditional search engine. The product is shit compared to Anthropic and OpenAI, but I would call this a pass, since you can use Gemini instead of Google Search.</p>

<h2>2025 Predictions</h2>

<ul><li>Apple will not ship a successor to the Apple Vision Pro</li><li>At least one country will mandate AI watermarking for all AI-generated content used in commercial applications</li><li>Russia and Ukraine will come to a consensus and end the war. Ukraine will have lost territory</li></ul>

<p>And that&#39;s a wrap. I hope you all had a wonderful Christmas (if celebrated), and are as excited as I am for the new year!</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                About my 'smart' G-Shock
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-10-about-my-smart-g-shock
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-05-10-about-my-smart-g-shock?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 10 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>About two weeks ago, I got myself my very first G-Shock. My entry ticket to the <a href="https://mastodon.social/tags/CasioCult">#CasioCult</a>! Since I didn&#39;t want to miss out on any fitness features, I went with the <a href="https://www.casio.com/de/watches/gshock/product.DW-H5600-1/">G-Shock GW-H5600</a>, which comes with heart rate monitoring, step tracking and some other nice to have features.</p>

<p><img alt="A G-Shock DW-H5600" src="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/assets/32395585/ab17acee-5997-4a3d-8536-c8c8243d72d2"/></p>

<p>Having read every review I could find, I knew that the watch had some quirks, but I ultimately loved the look of it. But two weeks later, I&#39;m forced to return the watch. Let me first go over what I liked and dislike about this watch.</p>

<h2>Pros</h2>

<p><strong>It&#39;s a G-Shock</strong></p>

<p>I love the look and feel of a G-Shock and other Casio watches. This is my first G-Shock, but I&#39;ve had an eye on this brand for quite some time. It&#39;s tough, sturdy, waterproof and probably also bullet proof.</p>

<p><strong>The display</strong></p>

<p>Oh, the display! It&#39;s gorgeous. Many people are complaining why this MIP display hasn&#39;t found its way to the rest of the G-Shock lineup. But I&#39;m sure they will retrofit other models soon.</p>

<p><strong>Proper paper manual</strong></p>

<p>My first impression after the unboxing was &quot;holy sheers, the manual is a <strong>book</strong>&quot;! And I mean that in the best way possible. Every little feature of the watch is explained in extreme detail in the manual. You rarely see this in other watches or gadgets these days.</p>

<h2>Cons</h2>

<p><strong>Questionable UI and UX decisions</strong></p>

<p>G-Shocks are known for user interfaces that &quot;just work&quot;. In this watch however, there are a few things that really make the watch frustrating to operate. Just to name a few quirks:</p>

<ul><li>There&#39;s only &quot;forward&quot;. If you scrolled passed something, you have to go aaaaall the way through the menu.</li><li>The timer can only be increased in 30 second steps. The UI is quite laggy, so setting a 10 minute timer takes about 1 minute of mashing buttons. There&#39;s also no press and hold.</li><li>The stopwatch only counts in seconds. No milliseconds.</li><li>You&#39;re locked to one task at a time. If you have a timer running, you can&#39;t go out of the menu. If you&#39;re recording a workout, you can&#39;t change the settings. And my favorite: You have to be on the home screen to sync settings from your phone to your watch. Just ... why?!</li><li>With a more or less recent update, the light now always turns on when you press any button. This makes the &quot;light&quot; button on the top right completely obsolete.</li><li>Unspecific battery indicator. You have four bars in the battery icon, that&#39;s it. The watch is solar powered, but it&#39;s to top up the battery at best. Don&#39;t expect to run fully off solar with this watch.</li></ul>

<p><strong>A bit thick</strong></p>

<p>Below the already thick bezel of the G-Shock sits the heart rate monitor, which is obnoxiously huge. I personally didn&#39;t feel like it irritated my skin, but it does add to the thickness.</p>

<p><strong>Fitness Features</strong></p>

<p>This is a two-edged sword. I originally wanted to list this as a pro. Features like run tracking, cardio status and sleep analysis are there, and they work fine. The step tracking and heart rate monitoring can be a bit off from time to time, but it&#39;s fine for the occasional run.</p>

<p>What&#39;s really bothering me is the mediocre implementation. There&#39;s no workout detection, the autopause feature barely works and you&#39;re limited to running, walking, gym workout and interval training. I also want to log my bike rides, which will always show up as a running activity in my app.</p>

<p>They recently added Strava integration, which sort of works. The data is all there, but for some reason the pace and moving time that Strava computes are completely off. For example, I ran 55 minutes straight with an average pace of 9 minutes / km. But with the data the watch sends, Strava thinks I only moved for 26 minutes with a pace of 4 minutes / km. If that were true, I could compete in the olympics! 😅</p>

<p><strong>Notifications barely work</strong></p>

<p>During the time I owned the watch, there was only one random day where the watch received notifications from my phone. I can&#39;t explain why, but I just didn&#39;t get this to work properly.</p>

<p><strong>Case is not screwed in. Could fall off</strong></p>

<p>This is just a minor thing if you really care about durability. All G-Shock squares so far had screwed in bezels. On this model, you can pull off the bezel with enough force. I&#39;ve never done it, but losing the bezel might be a concern.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>I enjoyed my time with this watch, but I filed a return. As pretty as the watch is, it is just too frustrating to use. Smart watches aren&#39;t a core part of Casio&#39;s business, and you can feel that in the lack of quality of the software. The app was likely developed as a one-off contract by some random agency, and once the contract ends, the watch won&#39;t ever be improved again.</p>

<p>I&#39;ve now ordered the <a href="https://www.garmin.com/de-DE/p/741462">Garmin Instinct 2S Solar</a>, which is very similar in terms of specs. MIP display, top-up solar charging, long-lasting battery and fitness features. But on top of that, it has features like music control, GPS, contactless payment and a compass. Contrary to Casio, Smartwatches are a core part of Garmin&#39;s business, which makes me believe that they go out of their way to develop the best possible watch they can. I will likely follow up with how this new watch compares to my G-Shock.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Beating Elden Ring
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-10-beating-elden-ring
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-04-10-beating-elden-ring?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p><strong>⚠️ WARNING ⚠️</strong>: This post contains a lot of spoilers for the game Elden Ring.</p></blockquote>

<p>So, I just beat Elden Ring. It took me 120 hours and, coincidentally, I was level 120 when I beat the final boss. That damn final boss... but more on that later.</p>

<p>Elden Ring won me over instantly, even though I&#39;ve never played any of the other Souls games. After beating <a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Legend_of_Zelda:_Breath_of_the_Wild">Breath of the Wild</a>, I called it my favorite game. I just needed more games like this. When Elden Ring came out, people compared The Lands Between to the open world of Hyrule, and I quickly agreed. The freedom these games give you is absolutely unbeaten. You almost never really get &quot;stuck&quot; on something. You can always wonder off and explore until you&#39;re ready to take on the fight.</p>

<p>After about 50 hours into playing Elden Ring, I kind of lost my focus and stopped playing for a while. It was too huge of a game to beat at the time, so I gave up.</p>

<p>But then, <a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Legend_of_Zelda:_Tears_of_the_Kingdom">Tears of the Kingdom</a> came out and doubled up on the world of Hyrule. I absolutely adored this game. I spent day and night playing until I finally beat it. This game also motivated me to beat Elden Ring one more time. Despite failing over and over, each play session gave me a feeling of progression. I might not have beaten a boss yet, but there was always something happening the side that got me closer to beating it. Be it exploring and getting better gear or learning as much as I can about a boss to find ways to deal damange, I always got a small step closer to my goal. I&#39;d go as far as to say I never felt so determined to reach a goal ever before in my life.</p>

<p>The boss fights in Elden Ring are obviously extremely difficult, but they&#39;re always fair. The bosses in this game never make mistakes, you&#39;re the one that screwed up. You just keep failing and failing, but with each run, you learn something new about the fight that makes it easier in the next run. And when you finally overcoming this challenge gives you a feeling of accomplishment like nothing else could.</p>

<p>What I didn&#39;t realize in the beginning of my playthough is how extremely well rounded the world and the lore of this game is. I spent days and nights indulging myself in the lore through numerous YouTube videos, guides and Wikis. Only then did I begin to understand the scale of this game. Every action of each character, every building and every item fits in the grand scheme of the world.</p>

<p>Going out of this, the biggest thing that stuck with me is the determination. Failing is part of your life, and that is okay. No matter how daunting a task is, there&#39;s <strong>always</strong> a way to overcome it. The Elden Beast is the final boss of the game, and it&#39;s also where I spent about a quarter of my playtime. This thing has absurd attacks, immense health, and did I mention that you have to beat it after beating another extremely difficult boss, without being able to top up your health? This fight is ridiculous. I spent multiple weeks trying to beat it. I was really close to giving up, but as I mentioned earlier, each run gets you a tiny bit closer to the finish line, so I pushed through. I refined my build, I leveled up my stats and I learned how to dance with the beast. Eventually, I won the fight not by luck, but by determination. I now feel like I understand every attack well enough to dodge it. My mind was on autopilot when I beat it.</p>

<p>Knowing this much about a game didn&#39;t teach me any practical skills. There&#39;s nothing I can do now that I couldn&#39;t do before I knew that Rykard (Lord of Blasphemy), son of Rennala and Radagon (also known as Queen Marika), chose to go against the Erdtree and eventually fed himself to a serpent to devour the entire world (which you prevented). But there&#39;s something about this game that left me craving for more. It&#39;s truly a masterpiece.</p>

<h2>Bonus</h2>

<p>In case you&#39;re interested, I uploaded some of the bossfights during my playthrough in this YouTube playlist:</p>

<p>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?si=j1Ue2lrrLy1JTOM9&amp;amp;list=PLS8TKBZz1x5S6ojf24SMF1h_HYb4AyTxc&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Cosmic Horror: The Festival
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-10-cosmic-horror-the-festival
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-02-10-cosmic-horror-the-festival?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 10 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&quot;The nethermost caverns are not for the fathoming of eyes that see; for their marvels are strange and terrific. Cursed the ground where dead thoughts live new and oddly bodied, and evil the mind that is held by no head.&quot;</p><p>— H.P. Lovecraft</p></blockquote>

<p>I loved reading <a href="https://www.hplovecraft.com/writings/texts/fiction/f.aspx">The Festival</a> by H.P. Lovecraft, especially this quote by &quot;the mad Arab&quot; at the end of the story. The Festival is one of Lovecrafts first short stories in the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cthulhu_Mythos">Cthulhu Mythos</a>. The quote excellently shows the unique style of Lovecrafts short stories. Each story is a grotesque depiction of horrors that are beyond our imagination. I recently tried to replicate this style of writing in  &quot;<a href="/posts/2023-09-10-short-story-haunted-memories">Haunted Memories</a>&quot;, a short story about digital media. I&#39;m just getting started with reading Lovecrafts stories, but the ones I read so far absolutely blew me away.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                2023 in Review
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-30-2023-in-review?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>That&#39;s a wrap! 2023 was an exciting year for me. I started my new role as a <a href="/posts/2023-04-22-the-role-of-a-devops-engineer">DevOps Engineer</a> at my current company, I got <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/open-source-der-patch-basierte-git-workflow-soll-bleiben-2302-171585.html">two</a> <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/wertestrom-in-devops-das-projekt-am-laufen-halten-2312-180174.html">articles</a> published on a prominent German news site and finally finished my <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a> challenge!</p>

<p>This year, I launched two projects: <a href="https://sendpasswords.net/">sendpasswords.net</a> and <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/positive_hackernews">Positive Hacker News</a>.</p>

<p>In <a href="/posts/2023-01-02-welcome-2023">last year&#39;s review</a>, I said I wanted to launch <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/fling">Fling</a>, my household management app. Fling is currently in open alpha, so you can try it out <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=de.garritfra.fling">on Android</a> or via the <a href="https://fling-list.web.app">hosted website</a> to give feedback! I&#39;m planning a public release very soon.</p>

<p>Furthermore, I wanted to launch <a href="https://docs.kubinity.com/">Kubinity</a>. This was a very ambitious project, and although it technically works, it&#39;s very hard to maintain due to high running costs, which I&#39;m not ready to pay yet.</p>

<p>I have some more drafts for projects in private repositories. One project that I&#39;m feeling comfortable to release next year is a website for the #10ShittyProjects (working title) hashtag. More on that hopefully later!</p>

<h2>Goals for 2024</h2>

<p>Here are some personal goals that I want to set myself for the upcoming year. Some of them are already defined on my <a href="/impossible">impossible list</a>.</p>

<ul><li>Build a side project that generated at least 100€ of value</li><li>Get a scuba diving license</li><li>Do a 10 km run (I really need to start moving again)</li><li>Sell my car</li><li>Write at least 50 blog posts</li></ul>

<h2>Prediction results</h2>

<p><strong>&quot;Meta will change course (again), and kill the &quot;Metaverse&quot;&quot;</strong></p>

<p>A <a href="https://labs.sogeti.com/the-metaverse-is-dead/#:~:text=The%20Real%20Promise%20of%20VR%2FAR%20Lies%20in%20Training%20Simulations&amp;text=Yet%2C%20as%20of%202023%2C%20we,Reality%20(AR)%20has%20diminished.">quick Google search</a> reveals that the metaverse as originally imagined is not dead, but it&#39;s focus shifted to a more enterprise-y approach. I must admit that this prediction was quite vague. Depending on whom you ask, the metaverse is <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schr%C3%B6dinger%27s_cat">both alive and dead at the same time</a>.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Cheap matter devices will enter the market. As a reference point: I predict that there will be a matter-ready smart plug for under 20€ on Amazon&quot;</strong></p>

<p>I found <a href="https://amzn.eu/d/iA9ZBQf">this</a> matter-enabled smart plug on Amazon for 19,54€. If this is a real product, I&#39;d say my prediction is a pass!</p>

<p><strong>&quot;AI generated content will be regulated in some way&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Also a pass! On December 9th, the European union agreed on the <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/headlines/society/20230601STO93804/eu-ai-act-first-regulation-on-artificial-intelligence">EU AI Act</a> and will now become EU law.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;Twitter is still around, but it&#39;s still not profitable&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Twitter is in fact <a href="https://www.businessofapps.com/data/twitter-statistics/#:~:text=Twitter%20generated%20%244.4%20billion%20revenue%20in%202022%2C%20a%2011%25%20decrease,a%20loss%20of%20advertising%20revenue.">still not profitable</a>. I&#39;ll leave the &quot;Twitter is still around&quot; part up for debate, as it&#39;s now called X.</p>

<p><strong>&quot;I still won&#39;t have finished my #100DaysToOffload challenge from 2021&quot;</strong></p>

<p>Wrong!! In early December, I decided to push through and whip out one post a day. I <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it">finished the challenge</a>!</p>

<h2>2024 Predictions</h2>

<ul><li>Bitcoin will at last reach a value of 100,000$, following the <a href="https://www.nicehash.com/countdown/btc-halving-2024-05-10-12-00">halving</a> likely happening in 2024</li><li>SpaceX will use a <a href="https://www.spacex.com/vehicles/starship/">Starship</a> prototype to launch Starlink satellites into orbit</li><li>Tesla cars a still not fully self driving (<a href="https://motherfrunker.ca/fsd/">reference</a>)</li><li>Google will replace their main search with an AI chat bot (see <a href="https://bard.google.com">Bard</a>)</li></ul>

<p>Let&#39;s see what 2024 brings to the table!</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Notes on "Immutability Changes Everything"
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-21-notes-on-immutability
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-21-notes-on-immutability?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Published books are immutable. Accountants don&#39;t use erasers or they go to jail.</p></blockquote>

<p>The paper <a href="https://www.cidrdb.org/cidr2015/Papers/CIDR15_Paper16.pdf">Immutability Changes Everything</a> by Pat Helland talks about the trend towards immutability in data storage thoughout all layers of the stack. From append-only apps (Record changes, then derive the current state), down to how bits are stored on a hard drive (e.g. Copy on Write).</p>

<p>I stumbled upon this paper through the <a href="https://paperswelove.org/">Papers We Love</a> collection. I was specifically looking for a paper that&#39;s short and easy to comprehend, since I don&#39;t have much experience in reading scientific papers. This is absolutely both short and easy to comprehend. If you&#39;re a beginner like me, I can highly recommend this one to you.</p>

<p>Key takeaways:</p>

<ul><li>Immutability enables clean replication</li><li>Change logs (e.g. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Write-ahead_logging">write-ahead logs</a>) are the source of truth. The database is a cache of a subset of those change logs</li><li>It&#39;s okay to consider violating <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Database_normalization">normalization</a> rules to trade storage cost for read speed</li><li>Modern SSDs minimize wear by storing new versions of data to other blocks instead of mutating the data in place</li><li>The cost of immutability is increased storage</li></ul>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 098 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Project Hail Mary
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-03-project-hail-mary
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-03-project-hail-mary?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I just finished the book <a href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Hail_Mary">Project Hail Mary</a> by Andy Weir. Rating: ⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐</p>

<p>I&#39;m completely nerdsniped. I was looking forward to each chapter, eagerly waiting for what will happen next. This book is full of completely unexpected turns, though I never felt lost. The plot is well thought out. Every chapter is like a puzzle piece that perfectly adds to the greater picture.</p>

<p>When I first heard about this book I was a bit skeptical. &quot;Human stranded in space&quot; surely can&#39;t fill some 500 pages (I&#39;m looking at you, <a href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravity_(2013_film)">Gravity</a>). But having read <a href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Martian_(Weir_novel)#">The Martian</a> some time ago, I knew that Andy Weir&#39;s style of writing would catch me. And catch me he did. The way he describes complex topics completely resonates with me. No matter how unsolvable the problems of the protagonist seem, it&#39;s always an invitation to get your mind blown by the solution.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 080 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>