<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Fri, 13 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Organizing multiple Git identities
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-13-organizing-multiple-git-identities
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-10-13-organizing-multiple-git-identities?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 13 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Here&#39;s a quick tip on how to manage multiple Git identities (e.g. personal, work, client1, client2).</p>

<p>I organize my Git repos in three levels. My personal projects live in a <code>~/sources</code> directory. All my work projects live in <code>~/work</code>. This is the first level.</p>

<p>Level 2 is the client, e.g. <code>~/work/client1</code>. Naturally, level 3 is the project repository: <code>~/work/client1/foo-api</code>.</p>

<p>This is how my work directory is organized:</p>

<p><code>
/Users/garrit/work
├── client1
│   ├── foo-api
│   ├── foo-ios
│   └── foo-android
└── client2
    ├── bar-ios
    └── bar-middleware
</code></p>

<p>Now, say that <code>client2</code> demands that we commit with a different identity than our default work email. Besides that, you probably also have a personal email address for your own projects. How do you manage that?</p>

<h2>.gitconfig includes</h2>

<p>The global configuration file for Git is <code>~/.gitconfig</code>. If you&#39;ve ever set a parameter like <code>git config user.name &quot;Foo Bar&quot;</code>: this is where it ended up.</p>

<p>One awesome feature of the .gitconfig file is that you can <strong>conditionally include other config files</strong>, and this is what does the trick. Here&#39;s my <code>~/.gitconfig</code> file:</p>

<p><code></code>`ini
[user]
    name = Garrit Franke
    email = garrit@slashdev.space</p>

<p>[includeIf &quot;gitdir:~/work/&quot;]
    path = ~/.gitconfig-work</p>

<p>[includeIf &quot;gitdir:~/work/client2/&quot;]
    path = ~/.gitconfig-client2</p>

<p>[includeIf &quot;gitdir:~/sources/&quot;]
    path = ~/.gitconfig-personal</p>

<h1>...</h1>

<p><code></code>`</p>

<p>By default, my name and email are always set to my personal identity. I also store some other global settings here, but those are not relevant for this post. If the repository is located inside the <code>~/work</code> directory, a file named <code>~/.gitconfig-work</code> is included. This is just another gitconfig file. This is what that looks like in my case:</p>

<p><code></code>`ini
[user]
    name = Garrit Franke
    signingkey = 12345678
    email = garrit@work.de</p>

<p>[commit]
    gpgsign = true
<code></code>`</p>

<p>I hope you&#39;ll see where this is going. For every identity, you keep a separate gitconfig file and include it in the main <code>~/.gitconfig</code>. Crucially, this requires you to organize your repositories grouped by client.</p>

<p>This trick has simplified my project onboarding quite a bit. No more &quot;You forgot to update your Email Address&quot; requests from clients!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 083 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                So, you want to win the lottery
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-08-23-so,-you-want-to-win-the-lottery
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-08-23-so,-you-want-to-win-the-lottery?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 23 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>The lottery is often used as a comparison for something that&#39;s far out of reach. But how far out of reach exactly is the lottery?</p>

<h2>1 in 302 Million</h2>

<p>Apparently, you have a 1 in 302 million chance to win the lottery. Well, that sounds like a lot... but how much is that exactly?</p>

<p>Imagine 66 bathtubs.</p>

<p>Now, imagine each of these bathtubs is filled to the brim with <strong>rice</strong>.</p>

<p>One of the grains of rice inside one of the bathtubs is painted gold. This is our jackpot.</p>

<p>Whenever you purchase a lottery ticket, imagine grabbing one grain of rice from this sea of bath tubs. Do you think you&#39;d have a chance to find the golden grain?</p>

<p>Source: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3Yn_3HqfV1w">The Scam No One Sees</a></p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 074 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Instant dark theme
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-12-instant-dark-theme
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-12-instant-dark-theme?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Thanks to <a href="https://jacksonchen666.com/">Jacksons</a> <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/darktheme.club/pull/79">update to darktheme.club</a>, I just came across a neat little <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/color-scheme">CSS property</a> that turns a mostly CSS-free document into a pleasantly dark site:</p>

<p><code>css
:root {
  color-scheme: light dark;
}
</code></p>

<p>This will adjust all elements on the page to the color scheme preferred by the user - without any other custom styles! 🤯 It is also <a href="https://caniuse.com/mdn-css_properties_color-scheme">widely supported</a> by browsers.</p>

<p>I&#39;ve always been quite dependent on CSS-frameworks for any project I&#39;m starting. Going forward, I&#39;d be interested to see how framework-less sites would feel using this property. If all else fails, there&#39;s always the awesome <a href="https://simplecss.org/">simple.css</a> library, which you can slap on top of a raw document to make it pretty (and dark, if preferred) without using custom classes.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 064 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                TIL about CSS Insets
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-02-19-til-about-css-insets
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-02-19-til-about-css-insets?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Just a quick tip that I thought is worth sharing. Instead of declaring:</p>

<p><code>css
.foo { 
  top: 0;
  right: 0;
  bottom: 0;
  left: 0;
}
</code></p>

<p>you can just use:</p>

<p><code>css
.foo {
  inset: 0;
}
</code></p>

<p>It&#39;s supported everywhere computers are sold!</p>

<p>MDN: https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/inset</p>

<p>Source: https://front-end.social/@estelle/109878532782943511</p>

<p>This is post 047 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Cloning Windows to a new drive
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-05-24-cloning-windows-to-a-new-drive
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-05-24-cloning-windows-to-a-new-drive?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 24 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>My grandpa has been using his current computer for about 10 years now. After
such a long time, the system has become quite slow and bulky. Back then it was
relatively normal to use a HDD as a primary hard drive, which adds to the slow
experience. It was time for an upgrade!</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>TL;DR</strong>: Use <a href="https://clonezilla.org/">Clonezilla</a> on a live usb stick to
create an exact copy of your old drive onto your new one.</p></blockquote>

<p>I got him a 512 GB SSD, which, conveniently, is the same size of his current
HDD. While installing the new drive alongside his existing one, I thought about
how to copy the existing Windows-installation.</p>

<p>Naïvely, I thought that I could just <code>dd</code> the contents of the HDD onto the new
drive would work, since, <em>every byte is copied as is</em>, or at least that&#39;s what I
thought. Turns out it wasn&#39;t that easy. I&#39;m sure it would&#39;ve worked if I was
more careful, but by default, <code>dd</code> just wipes over each byte, not caring if it
made a mistake. After very long 5 hours, I came back to the PC to see that it
finished copying the 512 GB (yes, it&#39;s not just copying the data, it&#39;s copying
the entire partition!). In a super excited mood, I restarted the PC and selected
the SSD as a boot medium. Aaaaand... nothing. Windows tried to repair some stuff
but it wasn&#39;t successful. I fiddled around with the boot partition a bit, but I
had to give up after an hour or so.</p>

<h2>The second attempt</h2>

<p>After researching a bit (I should&#39;ve done that sooner...) I stumbled across
<a href="https://clonezilla.org/">Clonezilla</a>, a Linux distribution custom-built for
this purpose. I flashed it onto a usb-stick and started the cloning process.
After just 20 minutes (!), it was done cloning the existing data. The process is
extremely simple!</p>

<p>Before rebooting, I disconnected the old drive to make sure that there&#39;s no
funny business going on. Apparently, Windows had to self-adjust UIDs of the
drives, but after a short &quot;Preparing Windows&quot; animation, the system started up
as expected. <strong>Success</strong>!!</p>

<p>The performance of the new hard drive is amazing, at least compared to the HDD
my grandpa had before. Plus, we can use the existing HDD to take full system
backups every now and then, using the same process.</p>

<p>This is post 031 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                TIL how to get the active language of a browser
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-01-28-til-how-to-get-the-selected-language-of-a-browser
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-01-28-til-how-to-get-the-selected-language-of-a-browser?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Today I learned how to get the selected language of a browser.</p>

<p>It&#39;s super simple!</p>

<p><code>js
const userLang = navigator.language || navigator.userLanguage;
</code></p>

<h2>An interesting discovery</h2>

<p>Eventhough I&#39;m using a chromium-based browser, the user-agent and some other
fields of the <code>navigator</code> object imply that I&#39;m running Mozilla Netscape 5.0.
This is a relic of the past, where the user agent heavily influenced the look
and feel of a served website. Nowadays, all rendering engines work more or less
equally, but back then, browsers tried to be as good as the market leader, so
they disquised themselves as Netscape. This podcast episode goes into more
detail about how this developed (jump to minute 3 to listen to this topic):</p>

<p>&lt;iframe style=&quot;border-radius:12px&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/71URVFdhF6pcUBRhxerDIV?utm_source=generator&amp;t=190&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;232&quot; frameBorder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 024 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>

<h2>Resources</h2>

<ul><li><a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/8199760/how-to-get-the-browser-language-using-javascript">Stack Overflow Thread on getting the user language</a></li><li><a href="https://corecursive.com/internet-is-duct-tape/#">Full link to the Podcast episode</a></li></ul>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>