<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                A fix for long-pressing movement keys in VSCode with Vim-Mode
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2026-02-04-a-fix-for-long-pressing-movement-keys-in-vscode-with-vim-mode
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2026-02-04-a-fix-for-long-pressing-movement-keys-in-vscode-with-vim-mode?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<h2>The Setup</h2>

<ul><li>MacOS</li><li>VSCode</li><li>Vim Extension</li></ul>

<h2>The Issue</h2>

<p>Long-pressing <code>j</code> or <code>k</code> (think &quot;down&quot; or &quot;up&quot; in Vim) only results in one down or up action, instead of continuous scrolling.</p>

<h2>The Fix</h2>

<p>In a terminal, run the following command:</p>

<p><code>
defaults write com.microsoft.VSCode ApplePressAndHoldEnabled -bool false
</code></p>

<p>Original post: https://stackoverflow.com/a/44010683</p>

<h2>Additional tip</h2>

<p>In the MacOS settings, set &quot;Key Repeat Rate&quot; and &quot;Delay Until Repeat&quot; to the highest setting to be able to scroll much faster.</p>

<p>&lt;img width=&quot;478&quot; height=&quot;92&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; src=&quot;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/7bf85853-377d-4727-a5c8-2766f2794e8a&quot; /&gt;</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Strategies to use a terminal alongside (Neo)Vim
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-02-24-vim-terminal-strategies
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-02-24-vim-terminal-strategies?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>One thing that bothered me about vim for a long time, was the lack of a terminal
directly in your editor. If I&#39;m not using Vim, I&#39;m most definetely using VSCode
and its built-in Terminal. After searching the webs for possible solutions, I
came across a couple of strategies to achive this.</p>

<h2>Executing single commands</h2>

<p>If you just want to issue a single command without spawning an entire shell,
you can just use the <code>:!</code> command:</p>

<p><code>
:! printf &quot;Hello Sailor&quot;
</code></p>

<h2>Vims builtin terminal</h2>

<p>I couldn&#39;t believe my eyes when I read this, but Vim ships with a builtin
terminal! Executing <code>:term</code> will spawn it in your current buffer. How you
integrate it in your workflow is up to you. You could use tabs or open a
horizontal buffer and spawn it there. I must say that it is rather clunky to
use, since its literally a Vim buffer that forwards stdin and stdout to the
buffer, but it&#39;s there for you to use.</p>

<h2>Vim x Tmux</h2>

<p>Another great alternative is to set up Tmux with two windows, one for Vim and
one for your terminal, and switch between them. This works great on a minimal
system, but on MacOS for example, it is easier to simply use cmd+1 and cmd+2 to
switch between two tabs of the Terminal application.</p>

<h2>Pausing and resuming Vim</h2>

<p>This one is my personal favorite. The idea comes from
<a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/1258318/9046809">this</a> stackoverflow answer.</p>

<p>The plan is to pause the Vim process and resume it later. To pause Vim, you
press <code>&lt;ctrl&gt;-z</code>. This sends the process in the background. Then, to resume the
process, simply issue the <code>fg</code> command and Vims process resumes in the
foreground.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I&#39;m sure there are many more strategies that could be added to this list. I&#39;d be
interested to hear how your setup works! If you liked these techniques, you
might be interested in
<a href="https://fosstodon.org/web/accounts/211905">@lopeztel</a>s
<a href="https://lopeztel.xyz/2021/02/21/my-neovim-cheatsheet/">cheat sheet</a> for Vim.</p>

<p>This is post 014 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Using Macros in Vim
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-01-26-vim-macros
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-01-26-vim-macros?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 26 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>For a long time, macros in Vim were a huge mystery for me. I knew they existed, but I didn&#39;t know how or why you&#39;d use them. A recent task of mine involved replacing the unsafe operator (<code>!!</code>) in a large kotlin codebase with a null-safe operator (<code>?</code>). This game me a good opportunity to learn about macros. This is a snippet I encountered numerous times:</p>

<p><code>kt
mLeftButton!!.text = &quot;Left&quot;
mLeftButton!!.setOnClickListener(leftListener)
mLeftButton!!.visibility = View.VISIBLE
mRightButton!!.text = &quot;Right&quot;
mRightButton!!.setOnClickListener(rightListener)
mRightButton!!.visibility = View.VISIBLE
</code></p>

<p>You could go ahead and change each line individually, or use the IDEs built in &quot;multi-cursor&quot; tool to save you some work. But, let me show you how I automated this using a Vim-Plugin for Android Studio. Not that the plugin matter, it will work in every Vim-like editor.</p>

<p>A macro in Vim works like this:</p>

<ol><li>Record any sequence of keystrokes and assign them to a key</li><li>Execute that sequence as often as you wish</li></ol>

<p>So let&#39;s see how we&#39;d do that.</p>

<h2>Recording a macro</h2>

<p>To record a macro in Vim, you press <code>q</code> (In normal mode) followed by a key you want to assign the macro to. So, if you wanted to record a macro and save it to the <code>q</code> key, you&#39;d press <code>qq</code>. Vim will notify you that a macro is being recorded. Now, you can press the keystrokes that define your actions. When you&#39;re done, press <code>q</code> in normal mode again to quit your macro.</p>

<p>Coming back to my task, I would want to do the following:</p>

<ol><li><code>qq</code> Record a macro and save it to the <code>q</code> key</li><li><code>_</code> - Jump to the beginning of the line</li><li><code>f!</code> - Find next occurrence of <code>!</code></li><li><code>cw</code> - Change word (Delete word and enter insert mode)</li><li><code>?.</code> - Insert the new characters</li><li><code>&lt;esc&gt;</code> - Enter normal mode</li><li><code>j</code> - go down a line</li><li><code>q</code> - Finish macro</li></ol>

<p>If everything went right, this line:</p>

<p><code>
mLeftButton!!.text = &quot;Left&quot;
</code></p>

<p>Should now look like this:</p>

<p><code>
mLeftButton?.text = &quot;Left&quot;
</code></p>

<p>and your macro should be saved under the <code>q</code> key.</p>

<h2>Using the macro</h2>

<p>In order to use a macro in vim, you press the <code>@</code> key, followed by the key the macro is saved under. Since our macro is defined as <code>q</code>, we&#39;d press <code>@q</code>, and the macro is executed immediately.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s take this further. You might have noticed that I went down a line before closing the macro. This becomes handy when you want to execute it many times. In our case we have 6 lines we want to refactor. 1 line has already been altered, so we have to execute it 5 more times. As per usual with vim, you can execute an action n times by specifying a number before doing the action. Let&#39;s press <code>5@q</code> to execute the macro 5 times. And voila! Our unsafe code is now null-safe.</p>

<p><code>kt
mLeftButton?.text = &quot;Left&quot;
mLeftButton?.setOnClickListener(leftListener)
mLeftButton?.visibility = View.VISIBLE
mRightButton?.text = &quot;Right&quot;
mRightButton?.setOnClickListener(rightListener)
mRightButton?.visibility = View.VISIBLE
</code></p>

<p>Macros are really satisfying to watch, if you ask me!</p>

<p>This is post 007 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>