<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Fri, 06 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Weeknote 18/2022
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-05-06-weeknote-18-2022
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-05-06-weeknote-18-2022?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 06 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>It&#39;s friday, my dudes! Here are some notes on what happened during my week.</p>

<h2>At Work</h2>

<p>I wanted to start off my week by looking into migrating our deployment workflow
to a GitLab Agent, as described <a href="/posts/2022-04-29-weeknote-17-2022">last week</a>.
That didn&#39;t really go well, since a database from another project bursted into
flames (not literally) for a reason I still couldn&#39;t figure out. As a
workaround, I just beefed up the AWS RDS instance size until we find a proper
solution.</p>

<p>While looking through the docs, I also read more about <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/de/rds/aurora/serverless/">Aurora
Serverless</a>, which would be a
match made in heaven, at least for this specific project. Instead of keeping
multiple instances running even without any load, serverless automatically
scales to as many resources as you need. This <strong>drastically</strong> improves
performance (according to the docs it&#39;s instantaneous, but I&#39;ll have to see that
with my own eyes), while keeping the price at a minimum. Once we&#39;re done with
that migration, I&#39;ll probably follow up with a blog post on this.</p>

<h2>Home Automation</h2>

<p>We recently wanted to configure a light in our bedroom to turn on early and the
morning, stay on for a few hours and then turn off. Same for the evening.</p>

<p>Soo, I ordered two power plugs pre-flashed with
<a href="https://tasmota.github.io/docs/">Tasmota</a> and yanked HomeAssistant onto an old
Pi. The plugs came as a pair, so I automated another light in our home. I think
this will be the beginning of a deep deep rabbit hole.</p>

<p>We&#39;ll be moving to a new flat soon, where humidity is higher than usual. I&#39;m
thinking to monitor this and react with some counter-measures, like air filters.
Sky is the limit, really. More to follow...</p>

<h2>Motorbike Maintenance</h2>

<p>I was long due to dust off my motorbike, but I finally did. Also, I did my first
oil change on a vehicle <strong>ever</strong>!</p>

<p><img alt="Motorbike oil change" src="/assets/posts/2022-05-06-weeknote-18-2022/motorbike_oil_change.jpeg"/></p>

<p>Feels great to finally be back on the road.</p>

<h2>Fun Fun Fun</h2>

<p>Besides riding my motorbike, we went to a fair in our town. It was the first
time in years that I&#39;ve been to a fair, and to ride bumper cars.</p>

<p>Also, I met up with a friend I haven&#39;t seen in a while. It was great taking a
walk and talking about life.</p>

<p>That&#39;s it for this week. Thanks for reading!</p>

<p>This is post 030 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Weeknote 17/2022
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-04-29-weeknote-17-2022
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-04-29-weeknote-17-2022?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 29 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This week was quite ordinary. We enjoyed the weather during walks in the park
and got some chores done.</p>

<h2>At work</h2>

<p>A major news this week was that GitLab decided to remove <a href="https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/clusters/deploy_to_cluster.html#deploy-to-a-kubernetes-cluster-with-cluster-certificates-deprecated">certificate-based
cluster
access</a>
to Kubernetes clusters sooner as we hoped. We&#39;re now fleshing out how to migrate
to the newer
<a href="https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/clusters/agent/install/index.html">gitlab-agent</a>.</p>

<p>I also got some refactoring work done. In one of our projects, we&#39;re currently
migrating our GraphQL queries away from a HOC-pattern towards React hooks, using
the amazing
<a href="https://github.com/appmotion/apollo-augmented-hooks">apollo-augmented-hooks</a>
library for additional caching features.</p>

<h2>Sideprojects</h2>

<p>I continued to work on a secret side-project of mine, but I don&#39;t want to spoil
anything just yet.</p>

<p>BUT! If you&#39;re good at writing and would like to help out writing a couple of
paragraphs that can catch the users attention, <a href="/contact">I&#39;d love to hear from
you</a>.</p>

<p>That&#39;s it for this week. Thanks for reading!</p>

<p>This is post 029 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Weeknote 16/2022
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-04-25-weeknote-16-2022
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2022-04-25-weeknote-16-2022?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Mon, 25 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This is my first (already belated) weeknote. Even though it&#39;s the monday of the
next week, I thought I&#39;d reflect on what happened last week. I already tried <a href="/posts/2020-12-18-update-december">a
similar format</a> on this blog in a monthly
fashion, but didn&#39;t stick to it. With these &quot;weeknotes&quot;, I will try to sit down
for half an hour each friday. This is heavily inspired by <a href="https://dougbelshaw.com/blog/">Doug Belshaw&#39;s posts
with the same name</a>.</p>

<h2>At work</h2>

<p>There&#39;s currently an effort to integrate a whole new backend into our
application. Fundamental features like user- and role-management will have to be
migrated to this new backend, which is mostly incompatible with our current
one. As I&#39;m currently the only developer on the project, building a concept
and realizing it will mostly be my part. I&#39;m somewhat frightened about this
undertaking, but I think I will learn a whole lot.</p>

<p>I also introduced versioned deployments for our application. To keep it simple,
releases are versioned by date (E.g. <code>v2022.04.21</code>). Alongside this, I also
added a changelog describing each release. I&#39;m still unsure whether this gives
us a benefit or if it&#39;s just unnecessary work, but time will tell. I&#39;m curious
of what you - the reader - thinks of this. Feel free to reply to this post via
the link at the bottom of the page.</p>

<h2>On this blog</h2>

<p>I&#39;m playing around with ideas about comments on this static website. I yanked
out some thoughts in this thread, but I&#39;ll have to think about it a bit more:</p>

<p>&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://fosstodon.org/@garritfra/108180821665987615/embed&quot;
class=&quot;mastodon-embed&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border: 0; height: 21rem&quot; width=&quot;400&quot;
allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;script
src=&quot;https://fosstodon.org/embed.js&quot; async=&quot;async&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</p>

<h2>Plants</h2>

<p>My girlfriend and I are in love with plants. This week, we went to a nursery and
got ourselves a new member to our family: a Monstera Adansonii.</p>

<p><img alt="Monstera Adansonii" src="/assets/monstera_adansonii.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I also did a little experiment with one of my eucalyptus citriodoras. I cut it
from 50cm back to the first &quot;node&quot; in the trunk, at about 2cm. I&#39;m quite happy
with how it evolved in just about 10 months. It&#39;s now time to develop some
branches. Here&#39;s it before the pruning:</p>

<p><img alt="Eucalyptus before pruning" src="/assets/eucalyptus_before_pruning.jpeg"/></p>

<p>And this is what it looks like now:</p>

<p><img alt="Eucalyptus after pruning" src="/assets/eucalyptus_after_pruning.jpeg"/></p>

<p>I also made cuttings from the rest of the stem. Not sure if they&#39;ll survive, but
what could I lose?</p>

<p>That&#39;s it for this week. Thanks for reading!</p>

<p>This is post 027 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>