<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>
            garrit.xyz
        </title>
        <link>
            https://garrit.xyz
        </link>
        <description>
            Garrit Franke
        </description>
        <language>
            en
        </language>
        <lastBuildDate>
            Fri, 05 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
        </lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>
                Greg, the Developer
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Fri, 05 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This is Greg. Greg loves to play with his computer and create amazing things.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg.svg"/></p>

<p>Greg has many friends. He listens to his friends and helps them. Greg knows that teamwork is very important.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg and his friends" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-friends.svg"/></p>

<p>Greg is curious about what his friends do. Greg learned how they help everyone create amazing things. Greg was happy that he learned something new.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg learns from his friends" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-learning.svg"/></p>

<p>One day, Greg has an idea. Greg shares his idea with his friends. They try it, and it works! Everyone is happy that Greg shared his idea.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg has an idea" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-idea.svg"/></p>

<p>When Greg learns something new about computers, he writes it down and shows it to his friends. This helps everyone learn how computers work.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg writes down what he learned" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-documentation.svg"/></p>

<p>Sometimes Greg and his friends make a mistake, but Greg knows that&#39;s okay. Everyone makes mistakes, even Greg. He says that everyone can learn from mistakes. This makes them better and happier.</p>

<p><img alt="It&#39;s okay to make mistakes" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-mistake.svg"/></p>

<p>Greg is a good software developer. Be like Greg.</p>

<p><img alt="Greg is a good software developer" src="/assets/posts/2024-01-05-greg-the-developer/greg-okay.svg"/></p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                #100DaysToOffload: I made it!
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-23-100daystooffload-i-made-it?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 23 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>This marks post 100 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com">#100DaysToOffload</a>. These last couple of days, I&#39;ve been sprinting towards the finish line with one post every day to finish the challenge until the end of the year. And I finally made it!</p>

<p>I started this challenge with <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2021-01-11-100daystooffload">this</a> post on January 11th, 2021, which means it took me almost three full years to finish it. The original challenge was to write 100 posts in <strong>one</strong> year, so I&#39;m way overdue. 😅 But that doesn&#39;t make me less proud to finish it!</p>

<p>If you&#39;re interested, you can find the list of all 100 of my posts <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts?tags=100DaysToOffload">here</a>.</p>

<h2>What I learned</h2>

<p>Before starting this challenge, I sometimes struggled with putting out content on this blog. It felt like each post had to be perfect, and if it wasn&#39;t, I was scared to publish it.</p>

<p>The idea of #100DaysToOffload is to let go of this fear and <em>Just. Write.</em> This absolutely worked. I accepted the fact that not every post is perfect and <a href="https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity">sometimes posting more often with worse quality makes way for better posts</a>.</p>

<p>In order to post more often, I also found ways to reduce the friction between me writing a text and publishing it to the blog. I&#39;ve yet to cover this in a post, but I built myself <a href="https://github.com/garritfra/garrit.xyz/blob/main/.github/workflows/publish_via_issue.yaml">a handy script</a> that turns the contents of a GitHub issue into a pull request, ready to be merged as a blog post. This enables me to write posts everywhere I want (like the one right now, which is written on my phone), instead of having to open my laptop, create a new file, write the post and commit it to the repository.</p>

<h2>What&#39;s next?</h2>

<p>I will continue posting when I feel like it! I set myself the goal to publish at least 50 posts a year, but that&#39;s just a rough estimate. If I don&#39;t feel like blogging, I won&#39;t force myself to do it.</p>

<p>All in all, I&#39;m very thankful for having taken part in this challenge. I met <a href="https://kevquirk.com/">a</a> <a href="https://joelchrono.xyz/">bunch</a> <a href="https://claytonerrington.com/">of</a> <a href="https://dougbelshaw.com/">like-minded</a> <a href="https://jlelse.blog/">folks</a> that are happy to discuss whatever I&#39;m rambling about, and it&#39;s great to read whatever they are rambling about as well! I&#39;m also thankful for all the nuggets of information I got to share with you, and also with my future self (seriously, you won&#39;t believe how often I&#39;m looking up old posts and being happy that I wrote that down!).</p>

<p>Thanks for reading, until next time!</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 100 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Roast my Site!
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-12-12-roast-my-site?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Tue, 12 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>Let&#39;s try something: <code>#RoastMySite</code>!</p>

<p>I want to hear your honest feedback about my website. (Not so) constructive criticism, funny bug reports and savage burns. 🔥</p>

<p><a href="/contact">Shoot me a mail</a> with your roast and I&#39;ll include it on this site!</p>

<p>Got your own site? I&#39;ll roast it! Just ping me via mail or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@garritfra">on Mastodon</a>.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 093 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Short Story: Haunted Memories
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-10-short-story-haunted-memories
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-09-10-short-story-haunted-memories?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 10 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>I had ventured deep into the heart of the forest that day, my heart alive with the joy of nature&#39;s embrace. The woods had called to me, and I, unwary of what lay ahead, had answered.</p>

<p>Beneath the green canopy, in the soft sunlight, I had walked along ancient trails, watched leaves fall to the forest floor, and breathed in the earthy scent of life. The sound of rustling leaves and chattering birds filled the air, and I wanted to capture these moments with my little device.</p>

<p>My phone, the recorder of my adventure, was like an extra eye. Every twisty tree and glistening stream, every play of light on a dewy leaf, I kept them all in digital form. It was my way of keeping a piece of nature&#39;s beauty.</p>

<p>When I got back home, I found myself alone, sitting in my comfy chair. I gazed at the screen, filled with memories of the day. Each swipe revealed a collection of images: the old trees, the winding paths, and the sun playing with the leaves. It was a familiar ritual, going through the day&#39;s photos.</p>

<p>Little did I know that this simple act would reveal a story of strange and unsettling things. As I looked at the pictures, the happy memories started to change. The forest seemed to hide something old and dark.</p>

<p>Amidst the familiar snapshots of trees and trails, one photo stood out, like a misplaced puzzle piece. I stared at it in confusion, for I had no memory of capturing this image. It was a peculiar blur, a distortion in the nature of my otherwise ordinary pictures.</p>

<p>As I swiped to the next image, I hoped to dismiss this oddity as a simple mistake. But with each passing second, my heart sank. The forest in the next photo, while clearly the same place, looked nothing like the serene woods I had hiked through earlier. This picture showed a twisted, distorted version of reality. The colors were dim, the trees bent in unnatural ways, and the sky turned an eerie shade of crimson. It felt like the world had shifted, and a creeping sense of fear washed over me.</p>

<p>My thumb swiped to the next image, my curiosity piqued and anxiety started manifesting at my insides. What I saw next sent a chill down my spine. The distortion had spread, like a creeping darkness, and it now shrouded the entire frame. The forest in the photo seemed to reveal an uncanny life of its own, as if it held secrets it had never intended to surface. The more I delved, the more my phone&#39;s screen seemed to protest, flickering and stuttering in its struggle to depict the incomprehensible. It was as if the very device I held in my shaky hand recoiled from the horrors unveiled, a witness to the sinister unraveling of a twisted reality.</p>

<p>With a shiver in my spine, I continued my descent into this abyss of photos. Each one was a descent deeper into the uncanny, the forest growing more distorted and nightmarish with every passing image. The very air seemed to grow heavy, pressing down on me, as if the forest itself disapproved of my presence.</p>

<p>My phone, now a reluctant accomplice in this unfolding nightmare, grew hotter with every image, as though its circuits strained to contain the eldritch force invading its digital realm. The terror I felt mirrored in the device&#39;s erratic behavior, a momentary dance of dread and malfunction that whispered of a cruel intelligence lurking just beyond the frame.</p>

<p>As the seconds turned into minutes, my heart raced. One last photo showed the forest in complete disarray, and there, amidst the chaos of the twisted woods, a formless void seemed to coalesce, lurking in the background.</p>

<p>This indescribable entity defied the very essence of reality. It was a shadowy figure, a blot upon the photograph that should not have been. Its proportions, though vaguely human, were maddeningly incomprehensible. The creature, if it could be called that, emitted an aura of profound wrongness, as though it were a fracture in the very essence of existence.</p>

<p>It lacked eyes, for it existed beyond the realm of vision, yet it gazed into the depths of my soul. Its presence was an disgrace to the senses, an intrusion into the harmony of the natural world. It was a thing of pure darkness, an incarnation of the void, and it appeared to call forth from the fringes of my comprehension, as if tempting me to explore its mystifying abyss.</p>

<p>My phone, seemingly unable to bear the weight of the strange, otherworldly images, emitted an unsettling, high-pitched whine. Extreme heat radiated from the device, and before I could react, it swelled and erupted into a burst of searing smoke, leaving nothing but a charred and twisted shell.</p>

<p>I was left paralyzed, my mind reeling with a terror beyond description. And as the acrid scent of burnt electronics hung in the air, I couldn&#39;t help but glance up, for I felt a presence, an impenetrable darkness, looming before me. It was as though the forest itself had birthed this malevolent entity, and it was now here, before my very eyes.</p>

<p>What happened next, I cannot say. Years have passed, and my memory remains shrouded in mystery, offering no answers. But one thing is certain: that unholy encounter left me forever changed, and I swore off digital devices, for fear of stirring the terrors that lurk beyond the screen.</p>

<p>From that day forward, I embraced nature with renewed compassion, still drawn to the inspiration of the woods. But I chose a different path for documenting my adventures, one free from the digital terror that had haunted me. A trusty notebook and an old ink pen became my companions, capturing the essence of my journeys as I ventured deeper into the heart of the wild. My hikes remained a source of clarity and inspiration, and through the ink-stained pages of my journal, I chronicled the world&#39;s beauty and wonder, preserving memories in the tangible, uncorrupted form of the analog.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: The characters and events portrayed in this story are entirely fictional. Any resemblance to real individuals, living or deceased, or to actual events is purely coincidental. Furthermore, portions of this story were developed with the assistance of artificial intelligence (AI) to enhance storytelling and brainstorm ideas.</p></blockquote>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 076 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>
                Quality vs. Quantity
            </title>
            <guid>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity
            </guid>
            <link>
                https://garrit.xyz/posts/2023-04-01-quality-vs.-quantity?utm_source=rss
            </link>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
            <description>
                <![CDATA[<p>The amount and quality of the posts on this blog strongly depends on my mood. Some times I want to write about every thought that crosses my mind, leading to 4+ average- to low-quality posts a week. I think I&#39;m in one of these phases right now.</p>

<p>Some other times, I feel like most of my thoughts are not worth the effort to write about, but the ones that I <strong>do</strong> write about, often become the ones that I&#39;m <a href="/posts/2021-04-07-pgp-guide">most</a> <a href="/posts/2021-10-04-server-side-caching-with-apollo-graphql">proud</a> <a href="/posts/2021-01-18-reasons-the-fediverse-is-better">of</a>.</p>

<p>These phases act like opposing forces that coexist very well. Pumping out more thoughts of lesser quality frees up my mind for higher quality ones, and when I&#39;m writing about higher quality thoughts, I get the urge to write more often, completing the circuit.</p>

<p>In the end, it&#39;s not about <strong>what</strong> you write about, but about the process of writing itself. Every post on a personal blog is <a href="https://kevquirk.com/thoughts-on-editing-posts/">a snapshot of your thoughts at a point in time</a>, no matter if you&#39;re feeling qualitative or quantitative.</p>

<hr/>

<p>This is post 062 of <a href="https://100daystooffload.com/">#100DaysToOffload</a>.</p>]]>
            </description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>